<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Literature Geek</title>
    <description>smarter online communities via digital humanities</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sat, 24 Nov 2018 15:37:28 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 24 Nov 2018 15:37:28 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.4.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>I/O: Reading &amp; writing as a digital humanist</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently collaborated with my awesome colleagues Ammon Shepherd and Brandon Walsh &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/i-o-reading-writing-as-a-digital-humanist/&quot;&gt;to self-interview&lt;/a&gt; about how we read and write as digital humanists, e.g. how our PhD program experiences changed where and how often we read. I’ve included my answers below, but please do check out &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/i-o-reading-writing-as-a-digital-humanist/&quot;&gt;the whole post&lt;/a&gt; to read Brandon and Ammon’s thoughts and see the variety (and some interesting similarities: fewer print books!) among three digital humanists growing in alternative academic careers in libraries after humanities doctoral research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-has-your-reading-style-changed-over-the-years&quot;&gt;How has your reading style changed over the years?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/i-o-reading-writing-as-a-digital-humanist/&quot;&gt;Brandon writes&lt;/a&gt;, reading for literature comps (&lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/assets/ExamsSharingCopy.pdf&quot;&gt;here’s my reading list and rationale!&lt;/a&gt;) changed my relationship to reading, but in an ultimately good way—I pay a lot more attention to whether I’m enjoying and challenged and learning from something I’m reading now, and am better at just stopping reading when those things aren’t happening. There was never enough time to read, during the first three years of my PhD program—I always was racing to get through the pages, and didn’t have enough time to reflect, or to move through readings non-linearly. I worried about being questioned about some random concept on page 180, rather than getting a sense of some of a book’s arguments and what &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; thought about them. And I felt like I needed to Know Things, that I needed to have read X thinkers on Y authors to be a functional scholar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(My mentors in grad school were &lt;em&gt;amazing&lt;/em&gt;, and to their credit none of these pressures came from them. Rather, I was seeing how other students were working and figuring out what being a scholar meant to me. I remember Melanie Kill recommending I use exams prep to figure out how I want to manage the reading part of being a scholar, before starting the first big project of the dissertation. Her advice rewrote my initial floundering with how to usefully ingest a lot of texts into something expected and welcomed.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I basically don’t read any books or print journal articles anymore. I’ve gotten off most (all?) listservs. I’m not any less of a scholar for delimiting my reading to other formats. Folks who do all or some of their reading via these formats are real scholars, too. How, when, and where you read are personal choices. There is a lot of writing and discussing out there, no one can read more of it, and it’s completely fine and intellectually responsible to delimit the formats and topics you’re going to read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scholarship doesn’t come from restricting the ways you take in new ideas; scholarship is challenging yourself to think hard and share that thinking so others can learn from and build on it (a re-articulation of Mark Sample’s great “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.samplereality.com/2013/02/08/when-does-service-become-scholarship/&quot;&gt;When does service become scholarship?&lt;/a&gt;“). And I guess I do extrapolate some best practices from that definition of scholarship, like representative and accurate citation being necessary for scholarship to &lt;em&gt;work&lt;/em&gt; (e.g. see &lt;a href=&quot;http://saranahmed/&quot;&gt;Sara Ahmed&lt;/a&gt;‘s articulation of citation as a black feminist practice). You can’t share your thinking well if you don’t say whose work you’re building on and how, and contribute to the community’s knowledge of other thinkers to learn from in addition to your thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-do-your-reading-inputs-connect-with-writingoutputs&quot;&gt;How do your reading inputs connect with writing/outputs?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My reading nowadays largely consists of: blog posts, tweets and Twitter conversations, attending conference and event talks (or reading transcripts afterward), talking/Slacking/emailing with people. For Slack, we’ve got an active Scholars’ Lab internal Slack for our staff and students, I love the &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/1Wk0JdF2Cty2VHMqpf_QlJXVKQdUtfeeFhaYRben3qaM/viewform&quot;&gt;Documenting the Now Slack&lt;/a&gt; for generous and smart thinking about the ethics of archives (particularly archiving and doing research with social media), and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://tinyurl.com/DHSlack&quot;&gt;DH Slack&lt;/a&gt; (which I’ve been posting to less lately, but still enjoying reading). Sometimes the blog posts or tweet link to digital projects or online journal articles that I read, but the “next” books on my work to-read list have been the same ones for what feels like a year, and I’m not getting to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve moved away from bookmarking stuff that I think I ought to read, and am only bookmarking things I think I’m likely to read soon, and that will impact my work (change or improve how I think or talk or listen). Having a huge backlog of “should reads” can make me feel behind, or like I’m slogging through processing text for reasons other than my own. I’d rather not have too much stuff on the backburner, and take longer thinking about the stuff I do read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes it’s physically small pieces of reading that have a large impact on my writing, like this &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/elikaortega/status/618097310505938944&quot;&gt;tweet&lt;/a&gt; by Élika Ortega, that rewrites the popular focus on “What is DH?” to instead ask “What can DH be?” That tweet—and &lt;a href=&quot;https://elikaortega.net/&quot;&gt;her work&lt;/a&gt; living that shift—plus Stewart Varner’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://stewartvarner.com/2016/01/what-dh-could-be/&quot;&gt;building on&lt;/a&gt; Élika’s thinking, all encouraged me to take more personal agency in my scholarly community. Rather than just imagining what I’d like DH to become as a field, I started looking at how the tiny snowflake of &lt;em&gt;my&lt;/em&gt; scholarly choices contributes to what the field becomes. For example, &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2014/05/27/inclusivityeditioncanon&quot;&gt;I’d thought&lt;/a&gt; I was okay with my dissertation creating yet another edition of a canon white male author, and I don’t think I’d argue the same today. That is not a comment on what anyone else should study—I just found that a shift in my thinking about the field of DH accompanied a shift in scholarly topics and formats. This is all to say that something as un-book-like as a tweet can cause a profound shift in someone’s scholarly career, and influence various kinds of future scholarship (including, in this instance, blogs posts, research projects, and keynotes).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Élika’s tweet (arising from the #WhatIfDH2016 etc. hashtags) made a huge impact, but Twitter’s been significant for my scholarship in subtler ways as well. I’ve learned to be a better scholar and person from Twitter exposing me to new ideas, or ideas I didn’t take seriously enough. It is wrong that I’m able to get so much from a platform that is actively unsafe for many of my peers to use. Some of my more recent scholarship has been a reaction to this: what features and feeling would an ideal academic virtual community have; what good virtual academic communities already exist, and whether there’s even a need for alternative technical platforms to assist with addressing social issues; and how we can better structure the work of community-building and moderation that helps such communities thrive (particular interests: more equitable distribution of the labor and stress of moderation, and recognition and reward for this work as scholarship).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-do-you-wish-you-did-differently-what-do-you-want-to-try&quot;&gt;What do you wish you did differently? What do you want to try?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d like to get back to blogging a couple of times a month. I’ve got a large backlog of drafts, including a series on designing DH infrastructure from my previous role at Purdue—I’d like to post those, and to continue to make infrastructural documents and decisions from my role in the Scholars’ Lab public, like the work of structuring our new job openings equitably and drafting job ads to match (&lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/announcements/job-opening-developer-outreach-testing-coordinator/&quot;&gt;one example&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/announcements/job-opening-curious-about-focusing-on-dh-development/&quot;&gt;another example&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also want to experiment further with my blogging voice. I’m interested in making public the pieces of scholarship that get “published” less often, whether that’s things like hiring that we don’t share to the detriment of the diversity of our community (e.g. folks sharing the text of their successful job talks—&lt;a href=&quot;http://readywriting.org/uncategorized/faculty-development-for-the-21st-century-and-beyond/&quot;&gt;Lee Skallerup Bessette&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://celestesharpe.com/onward/&quot;&gt;Celeste Tuong Vy Sharpe&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://chrisbourg.wordpress.com/2015/07/12/infrastructure-and-culture-a-job-talk/&quot;&gt;Chris Bourg&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/in-out-across-with-collaborative-education-and-digital-humanities-job-talk-for-head-of-graduate-programs/&quot;&gt;Brandon Walsh&lt;/a&gt;, as well as my &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/disrupt-the-humanities-managing-director-job-talk/&quot;&gt;Scholars’ Lab&lt;/a&gt; and previous &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2016/02/28/DHjobtalk&quot;&gt;Purdue job talk&lt;/a&gt;s), or what the daily scholarly practices look like that eventually result in a book or website (e.g. the software they use to make daily progress on &lt;a href=&quot;https://mkirschenbaum.wordpress.com/2012/08/15/on-tradecraft-and-track-changes/&quot;&gt;writing a book&lt;/a&gt;), or some small technical thing I figured out (e.g. automating screenshots of my liked tweets for personal Morale Boosting; post coming… soon?). And I’m proud of my &lt;em&gt;Programming Historian&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://programminghistorian.org/en/lessons/building-static-sites-with-jekyll-github-pages&quot;&gt;lesson&lt;/a&gt;, which I tried to write with kindness and thorough explanation of non-obvious technical stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I also love to read digital writing that is thoughtful in a different way about language and structure. I think I’ve had “write something that makes me feel excited about scholarship the way &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/nowviskie&quot;&gt;Bethany Nowviskie&lt;/a&gt;‘s &lt;a href=&quot;http://nowviskie.org/&quot;&gt;blog posts&lt;/a&gt; make me feel” as a goal for years now. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/walshbr&quot;&gt;Brandon&lt;/a&gt; recently shared &lt;a href=&quot;http://walshbr.com/blog/praxis-and-scale-on-the-virtue-of-small/&quot;&gt;some of his writing&lt;/a&gt; that made me similarly really excited about work, and reminded me that I want to try similarly structuring some of my own thoughts. I think more attention to language and structure could help me here, but I’m also realizing that a difference between many of my blog posts and these digital essays I admire, is that they argue in a generative way much of my writing doesn’t. Some things I’d like to experiment with emulating and building on: Bethany’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://nowviskie.org/2014/anthropocene/&quot;&gt;lyrical force&lt;/a&gt;, Brandon’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://walshbr.com/blog/praxis-and-scale-on-the-virtue-of-small/&quot;&gt;clarity&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/digiwonk&quot;&gt;Aimée Morrison&lt;/a&gt;‘s life-giving affirmation of &lt;a href=&quot;https://hookandeye.ca/2018/02/21/i-did-it-myyyyyyy-waaaaay-and-you-should-too/&quot;&gt;scholars’ brains and bodies&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AprilHathcock&quot;&gt;April Hathcock&lt;/a&gt;‘s &lt;a href=&quot;https://aprilhathcock.wordpress.com/2018/09/18/my-fire-this-time/&quot;&gt;courage and concision&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-technologies-do-you-use-to-facilitate-your-reading-and-writing&quot;&gt;What technologies do you use to facilitate your reading and writing?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I blog in a GoogleDoc (for collaborative stuff like this post), or using a Markdown editor (Typora) or text editor (BBedit, for when I really need to focus and not mess with formatting). I moved my personal blog (&lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/&quot;&gt;LiteratureGeek.com&lt;/a&gt;) from WordPress to a Jekyll-generated static site hosted on GitHub Pages, so sometimes I write directly on the GitHub website. I read and write tweets using Tweetbot (on my iPhone) or Tweetdeck (from my laptop). In the past, I’ve used &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hogbaysoftware.com/products/writeroom&quot;&gt;WriteRoom&lt;/a&gt; (for distraction-free exams presentation writing), and bookmarking tools including &lt;a href=&quot;https://getpocket.com/&quot;&gt;Pocket&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instapaper.com/&quot;&gt;Instapaper&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://pinboard.in/&quot;&gt;Pinboard&lt;/a&gt; to save things to read later. Currently, I save links from Twitter to Chrome bookmarks, and try to open those tabs at work once a week to read or discard them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;where-do-you-read-what-do-you-read-authors-forumsplatforms-formats-topics&quot;&gt;Where do you read? What do you read? (authors, forums/platforms, formats, topics…?)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been meaning to gather a list of frequent authors/places I read online, but have exhausted too much energy on my other answers to do that well right now! ¯_(ツ)_/¯ In addition to more professionally related reading by folks like my colleagues at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/&quot;&gt;Scholars’ Lab&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://nowviskie.org/2014/anthropocene/&quot;&gt;Bethany Nowviskie&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://walshbr.com/blog/praxis-and-scale-on-the-virtue-of-small/&quot;&gt;Brandon Walsh&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://hookandeye.ca/&quot;&gt;Aimée Morrison and the other &lt;em&gt;Hook &amp;amp; Eye&lt;/em&gt; bloggers&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AprilHathcock&quot;&gt;April Hathcock&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://chrisbourg.wordpress.com/&quot;&gt;Chris Bourg&lt;/a&gt;, I follow folks on Twitter who do creative, feminist tech work, many of whom also publish great &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/scholarslab/resources/blob/master/ZineBoard.md&quot;&gt;zines&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/wynkenhimself&quot;&gt;Sarah Werner&lt;/a&gt; does great scholarly blogging and tweeting, and I think I’ve also enjoyed basically every fiction book she’s recommended on Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Our thanks to colleague Ronda Grizzle for helping us frame this piece in a generative way! This is a partial cross-posting from &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/i-o-reading-writing-as-a-digital-humanist/&quot;&gt;a 9/27/2018 group-authored piece&lt;/a&gt; on the Scholars’ Lab blog.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 10 Oct 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/10/10/digital-humanities-reading-writing-habits</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/10/10/digital-humanities-reading-writing-habits</guid>
        
        <category>digital-humanities</category>
        
        <category>meta-DH</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Starter kit for considering a DH dissertation</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cross-posted on the Modern Languages Association (MLA) &lt;a href=&quot;https://infotech.mla.hcommons.org/2018/digital-humanities-dissertation-starter-kit/&quot;&gt;Committee on Info Tech blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Successful non-traditional dissertations include a comic book (&lt;a href=&quot;http://spinweaveandcut.com/unflattening/&quot;&gt;Nick Sousanis&lt;/a&gt;), a hip-hop album (&lt;a href=&quot;http://phd.aydeethegreat.com/&quot;&gt;A.D. Carson&lt;/a&gt;), code and design without written chapters (&lt;a href=&quot;http://dr.amandavisconti.com&quot;&gt;me&lt;/a&gt;), and the use of digital formats and methods such as a Tumblog counter-narrative (&lt;a href=&quot;http://vintageblackbeauty.tumblr.com/&quot;&gt;Jade E. Davis&lt;/a&gt;) or topic modeling (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lisarhody.com/revising-ekphrasis/&quot;&gt;Lisa Rhody&lt;/a&gt;). Are you curious about using digital methods or forms to pursue your dissertation research questions? Or maybe dissertational gate-tenders (advisors, mentors, departments) have you seeking successful examples of DH as part of the dissertation. Wherever you’re coming from, here’s a short selection of readings to get you started exploring digital humanities as doctoral scholarship:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Humanities Commons &lt;a href=&quot;https://hcommons.org/deposits/?facets%5Bgenre_facet%5D%5B%5D=Dissertation&quot;&gt;hosts around 70 dissertations&lt;/a&gt;; you can search for “digital humanities” to whittle these down to around 10 DHy theses such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://hcommons.org/deposits/item/hc:11773/&quot;&gt;Jason Rhody’s &lt;em&gt;Game Fiction&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://hcommons.org/deposits/item/mla:61/&quot;&gt;Alex Gil’s &lt;em&gt;Migrant Textuality&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;DH discussions under the aegis of scholarly organizations like MLA or AHA spend a good portion of time on concerns around evaluation and promotion relevant to the dissertation process. Resources you might check out on Humanities Commons include the &lt;a href=&quot;https://hcommons.org/groups/digital-humanists/&quot;&gt;Digital Humanists Group&lt;/a&gt; and events like &lt;a href=&quot;https://medicalhumanities.mla.hcommons.org/2018/02/07/online-forum-digital-humanities-medicine/&quot;&gt;the Online Forum on DH and Medicine&lt;/a&gt; recently posted on the Medical Humanities site.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://bit.ly/remixthediss-models&quot;&gt;#RemixtheDiss Models&lt;/a&gt; (hosted by the Futures Initiative at the Graduate Center CUNY and HASTAC) A collaboratively built GoogleDoc with information on a variety of dissertations using new formats and methods, including digital humanities approaches. Info includes each dissertation’s university and department, tools and media used, status of the dissertation (possibly outdated), and contact addresses for getting on touch with these dissertators.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org&quot;&gt;The Praxis Program&lt;/a&gt; (hosted by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org&quot;&gt;Scholars’ Lab&lt;/a&gt; at the University of Virginia Library) Now in its seventh year, the Praxis Program offers &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/projects/&quot;&gt;7 examples&lt;/a&gt; of what a small team of (usually pre-ABD) humanities graduate students new to DH can learn, research, and build over the course of two semesters.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zotero.org/amandavisconti/items/collectionKey/V9DA47T7&quot;&gt;DH Guidelines for Dissertations and Tenure Zotero Library&lt;/a&gt; (46 items) Tenure and promotion cases can be models for DH dissertations, with the same issues of evaluation, effort, packaging, and translation at stake.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hastac.org/&quot;&gt;HASTAC&lt;/a&gt; (the Humanities, Arts, Science, and Technology Alliance and Collaboratory) A good community to read what other students in similar fields and stages of the degree to yours are thinking about, and for becoming comfortable with scholarly blogging. See especially those posts tagged as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hastac.org/explore/humanities-arts-media/digital-humanities&quot;&gt;digital humanities&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hastac.org/groups/digital-dissertations&quot;&gt;digital dissertations&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the materials I created before or during my completed DH dissertation might also be relevant:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/assets/ExamsSharingCopy.pdf&quot;&gt;My PhD Exams reading list&lt;/a&gt;, including an introductory argument for the items on the list and two sets of materials: broad digital humanities readings, and textual scholarship with a focus on digital scholarly editing. Among other benefits, making DH a focus of your exams reading can help you understand your exam committee’s (as a potential dissertation committee) attitudes toward DH. A &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zotero.org/amandavisconti/items/collectionKey/MXZR7HFN&quot;&gt;Zotero library of some of the list’s readings is here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My dissertation itself is a website: &lt;a href=&quot;http://Dr.AmandaVisconti.com&quot;&gt;Dr.AmandaVisconti.com&lt;/a&gt;. The focus of the dissertation was the design, building, and analysis of a participatory digital edition, &lt;a href=&quot;http://InfiniteUlysses.com&quot;&gt;InfiniteUlysses.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/tag/dissertation/&quot;&gt;blogged&lt;/a&gt; throughout the dissertation process. I particularly recommend the linked posts on &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2016/06/14/digital-humanities-dissertation-defense-advice&quot;&gt;defense advice&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2016/06/20/digital-humanities-dissertation-defense-talk&quot;&gt;the actual defense talk&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2014/09/30/evaluating-non-traditional-digital-humanities-dissertations&quot;&gt;evaluating a DH dissertation&lt;/a&gt;, thinking through &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2014/05/27/inclusivityeditioncanon&quot;&gt;diversity and inclusion in your dissertation scholarship&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2014/04/28/affinitywallarticle&quot;&gt;planning out the many pieces of a dissertation project&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2014/04/02/digitaldissformat&quot;&gt;choosing the best format (chapters? something else?) for your scholarship&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 26 Feb 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/02/26/digital-humanities-dissertation-starter-kit</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/02/26/digital-humanities-dissertation-starter-kit</guid>
        
        <category>digital-humanities</category>
        
        <category>advice-tutorial</category>
        
        <category>dissertation</category>
        
        <category>grad-advice</category>
        
        <category>meta-DH</category>
        
        <category>dh-now</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Making a pneumatic tube messaging system</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Progression of stuff leading to my new project:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a shower thought about how pneumatic tube messaging systems work (vacuums? but how exactly, when they’re not sealed because messages go in and out? what are the differences between Hyperloop and a tube system?).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m now co-directing the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.scholarslab.org&quot;&gt;Scholars’ Lab&lt;/a&gt; (the DH center at the University of Virginia’s Library).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have an awesome Makerspace, staffed by experts in a variety of digital and crafting methods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I googled “DIY pneumatic tube” and found a number of tutorials and videos showing how a small-scale system could be built using a shopvac.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have a shopvac!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone on our staff has 20% of their time devoted to personal research, learning, and development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first R&amp;amp;D project will be building a pneumatic tube messaging system!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I started working through comparisons of the various tutorials to figure out what supplies I need to order. I have not made much stuff in my life? (I did a bit of Lilypad Arduino work with Kari Kraus and Beth Bonsignore—sewing conductive thread and LEDs that were controlled with a bit of Processing code—and that was awesome.) I’m going to blog from the beginning, before I know anything about how to do this (much less how to do this well.) I don’t even know basic information like what length of tubing our shopvac can support! I’ll blog as I learn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides getting me comfortable with building and using our Makerspace, the tube is part of a larger idea—rebuilding a set of historical communication devices as a means of personally understanding how significant various small innovations to a given tool were. I’m thinking a telegraph, light signals, audio signals (drums?), a drone carrier pigeon. A fax machine? (maybe hacking one, not building one.) Radio? (Maybe learning HAM radio, and also building a radio?) Any other ideas?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/historic-pneumatic-tube-system.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Public domain photo, work of an unknown employee of the United States Farm Security Administration or Office of War Information domestic photographic units.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jun 2017 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2017/06/30/making</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2017/06/30/making</guid>
        
        <category>digital-humanities</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>DH Job Talk (for my new role!): Scholars' Lab Managing Director</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m starting as Managing Director of the University of Virginia’s Scholars’ Lab digital humanities center later this spring! I shared &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2016/02/28/DHjobtalk&quot;&gt;the job talk I did for my previous role&lt;/a&gt; after I was hired, and here I’ll do the same for this new position (&lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/announcements/are-you-our-new-managing-director/&quot;&gt;check out the job ad here&lt;/a&gt;). Where my previous job’s interview presentation asked me to comment on the broad trends in libraries + DH citing current literature, this talk asked for a discussion of my past projects:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The digital has the potential to be a disruptive force in humanities scholarship, giving scholars the means to critique, reimagine, and transform ideas, theories, material artifacts, and even interpersonal relationships. Using examples from your own collaborations with faculty, graduate students, and staff, please discuss how this disruption can be successfully embodied in scholarly inquiry, as well as in the cultivation of people and organizations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve blogged the projects I shared in my talk (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.infiniteulysses.com&quot;&gt;Infinite Ulysses&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://tinyurl.com/DHSlack&quot;&gt;DH Slack&lt;/a&gt;) in previous posts on this website, but I’m sharing the talk regardless as the overall framing of my projects in response to the prompt might be of interest to someone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When scholars share their job talks after being hired, DH and libraries interviewing processes become a little less mysterious. Academia has many genres of presentation. It can be difficult to draft your first job talk without seeing how others in your field translate a job ad’s requirements into a job talk’s expression of their unique expertise. &lt;a href=&quot;http://readywriting.org/uncategorized/faculty-development-for-the-21st-century-and-beyond/&quot;&gt;Lee Skallerup Bessette&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://celestesharpe.com/onward/&quot;&gt;Celeste Tuong Vy Sharpe&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://chrisbourg.wordpress.com/2015/07/12/infrastructure-and-culture-a-job-talk/&quot;&gt;Chris Bourg&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/in-out-across-with-collaborative-education-and-digital-humanities-job-talk-for-head-of-graduate-programs/&quot;&gt;Brandon Walsh&lt;/a&gt; all share successful DHy job talks on their websites (I shared the &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2016/02/28/DHjobtalk&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/a&gt; for my previous faculty role, too).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-presentation&quot;&gt;The presentation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/UVaJobTalkSlides/UVaManagingDirector.001.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My digital humanities is not disruptive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/UVaJobTalkSlides/UVaManagingDirector.002.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disruption can be a force for good, especially against systemic problems. But to my ear, disruptive is not what I want DH to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disruption is inherently non-introspective; you disrupt others, rather than looking hard at yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disruption can ignore a history of similar work, and the humanities can’t afford that mistake. For example, a movement to make the humanities more public that ignored the fanfiction communities’ existing public humanities—people using the web to improve one another’s close readings and counterfactual interventions—would be deeply flawed. DH has diverse roots in pre-digital humanities scholarship, including highly recognizable non-digital, algorithmic criticism of the kinds Stephen Ramsay explores in his book &lt;em&gt;Reading Machines&lt;/em&gt;. We have much to gain by connecting our efforts today to what has worked in the humanities of the past, and to the humanities that also thrives outside academia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/UVaJobTalkSlides/UVaManagingDirector.004.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So when I share some of my recent collaborative DH work with you today, I’d like us to consider this work not in terms of how it &lt;em&gt;disrupts&lt;/em&gt; the humanities, but through a variety of more positive and generative lenses. DH as…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An applied humanities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Experimental&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Public and participatory&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A radically interdisciplinary humanities, embracing social science, science, and art&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Open to any challenges to which we can bring our skills of humanities thinking&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/UVaJobTalkSlides/UVaManagingDirector.005.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m hopeful for the humanities Bethany Nowviskie has imagined in her work “&lt;a href=&quot;http://nowviskie.org/2015/on-capacity-and-care/&quot;&gt;on capacity and care&lt;/a&gt;”. Nowviskie cautions: “Please do not mistake [capacity and care work] for something idealistic and motherly and sweet. I offer care as a hard-nosed survival strategy… to increase the reach and grasp (which is at the root of the word “capacity”—the “capture”) of the humanities.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seeing both the positive and negative sides of disruption, and turning to other concepts with different values, aren’t only reactions fueled by thinking these are good ways for a person to be in the world. There are significant gains for pushing our scholarship to be more intellectually generous, more locally interconnected, and better at crediting key emotional labor such as team-building and mentorship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/UVaJobTalkSlides/UVaManagingDirector.004.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in the next twenty minutes today, I want to tell you a bit about two of my recent DH projects, one where the bulk of the work is my own, and one where I’m only nominally the creator. This work articulates some of my hopes for what the digital humanities could be, a DH deeply part of the humanities rather than opposed to it, a DH that’s more interested in the right column up on the screen [&lt;em&gt;in the image above this paragraph, for blog readers&lt;/em&gt;]—in seeing innovation in maintainance, the quality rather than the quantity of impact, on “people over projects” (as the Scholars’ Lab puts it).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/UVaJobTalkSlides/UVaManagingDirector.007.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first project I’ll discuss, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.infiniteulysses.com&quot;&gt;Infinite Ulysses&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, shows humanities scholarly inquiry that’s been reimagined and opened beyond academia, rather than disrupted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m a textual scholar. I decided that instead of focusing on the scholarly editing aspect of digital editions, my skills and interest were more in line with work like that of Alan Galey, whose &lt;em&gt;Visualizing Variation&lt;/em&gt; project created code that lets editors of digital editions intervene in their texts in unique ways. Rather than creating a scholarly edition, I focused more on interface design aimed at opening a literary edition to a public audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/UVaJobTalkSlides/UVaManagingDirector.009.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I asked: What if we build a digital edition and invite everyone? What if millions of scholars, first-time readers, book clubs, teachers and their students, show up and annotate a text with their “infinite” annotations (that is, digital marginalia of interpretations, questions, contextualizations, and other comments)? How would we do that, and what would it do to the text and our understandings of it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/UVaJobTalkSlides/UVaManagingDirector.010.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I worked through this speculative experiment, with its admittedly unlikely hypothetical of a massive public desire to read &lt;em&gt;Ulysses&lt;/em&gt; online. But I also built a prototype that was immediately useful in exploring these questions, through the generous annotations and feedback of an actual, modestly sized community of readers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Infinite Ulysses&lt;/em&gt; (at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.infiniteulysses.com&quot;&gt;InfiniteUlysses.com&lt;/a&gt;), is a participatory digital edition of James Joyce’s challenging novel &lt;em&gt;Ulysses&lt;/em&gt;. Its goal was to support a public conversation about the novel, bringing readers of different backgrounds into participating in the same discussion space. The design, code, usertesting, and thinking that went into this project doubled as my literature dissertation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what reading a page on Infinite Ulysses looks like. There are three main activities you can pursue:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;While reading the novel, you can highlight parts of the text and annotate these with your questions, interpretations, reactions, translations, and other comments. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can also read the annotations created by other readers.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And I tried, at a basic level, to personalize your reading experience by filtering the displayed annotations so that you could just be shown the ones that fit your needs, interests, and background. For example, a reader can choose to see the top-rated annotations first, or the newest annotations; or to not see any spoilers; or to only see annotations tagged as clues to the book’s mysteries, references to Irish politics, or jokes you might miss.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is some solid interest in this approach. My work was cited in &lt;em&gt;The New York Times&lt;/em&gt; this past summer, drew around 13,000 unique visitors in its first month of beta testing, and drew over 25,000 unique visitors during its beta year (April 2015-2016), despite little intentional publicity after the first month. I share these numbers to show that there’s interest in this scholarship, but in doing so I feel uncomfortably close to getting caught up in the allure of large-scale impact. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much more important to me, and to the humanities, are the far smaller number of people who actually repeatedly visited and annotated &lt;em&gt;Ulysses&lt;/em&gt; on the site. What matters is the students who hear about my dissertation and are encouraged to also pursue the most appropriate methods for their research questions. I care about my impact at the scale of individual readers, like the South Korean reader who found my edition more accessible for her translation and understanding. Or the 90-year-old retired man who wrote that he’d always wanted to read &lt;em&gt;Ulysses&lt;/em&gt;, and now he felt like he could take his laptop to a bar, pull up a stool, and maybe actually read the thing this time using my site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/UVaJobTalkSlides/UVaManagingDirector.013.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are other facets to the scholarship of &lt;em&gt;Infinite Ulysses&lt;/em&gt;, clear areas of research inquiry:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My 1st research question was an interdisciplinary DH one:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How can we design digital editions that are not just theoretically accessible to the public, but invite and assist public participation? And are there ways to design for meaningful public participation in literature, that don’t require the public to learn scholarly rhetoric?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My 2nd question was from the field of information science:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How can we design public DH websites to handle a huge influx of readers and annotations, so that individual user experience doesn’t suffer and diverse user needs are met? How would each user find the “signal” of the best annotations for them to read, from the noise of “infinite” public annotations?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My 3rd question was from the field of literature:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Textual scholars often create editions as their scholarship. By separating out historical textual scholarship values from how the editions realizing those values looked, can we imagine other forms still holding true to the values of our field? What can we learn by accepting scholarly editions as just one of many ways of embodying textual scholarship values?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/UVaJobTalkSlides/UVaManagingDirector.016.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I’m here to speak about collaborative DH today, and you might be wondering how a literature dissertation can be a collaborative rather than a largely solo activity. I did perform the full scholarly labor you’d expect from a literature dissertation—most people would agree successfully defending the dissertation and becoming a tenure-track assistant professor shows that. But beyond my dissertation-length work, the larger project around my dissertation relied strongly on collaboration and the intellectual generosity of others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A huge number of people made Infinite Ulysses possible, so much so that I can’t name everyone right now, but I’ve put as many as possible up on the screen [&lt;em&gt;image above previous paragraph, and http://www.infiniteulysses.com/credits goes into more detail&lt;/em&gt;].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My advisor Matt Kirschenbaum and committee members Neil Fraistat, Kari Kraus, Melanie Kill, and Brian Richardson are amazingly intellectually generous scholars. They met with me as a team regularly throughout the entire dissertation, which was hugely helpful in keeping everyone informed about and happy with the developing look of the dissertation. I also benefitted from the feedback of colleagues at the MITH DH center where I worked 2009-2015, such as Stephanie Sapienza and Ed Summers. Their questions, guidance, and encouragement were critical in realizing my project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through social media, DHer Michael Widner at Stanford and I discovered we were working on similar tech (the Drupal annotator module). Despite being on opposite coasts, we Skyped to discuss our work, and he ended up generously allowing me to build on top of some of his Lacuna Stories project code that hadn’t yet been publicly released, allowing me to spend more time on a different piece of coding more closely tied to my research questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The people who visited Infinite Ulysses and shared annotations and/or feedback on the site are collaborators, too. The majority of the site’s annotations were authored by people other than me. Ten types of user testing, data gathering, and participatory design, with a variety of people, over the course of the site’s development, directly shaped the growth of the site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Infinite Ulysses was a collaborative project with a large portion created by one person. Now, I want to tell you about a project that’s far more of a distributed and balanced collaborative, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://tinyurl.com/DHSlack&quot;&gt;Digital Humanities Slack&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/UVaJobTalkSlides/UVaManagingDirector.019.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slack is a social media platform that functions like a set of interconnected, themed chat rooms. Using the Slack platform, I created and manage the scholarly forum of the Digital Humanities Slack (or DH Slack). Started a little over a year ago, it now supports over 1,200 digital humanists through around 70 “channels” (thematic chat rooms on topics like libraries and the digital humanities, open access, data sharing, and various DH methods and theories). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/UVaJobTalkSlides/UVaManagingDirector.020.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The DH Slack is open to anyone with a curiosity about DH and/or related interests (e.g. digital libraries, museums, and archives)—those interested just visit &lt;a href=&quot;http://tinyurl.com/DHslack&quot;&gt;tinyurl.com/DHslack&lt;/a&gt; to join. Absolutely no DH expertise is required, and we have several specific channels devoted to DH beginners, students, job seekers, and asking all kinds of DHy questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/UVaJobTalkSlides/UVaManagingDirector.021.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The DH Slack is ““mine”” [&lt;em&gt;all the air quotes&lt;/em&gt;] in an extremely limited sense, if any. I set up the Slack, publicize its existence, moderate it, periodically started discussions (more in its early days than now), answer questions about using the Slack, and lead policy-making such as adapting a DH-specific code of conduct. That code of conduct covers things like not publicly posting screenshots of Slack conversations without first getting the consent of everyone shown in the shot, which is why I’m largely showing tweets rather than screengrabs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/UVaJobTalkSlides/UVaManagingDirector.022.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Five other DHers generously collaborate with me as additional Slack moderators: Alan G. Pike, Sam Abrams, Alex Gil, Ed Summers, and Paige C. Morgan. We take our code of conduct seriously, and have taken firm action when it’s been called for, to protect our community members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/UVaJobTalkSlides/UVaManagingDirector.023.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The DH Slack exists because of its members, who build a humanities community through their conversations and sharing. Even the most collaborative and democratic of teams needs one person to really be in charge of project management, and I feel like my current role with the DH Slack is similar—helping things along, being available and responsible should problems arise, and making the final call after group discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/UVaJobTalkSlides/UVaManagingDirector.024.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re still figuring out how Slack can be useful to our scholarship: Can it allow different kinds of conversations than Twitter? On the screen, you can see examples of DHers moving between the Slack and Twitter to have different kinds of conversations—in that middle tweet, a technical discussion that was limited by Twitter’s format switched to the Slack to continue more freely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/UVaJobTalkSlides/UVaManagingDirector.025.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of our members work at non-profits or in K-12 teaching, or aren’t professionally involved in academics; some are undergrads or grad students. It’s clear that the Slack, like many other platforms, can support geographically dispersed collaborators. But can we use the Slack to teach and support people interested in DH who don’t know of any potential collaborators, don’t have mentors geographically near them, or who aren’t inside academia? For example, I’m hoping to do a Slack hangout this spring where I’ll be available on the Slack to help anyone who wants to work through &lt;a href=&quot;http://programminghistorian.org/lessons/building-static-sites-with-jekyll-github-pages&quot;&gt;my &lt;em&gt;Programming Historian&lt;/em&gt; lesson on creating their own first research website&lt;/a&gt;. If DH mentors can periodically be virtually available to support questions about specific tech tutorials, maybe we can ease new DHers experimentation with digital methods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interesting uses of the DH Slack I’ve seen so far include allowing remote participants at MITH’s recent “Night Against Hate” scholarly-activist hackathon, mentorship for new digital humanists, a place to connect regional DH networks such as in Tennessee, Baltimore, and Australia and languages such as Spanish, and as a space to expand Twitter conversations. We’ve been used as a model by other scholars for their own Slack instances, and I authored an invited guest post about the DH Slack for the London School of Economics blog this past summer. If you’d like a place to discuss and learn about the digital humanities, or a friendly place to ask questions, please join us via &lt;a href=&quot;http://TinyUrl.com/DHSlack&quot;&gt;TinyUrl.com/DHSlack&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both the DH Slack and Infinite Ulysses model a digital humanities that’s not disruptive, but different. Both take an experimental approach grounded on past humanities successes, whether that’s DH Twitter or speculative textual experiments like the Ivanhoe game or Prism. The experiments of both projects recognizably demonstrate humanities scholarship and community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both experiments also demonstrate my key interests. I’m deeply invested in DH design and building as a route to new knowledge, especially through interfaces for public, communal learning. And I’m keenly interested in the larger questions of how we make DH go: infrastructure and process, project management, and community-building. If you visit my &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.LiteratureGeek.com&quot;&gt;LiteratureGeek.com&lt;/a&gt; blog, you’ll see that I share everything from theory and analysis, to my software and design decisions, how I get started planning a new project, and how my work space is set up. This is all as a way to think through not just the strategies, but also the daily tactics of successful DH.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Infinite Ulysses and the DH Slack are at two ends of the collaboration spectrum, but the bulk of my interdisciplinary collaboration experience actually happens quite differently, in project teams that regularly meet face-to-face (as with a group of graduate students I taught to work with the &lt;em&gt;Shelley-Godwin Archive&lt;/em&gt;) or over Skype (as with the BitCurator team).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/UVaJobTalkSlides/UVaManagingDirector.028.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, in my current role as a DH librarian and faculty at Purdue Libraries, I enjoy a close working relationship with my colleagues in both Archives and Special Collections, and in our university press. Together, we’re using DH as the connector to build a workflow for campus DH research and teaching that runs from archival description and discovery, through scholarly communication and publication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t cover this kind of collaboration in detail in this talk, as I suspect this kind of face-to-face collaboration is the most common and familiar. But, I’ll wrap up by listing on the screen a few of my more typically collaborative DH projects on the screen, and I’m happy to discuss these further in the Q&amp;amp;A or over email. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/UVaJobTalkSlides/UVaManagingDirector.031.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 23 Feb 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2017/02/23/scholars-lab-dh-center-managing-director-job-talk</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2017/02/23/scholars-lab-dh-center-managing-director-job-talk</guid>
        
        <category>digital-humanities</category>
        
        <category>advice-tutorial</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>New role: Scholars' Lab Managing Director</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m starting as Managing Director of the University of Virginia’s Scholars’ Lab later this spring! Academic Director Alison Booth wrote &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/uncategorized/amanda-visconti-is-our-new-managing-director/&quot;&gt;a lovely post about my hire on the Scholars’ Lab blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/SLphoto.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Scholars’ Lab is a digital humanities center at the University of Virginia Libraries, and a founding member of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://dhcenternet.org/&quot;&gt;CenterNet&lt;/a&gt; international network of DH centers. The Lab has &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/people/&quot;&gt;an amazing team of DH experts&lt;/a&gt; (including new Head of Graduate Programs &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/walshbr&quot;&gt;Brandon Walsh&lt;/a&gt;), &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/about/charter/&quot;&gt;a team-authored charter&lt;/a&gt; I deeply respect, and past and current work including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://neatline.org/&quot;&gt;Neatline&lt;/a&gt;, “a mix-and-match toolset for the creation of interlinked timelines and maps as interpretive expressions of the literary or historical content of archival collections”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://codespeak.scholarslab.org/&quot;&gt;Speaking in Code&lt;/a&gt;, a symposium of advanced DH developers discussing tacit DH tech knowledge&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/&quot;&gt;Praxis Program&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis-network.org/&quot;&gt;Network&lt;/a&gt;—innovative models of DH student training, where students have collaboratively created projects such as &lt;a href=&quot;http://prism.scholarslab.org/&quot;&gt;Prism&lt;/a&gt; and an &lt;a href=&quot;http://ivanhoe.scholarslab.org/&quot;&gt;Ivanhoe reboot&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/makerspace/&quot;&gt;experimental humanities Makerspace&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Leadership Alliance Mellon Initiative (LAMI) fellows (supporting minority students interested in graduate studies)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And even more work captured in this 2016 &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/uncategorized/whats-the-scholars-lab/&quot;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; by Alison Booth and on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/research/&quot;&gt;Scholars’ Lab research page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m deeply honored to join and excited to work with the Scholars’ Lab team and community, and looking forward to being back in the VA/MD area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2017/02/23/scholars-lab-dh-center-managing-director-job-talk&quot;&gt;next post on this blog&lt;/a&gt; will share the job talk I gave while interviewing for this role, and you could also check out &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2016/02/28/DHjobtalk&quot;&gt;my previous role’s job talk&lt;/a&gt; if you’re interested in interviewing for DHy positions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2017/02/22/scholars-lab-dh-center-managing-director</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2017/02/22/scholars-lab-dh-center-managing-director</guid>
        
        <category>digital-humanities</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>DH 2017 Long Paper &amp; Panel Acceptances</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://dh2017.adho.org/&quot;&gt;DH 2017&lt;/a&gt; is the annual international digital humanities conference, held this August 2017 in Montréal. I’ll attend the annual &lt;a href=&quot;https://ach.org&quot;&gt;ACH&lt;/a&gt; executive council meeting then, and also present twice:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My “&lt;strong&gt;Less intent, more impact: Transforming public DH projects toward access, care, and inclusion&lt;/strong&gt;” talk was accepted as a long paper (see below for abstract). Among other thinkers mentioned in the abstract, the focus on a specific DH project’s social impacts was inspired by Mark A. Matienzo’s “&lt;a href=&quot;http://matienzo.org/2016/to-hell-with-good-intentions/&quot;&gt;To Hell With Good Intentions: Linked Data, Community and the Power to Name&lt;/a&gt;”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;strong&gt;Hack, Yack, Stack: Access, Culture, and DH Infrastructure&lt;/strong&gt;”, a panel I’m on with Laura Braunstein (Dartmouth College Digital Humanities Librarian) and Thomas Padilla (University of California Santa Barbara, Humanities Data Curator) was also accepted. We’ll be interviewing one another on our varied experiences with and definitions of developing DH infrastructure within libraries, with lots of space for audience conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;long-paper-debriefing-the-infinite-ulysses-project-towards-a-socially-just-digital-humanities&quot;&gt;Long paper: Debriefing the Infinite Ulysses project towards a socially just digital humanities&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The abstract I submitted, followed by responses to the (very helpful—thanks, anonymous reviewers!) reviewer comments:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good intent carries no guarantee of a positive impact on the world. For digital humanities designers and makers building projects that face or involve public audiences, we have an extra scholarly and human responsibility for all the repercussions of our work. Focusing not on what we mean to create, but on how our work could both positively and negatively affect others, enables a more caring, accessible, and inclusive DH.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This paper uses my design, coding, and user testing of the participatory digital edition of James Joyce’s challenging novel &lt;em&gt;Ulysses&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://InfiniteUlysses.com&quot;&gt;Infinite Ulysses (InfiniteUlysses.com)&lt;/a&gt;, to demonstrate a public DH project designed with care for its impact on both its audience and the DH community. More importantly, I’ll explore how ethical design considerations such as increasing accessibility and inclusion can be added or increased in existing projects that may not have explicitly built these values in from the start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.InfiniteUlysses.com&quot;&gt;Infinite Ulysses&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; is a public digital humanities project that has drawn over 25,000 unique site visitors, as well as a smaller body of 775 readers who created user accounts to interact more closely with the digital edition through annotation and other social features. &lt;em&gt;Infinite Ulysses&lt;/em&gt; is also the bulk of a unique, successfully defended, no-chapters literature dissertation, and as such those interested in the future of humanities graduate education may enjoy this paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building the &lt;em&gt;Infinite Ulysses&lt;/em&gt; digital edition helped me separate the scholarly values of textual scholarship from the common embodiment of these values (i.e. the scholarly digital edition or SDE). Through this clarification, I imagined new types of digital edition that, while different from SDEs, hold true to the same values performed by SDEs. Through building and testing the public use of one of these new models for reifying textual scholarship values, I experimented with designing an edition that is not just publicly accessible, but also invites and assists public participation in the scholarly love for a text’s materiality, history, and meaning. On the spectrum of crowdsourcing engagement, I located multiple paths for meaningful public DH activity that fall between the endpoints of full critical rhetoric and “adding a tag”. To enable this public engagement, I explored ways of designing participatory digital editions to adeptly handle an influx of public readers and their annotations, and tested suggestions on what scholars can learn about digital editions and their texts from the accompanying influx of website use data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Femtechnet scholars’ recentering of DH on ethical questions around technology design led me to connect the fields of textual scholarship and human-computer interaction, porting concepts of humane and ethical digital design to the domain of literary editions. Michael Muller’s formulation of participatory design as a “third space” connecting two audiences helped me support both scholarly and public edition readers in “challenging assumptions, learning reciprocally, and creating new ideas, which emerge through negotiation and co-creation of identities, working languages, understandings, and relationships, and polyvocal (many-voiced) dialogues across and through differences“. Katie Shilton’s exploration of how the design of a technology shapes the social values and ethics of its users helped me plan toward a community of annotators that would care for, rather than compete against, one another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My post-dissertation work on &lt;em&gt;Infinite Ulysses&lt;/em&gt; pulls in thinking from libraries and information science. Librarian Chris Bourg argues that neither technology nor knowledge infrastructures such as libraries can be neutral, and that therefore we must leverage both toward, rather than away from, social justice. Archivist Jarrett M. Drake calls us to move beyond current institutional archives to build knowledge structures that let us “unlock our futures as humans, as community members, as archivists, and as memory workers”, and suggests design that encourages perceptions of community belonging as a way forward. Digital Library Federation Director Bethany Nowviskie asks, “Can we position our digital collections and digital scholarly projects more plainly not as statements about what was and is, but as resources for the building of different, better worlds?” The knowledge infrastructure of libraries and archives ports well to that of digital editions, as well as to DH more broadly. Each of these thinkers push us to create work that would take us from what DH is to what DH can be; in this presentation, their arguments act as direct prompts for exploring small ways of designing toward a better DH through the specific use case of &lt;em&gt;Infinite Ulysses&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This paper quickly paints a cohesive picture of the &lt;em&gt;Infinite Ulysses&lt;/em&gt; project, &lt;u&gt;instead spending the bulk of its time&lt;/u&gt; critiquing the impact of the project on its users and on the DH community. In “Do Artifacts Have Ethics?”, Michael Sacasas proposes a series of questions to be asked by anyone making something of what they’re making—whether that’s building an app, designing a class, or in this case designing and coding a digital humanities project. I use Sacasas’ provocations to examine the successes, failures, and difficult decisions of &lt;em&gt;Infinite Ulysses&lt;/em&gt;’ design, &lt;strong&gt;walking the audience through concrete examples of what I did, what I should have done, or what I could do to make the project have an even better impact on the world.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An example of a positive impact on &lt;em&gt;Infinite Ulysses&lt;/em&gt;’ users: I provided my annotators with the ability to export their textual annotations from my website, giving them ownership and control over the results of their labor, and not forcing them to risk losing their work if my site crashed or closed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An example of a negative impact on &lt;em&gt;Infinite Ulysses&lt;/em&gt;’ users: I tried to populate the digital margins of &lt;em&gt;Ulysses&lt;/em&gt; with the characters in the book, by letting new users choose among illustrations of the novel’s characters for the avatar that accompanies their textual annotations. The makeup of Joyce’s text means that those avatars were largely white and male, with three white female options, a cat, and no other identities. For a text that already struggles with instances of sexism, racism, and transphobia, making new readers feel “I’m not represented here, I’m not supposed to be here” was an additional negative impact that should have easily been avoided.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An example of a positive impact of &lt;em&gt;Infinite Ulysses&lt;/em&gt; on the DH community: I demonstrated that a public DH project could support meaningful public participation that didn’t necessitate bending public questions, interpretations, and other comments on &lt;em&gt;Ulysses&lt;/em&gt; to fit the mold of scholarly rhetoric. By both successfully designing for public participation (my edition was cited in &lt;em&gt;The New York Times&lt;/em&gt; as a means for readers to make sense of the novel) and performing innovative humanities scholarship through that design (the project received my university’s 2016 award for arts and humanities distinguished dissertation), I added to the digital humanities’ long and ever-growing list of examples of how building can itself be critical research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An example of a negative impact of &lt;em&gt;Infinite Ulysses&lt;/em&gt; on the DH community: I deepened digital editions’ duplication of the problems with the print literary canon, by building a project around another canon text and author. When only 11 of 86 projects funded by the NEH Preservation &amp;amp; Access Office 2006-2011 had a topic other than a white male writer (&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ryancordell/status/409050747666706432&quot;&gt;Jessica DeSpain&lt;/a&gt;), I struggle with whether the positive public impacts of my work are worth deepening our problems with authorial representation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I act as my scholarship’s own harshest critic not to paralyze other DH builders from ever making anything, but to make visible specific examples of how in small ways, by adding the skill of care to the skill of critique, we makers can build a better DH and a better world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Responses to reviews:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A clear framing of the &lt;em&gt;Infinite Ulysses&lt;/em&gt; project is necessary before leading the audience through the project’s ethical considerations and how these might extend to other DH work. The long paper format would allow me time to ensure the audience comfortably understands this case study project, before I embark on exploring its implications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After my careful grounding of the &lt;em&gt;Infinite Ulysses&lt;/em&gt; case study, I will survey the critical DH cultural scholarship that grounded my assessment of the ethical impact of my work (e.g. Deb Verhoeven, Roopika Risam, Moya Bailey, Amy Earhart), as well as scholarship in related areas such as libraries feminist interface design (e.g. Bess Sadler, Catherine D’Ignazio and Lauren F. Klein, Shaowen Bardzell and Eli Blevis).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By combining my specific &lt;em&gt;Infinite Ulysses&lt;/em&gt; case study and this survey of critical DH, I can spend the rest of my talk exploring a sampling of how I addressed my project’s ethical challenges, while also relating these decisions back to broader best practices that future DH projects and scholars might reuse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;Bibliography&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arbuckle, Alyssa. “Considering The Waste Land for iPad and Weird Fiction as models for the public digital edition”. &lt;em&gt;Digital Studies&lt;/em&gt;. 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barab, Sasha and Kurt Squire. “Design-Based Research: Putting a Stake in the Ground”. &lt;em&gt;The Journal of the Learning Science&lt;/em&gt; 13(1), 1–14.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bourg, Chris. “Libraries, technology, and social justice”. Text of Access 2016 talk published as blog post on &lt;em&gt;Feral Librarian&lt;/em&gt; blog. October 7, 2016. chrisbourg.wordpress.com/2016/10/07/libraries-technology-and-social-justice&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drake, Jarrett M. “Liberatory Archives: Towards Belonging and Believing (Part 1)”. Medium blog post: “On Archivy” collection. October 22, 2016. medium.com/on-archivy/liberatory-archives-towards-belonging-and-believing-part-1-d26aaeb0edd1#.fbgxfse1v&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drucker, Johanna. “Graphesis: Visual Knowledge Production and Representation”. &lt;em&gt;Poetess Archive Journal&lt;/em&gt;. 2(1). 2010. journals.tdl.org/paj/index.php/paj/article/download/4/50&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;—. “Humanities Approaches to Graphical Display”. &lt;em&gt;Digital Humanities Quarterly&lt;/em&gt;. 5(1). 2011. digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/5/1/000091/000091.html&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Galey, Alan and Stan Ruecker. “How a Prototype Argues.” &lt;em&gt;Literary and Linguistic Computing&lt;/em&gt;. 25(4). 2010. 405-424.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Groden, Michael. “Introduction to ‘James Joyce’s &lt;em&gt;Ulysses&lt;/em&gt; in Hypermedia’”. &lt;em&gt;Journal of Modern Literature&lt;/em&gt;. 24(3/4). 2001. 359-362.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;—. “Problems of Annotation in a Digital &lt;em&gt;Ulysses&lt;/em&gt;” . &lt;em&gt;Hypermedia Joyce Studies&lt;/em&gt;. 4(2). 2003-4. www.oocities.org/hypermedia_joyce/groden.html&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kraut, R. E. and Paul Resnick. &lt;em&gt;Building successful online communities: evidence-based social design&lt;/em&gt;. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press. 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lacuna Stories&lt;/em&gt;. Collaborative annotation digital humanities project. www.lacunastories.com&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Losh, Elizabeth, Jacqueline Wernimont, Laura Wexler, and Hong-An Wu. “Putting the Human Back into the Digital Humanities: Feminism, Generosity, and Mess”. In &lt;em&gt;Debates in the Digital Humanities&lt;/em&gt;, Lauren F. Klein and Matthew K. Gold, eds. 2016. dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/61&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marino, Mark C. “Ulysses on Web 2.0: Towards a Hypermedia Parallax Engine”. &lt;em&gt;James Joyce Quarterly&lt;/em&gt;. 44(3). Spring 2007. 475-499.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matienzo, Mark A. “To Hell With Good Intentions: Linked Data, Community and the Power to Name”. Blog post of November 15, 2015 keynote for the 2015 LITA Forum. Matienzo.org/2016/to-hell-with-good-intentions&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Muller, Michael J. “Participatory Design: The Third Space in HCI”. In &lt;em&gt;The Human-Computer Interaction Handbook&lt;/em&gt;. 1051-1068.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Norris, Margot. &lt;em&gt;Virgin and Veteran Readings of Ulysses&lt;/em&gt;. Palgrave Macmillan. 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nowviskie, Bethany. “Interfacing the Edition”. Text of conference talk.www2.iath.virginia.edu/bpn2f/1866/interface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;—. “alternate futures/usable pasts”. Text of talk given at Marquette University Library in September 2016 published as blog post. October 24, 2016. nowviskie.org/2016/alternate-futures-usable-pasts/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pope, Rob. &lt;em&gt;Textual Intervention: Critical and Creative Strategies for Literary Studies&lt;/em&gt;. Taylor &amp;amp; Francis Group. 1995.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sacasas, L.M. “Do Artifacts Have Ethics?” &lt;em&gt;Technology, Culture, and Ethics&lt;/em&gt; blog, November 29, 2014. thefrailestthing.com/2014/11/29/do-artifacts-have-ethics&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shilton, Katie. “Values Levers: Building Ethics Into Design”. &lt;em&gt;Science Technology Human Values&lt;/em&gt; 38(3), May 2013, 374-397.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Utell, Janine M. “The Archivist, the Archaeologist, and the Amateur: Reading Joyce at the Rosenbach”. &lt;em&gt;Journal of Modern Literature&lt;/em&gt;. 31. 2008. 53-65.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warwick, C., Melissa Terras, P. Huntington, and N. Pappa. “If You Build It Will They Come? The LAIRAH Study: Quantifying the Use of Online Resources in the Arts and Humanities through Statistical Analysis of User Log Data”. &lt;em&gt;Literary and Linguistic Computing&lt;/em&gt;. 23(1). 2008. 85-102.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 19 Feb 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2017/02/19/dh-2017-paper-accepted</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2017/02/19/dh-2017-paper-accepted</guid>
        
        <category>digital-humanities</category>
        
        <category>infinite-ulysses</category>
        
        <category>scholarly-web-design-and-coding</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Theming Jekyll: Customizing the look of your GitHub Pages-hosted, Jekyll-generated website</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;If you’d like an entirely free, easy-to-maintain, preservation-friendly, secure website over which you have full control—such as a scholarly blog, project website, or online portfolio—using Jekyll and GitHub Pages is a good option. I wrote &lt;a href=&quot;http://programminghistorian.org/lessons/building-static-sites-with-jekyll-github-pages&quot;&gt;a peer-reviewed lesson that will get you started&lt;/a&gt; over at &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://programminghistorian.org&quot;&gt;The Programming Historian&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; (which is a really cool site full of peer-reviewed &lt;a href=&quot;http://programminghistorian.org/lessons&quot;&gt;lessons&lt;/a&gt; for lots of digital humanities skills and methods). My lesson, like many of the lessons at &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://programminghistorian.org&quot;&gt;The Programming Historian&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, assumes no technical knowledge and is specifically aimed at people who haven’t coded or created a website before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That lesson takes you through publishing a basic website that will look much like this &lt;a href=&quot;https://amandavisconti.github.io/JekyllDemo/&quot;&gt;demo website&lt;/a&gt;. If you enjoy the lesson and want to further customize the look of your website, this blog post will help you do that! (&lt;em&gt;This post assumes you’ve read &lt;a href=&quot;http://programminghistorian.org/lessons/building-static-sites-with-jekyll-github-pages&quot;&gt;my lesson&lt;/a&gt; already.&lt;/em&gt;) Thanks to Daniel Akacki for motivation to write this post!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;theming&quot;&gt;Theming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned in &lt;a href=&quot;http://programminghistorian.org/lessons/building-static-sites-with-jekyll-github-pages&quot;&gt;my lesson&lt;/a&gt;, “theming” means changing the visual appearance (and sometimes behavior, like adding a comment section or a new menu) of your website. “Styling” is often used to mean changing a site’s appearance through CSS (the language that tells a browser how to display things, much like HTML tells a browser how to structure content on a page); “theming” more often means that you’re achieving styling through not just changes to existing CSS, but by reusing, customizing, or creating a set of multiple files that change the site’s visual appearance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before you dive into learning CSS, you can simply reuse (and then tweak or more heavily customize) any of the many existing themes for Jekyll-generated sites. &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllthemes.org/&quot;&gt;The Jekyll Themes site&lt;/a&gt; is a good place to start looking for free themes, and most of the themes have a demo website set up so you can navigate around a site using the theme and really get a feel for how it would look on your website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll/issues/4510&quot;&gt;Jekyll moved recently&lt;/a&gt; from themes that consisted of just adding files to your site folder (some CSS, HTML layouts, images, Javascript, etc.), to themes that you install as Ruby Gems (the way you already had to install Jekyll plugins). This is useful in some ways (e.g. improvements the theme creator makes to their theme can be updated on your website just by your updating the gem), but it can also be confusing for people who aren’t familiar with Ruby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below, I explain how I took the website you should have at the end of &lt;a href=&quot;http://programminghistorian.org/lessons/building-static-sites-with-jekyll-github-pages&quot;&gt;my lesson&lt;/a&gt;, and changed the site to have a new theme. This isn’t the only way to theme, but I think it’s currently the easiest way if you’re new to web development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;switching-to-the-hacker-theme&quot;&gt;Switching to the “Hacker” theme&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll be switching to the “Hacker” theme, for which &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pages-themes/hacker&quot;&gt;you can find the code here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/jekyllhackertheme.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Jekyll-generated GitHub Pages site using the Hacker theme&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I set up a duplicate of&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the &lt;a href=&quot;https://amandavisconti.github.io/JekyllDemo&quot;&gt;https://amandavisconti.github.io/JekyllDemo&lt;/a&gt; site I created for my lesson&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;at &lt;a href=&quot;https://amandavisconti.github.io/JekyllDemoThemed&quot;&gt;https://amandavisconti.github.io/JekyllDemoThemed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;so that we’re starting from where &lt;a href=&quot;http://programminghistorian.org/lessons/building-static-sites-with-jekyll-github-pages&quot;&gt;my lesson&lt;/a&gt; left off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I went to &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pages-themes/hacker&quot;&gt;https://github.com/pages-themes/hacker&lt;/a&gt;, clicked on the green “clone or download” button on the right, and choose to download the files as a ZIP and then unpack the ZIP (usually doubleclicking the ZIP icon will do this).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I made a copy of my original site files elsewhere, then deleted everything &lt;em&gt;inside&lt;/em&gt; my website folder (/JekyllDemoThemed)—but not the folder itself. I then pasted in everything &lt;em&gt;inside&lt;/em&gt; that unpacked ZIP folder—rather than pasting in the whole folder and its contents.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;We made a copy of your original files so that we can later paste in any posts or pages you want to keep from your original site.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A skippable aside, if you’re interested:&lt;/em&gt; Making a copy of your website files before deleting them actually isn’t a huge need, since if you’ve followed my lesson you already have those files committed on GitHub, and can always go back to that or other earlier versions of your site (it’s just more hassle, which is why we’re making a local copy instead). Also, you &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; keep your original site files as-is and just add in the needed files (and/or code inside files) from the theme, but as someone newer to Jekyll it might be difficult to figure out which files need to be changed and which can stay, which is why we’re instead starting from the theme ZIP and importing anything from your original site you want to keep.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the terminal, cd into the website folder. For my file setup, that meant entering &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cd /Volumes/Vault101/Documents/GitHubGeneral/JekyllDemoTheme&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Enter &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;script/bootstrap&lt;/code&gt;. Let it finish running.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Open your _config.yml file and paste in the following (replacing &lt;em&gt;/JekyllDemoThemed&lt;/em&gt; with the name of your website folder):&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;baseurl: &quot;/JekyllDemoThemed&quot;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;url: &quot;localhost:4000&quot;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Paste in the /_posts folder from that copy you made of your old site (if you want the posts from the old site). Paste in the pages from the old site (&lt;a href=&quot;http://about.md/&quot;&gt;about.md&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://resume.md/&quot;&gt;resume.md&lt;/a&gt;) if you want them.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;These pages and posts from the old site reference a layout file that existed for the Minima theme (the theme that your first Jekyll site defaults to), but not for the Hacker theme. So, you need to open each page and change &lt;strong&gt;layout: page &lt;/strong&gt;to &lt;strong&gt;layout: default&lt;/strong&gt;, and open each post and change &lt;strong&gt;layout: post&lt;/strong&gt; to &lt;strong&gt;layout: default&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you’re using the default text in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://about.md/&quot;&gt;about.md&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://resume.md/&quot;&gt;resume.md&lt;/a&gt; files I used in my demo site, you need to erase two bits of code from each of these pages. Erase &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;include&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;icon-github.html&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;username=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&quot;jekyll&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;%}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; from both pages and erase &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;include&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;icon-github.html&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;username=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&quot;jekyll&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;%}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; from both pages. (The Minima theme knew how to handle those calls to include icon images, but the Hacker theme doesn’t, so they will make your site not run.)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Hacker theme doesn’t automatically add pages to a header menu (like the Minima theme did), but you can still access your pages by typing in their URL, e.g. by visiting &lt;a href=&quot;https://amandavisconti.github.io/JekyllDemoThemed/about&quot;&gt;https://amandavisconti.github.io/JekyllDemoThemed/about&lt;/a&gt; for the &lt;a href=&quot;http://about.md/&quot;&gt;about.md&lt;/a&gt; page. You can also add links to these into your theme or the &lt;a href=&quot;http://index.md/&quot;&gt;index.md&lt;/a&gt; page. I often try to find another theme that has a feature I want—such as a fancy header menu—and then copy and paste pieces of its code into my site by trial and error. &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllthemes.org/&quot;&gt;The Jekyll Themes site&lt;/a&gt; is a great place to look, and trial-and-error copying and pasting from other themes is a great way to get more familiar with how your site works.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That should do it! You can compare your site look and files with mine, if needed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My new demo site using the Hacker theme: &lt;a href=&quot;https://amandavisconti.github.io/JekyllDemoThemed/&quot;&gt;https://amandavisconti.github.io/JekyllDemoThemed/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The repo containing the code that runs the hacker demo site:
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/amandavisconti/jekylldemothemed&quot;&gt;https://github.com/amandavisconti/jekylldemothemed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 04 Feb 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2017/02/04/building-research-website-with-jekyll-githubpages-theming</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2017/02/04/building-research-website-with-jekyll-githubpages-theming</guid>
        
        <category>digital-humanities</category>
        
        <category>scholarly-web-design-and-coding</category>
        
        <category>advice-tutorial</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Buying digital humanities hardware (a proposal for an archival DH 3D scanner and 3D printer)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Early last year, I wrote a (successfully funded!) proposal for my department (Purdue Libraries) to purchase 3D scanning and printing equipment dedicated to archival digital humanities research. This was in response to a call to appropriately use some outstanding funds remaining in an equipment-funding account; the audience was department administration. I’m sharing the proposal now &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/tag/meta-dh/&quot;&gt;as part of a series of posts documenting practical, administrative, and infrastructural work that makes DH go&lt;/a&gt;. If you’re interested in possible DH applications of 3D printing, or more generally in researching and making a case for DH equipment, I hope this post is useful to you!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/BigTicketRequest_DigitalHumanitiesArchival3DSetup.pdf&quot;&gt;You can see the actual PDF I submitted here&lt;/a&gt;, if you prefer reading that to the blog post transcript below (it includes the budget and cost comparisons I didn’t feel like reformatting to paste into the blog text).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I try to start any proposal with a summary—this one has too long of a summary, and too long of an overall document. I was new to how the department handles purchase requests, and wanted to preemptively answer expected questions (e.g. you can see that I’m both trying to explain what 3D technology does and why purchasing it for open maker space service wasn’t my initial goal). I now try to keep reports and requests to a single page that’s easily skiable for key points like cost, value, and timeline, but I think this writeup might still be useful to someone seeking to familiarize their team with DH uses of 3D printing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Notes:&lt;/em&gt; Redactions are summarized [in brackets]—these are things where specific names were involved or ideas that we might want to use in competitive grant proposals. The “ASC” is Purdue’s Virginia Kelly Karnes Archives &amp;amp; Special Collections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;big-ticket-request-digital-humanities-3d-setup&quot;&gt;Big Ticket Request: Digital Humanities 3D Setup&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Summary/definition of 3D terms&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;General plans for the 3D Setup&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Location&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;IT support&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ASC support&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Budget&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Why not use the Engineering Library 3D setup?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Examples of possible projects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;summarydefinition-of-3d-terms&quot;&gt;Summary/definition of 3D terms&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I propose a dedicated setup for digital humanities 3D &lt;em&gt;scanning, modeling, and printing&lt;/em&gt; as research and
teaching:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3D scanning&lt;/strong&gt; lets you capture a three-dimensional digital model of an object such as a spacesuit or a model plane (much like a flat scanner lets you capture a two-dimensional model of a book page).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3D modeling&lt;/strong&gt; uses that scanning to create a digital object you can manipulate, label, and otherwise augment on a computer. (&lt;em&gt;3D models don’t necessarily need to be printed to be useful; for example, we could scan a model airplane propeller and then create a digital animation of the propeller in use.&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3D printing&lt;/strong&gt; produces three-dimensional physical, tangible objects representing either actual artifacts or visualizations of data:
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Artifacts:&lt;/strong&gt; Print out in plastic (or other materials) a three-dimensional copy of the original object (or a miniature, magnified, or otherwise altered version) for display and handling, further research (e.g. with previously hard-to-decipher engravings or texture), and experimentation (e.g comparison of behavior of historical airplane propellers by printing and powering miniature versions).&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Visualizations:&lt;/strong&gt; Digital files can also be created from scratch to produce 3D visualizations such as timelines, graphs, globes, and scale models (e.g. create a 3D model of a historic satellite orbit that can be viewed from multiple angles).&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The DH Center’s 3D printing setup would support &lt;em&gt;research&lt;/em&gt;, with a focus on how to best scan, digitally model and animate, and print facsimiles of archival and humanities artifacts for research and teaching use. Much of our time will be spent experimenting with scanner, printer, and software settings to produce accurately representative 3D models, and it is critical that researchers have full access to the equipment to do this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Requested funding:&lt;/strong&gt;  $7596.98 (see budget below)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Questions:&lt;/strong&gt;  Amanda Visconti (aviscont@purdue.edu)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;general-plans-for-the-3d-setup&quot;&gt;General plans for the 3D Setup&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Initial internal experimentation:&lt;/strong&gt; A one-year initial trial period will focus on experimenting with ASC artifacts suggested by the archivists, and on documenting best practices for creating accurate and useful digital and physical facsimiles for use in further DH research and teaching.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DH project use:&lt;/strong&gt; After this trial period, we will also begin to support humanities projects around campus that require our specific setup rather than the Engineering Library’s current printing service (e.g. a history class where students digitally “repair”, extend, label, or animate historicalartifacts using a computer). This outreach will be on the same case-by-case basis as other collaborative projects proposed to the DH Center, rather than as a drop-in service.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;External collaborations:&lt;/strong&gt; [grant project idea]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;location&quot;&gt;Location&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The setup will be located in the future DH Center; until that space is inaugurated, the setup will be located
in the DH Specialist’s office (table along the wall opposite the door).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;it-support&quot;&gt;IT support&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;IT for the setup will be entirely supported by the Digital Humanities Specialist (installation, support, maintenance). The DH Specialist would develop a contract with Libraries IT to record this understanding.
This is an excellent test case to create a workflow for DH in the libraries that includes DH control and
support for software, hardware, and policies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;asc-support&quot;&gt;ASC support&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have discussed a possible 3D setup with [colleagues] in the ASC, and they have helped me identify specific artifacts and collections that would benefit from 3D support. We will collaborate on a workflow for secure handling and scanning on any ASC artifacts to be scanned, and think about how future ASC processing workflows might include capturing 3D digital model files of artifacts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;budget&quot;&gt;Budget&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Research into appropriate equipment included speaking with humanists doing archaeological and archival
3D work at [institutions]. We’re attempting to strike a balance between the cheapest options (assuming in the short run we’d need to upgrade to intermediate options, costing more total) and highest grade options (e.g. the $25k Artec Spider might one day be useful, but I’d want several years of prior 3D work, successful class and research use, and external funding for an investment that large). &lt;strong&gt;Total requested: $7596.98.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/BigTicketRequest_DigitalHumanitiesArchival3DSetup.pdf&quot;&gt;For the budget table and cost comparisons, see this PDF of the request (pasting it into the post was taking too much time).&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Future possible costs that will be supported from DH Specialist startup funding and other sources:&lt;/em&gt; protected cart for bringing artifacts from ASC; blue painter’s tape for printing bed improvement, sink for cleanup; ventilation/fan; table covering; dedicated computer, monitor, keyboard, mouse, cables; lockable space for storage; shared ASC+DH graduate research assistant to assist with project design, 3D work, training others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-not-use-the-engineering-library-3d-setup&quot;&gt;Why not use the Engineering Library 3D setup?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Libraries already supports a 3D &lt;em&gt;printing&lt;/em&gt; setup in the Engineering Library, but for various reasons this is not adequate for digital humanities &lt;em&gt;scanning, modeling, and printing&lt;/em&gt; work:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Most of our research focus with the dedicated 3D setup will revolve around calibrating and customizing the setup to create accurate, representative facsimiles of historical artifacts, which requires DH and ASC experts to have hands-on oversight of the process. 3D printing setup in the Engineering Library is designed as a &lt;em&gt;service&lt;/em&gt; producing finished print-outs to those who submit files, rather than letting you calibrate settings and experiment to make the most representative facsimile for your given research use.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;DH research use necessitates iterative experimentation; the listed wait time for a print from the Engineering Library setup is up to a week.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Transporting rare and fragile artifacts safely and securely from the ASC is simplified by keeping the equipment in-building. Future ASC processing workflows might include capturing 3D digital model files of artifacts.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This expertise will allow experimentation focused toward publishing best practices for &lt;em&gt;humanities&lt;/em&gt; research, without competition from other (e.g. STEM) uses of existing equipment and without needing to constantly recalibrate from others using the equipment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;examples-of-possible-projects&quot;&gt;Examples of possible projects&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ideas that could be developed into full lesson plans, courses, or collaborative DH projects seeking external funding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;General classroom use&lt;/strong&gt;. The 3D setup will allow students to have a dedicated space to explore digital interactions with the objects in ASC’s rich collections, where humanities students and faculty could experiment directly with the machines while getting archivists’ support in handling items and negotiating file/image reuse/sharing/copyright.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A classroom module would be designed around scanning some of the more interestingly structured Flight/Space Archive artifacts, such as Neil Armstrong’s model of a lunar landing module. Students would then be able to access, extend, and handle these artifacts extensively without damaging the original artifact and with options such as printing magnified versions of an object to better assess its texture and structure.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[A specific professor’s] course around writing historical material object analyses currently asks students to write about a speculative archival artifact; we could support students creating and printing these speculative artifacts, possibly by combining digital files of real artifacts into a chimera object.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use 3D facial models for a direct connection with historical personages that would be otherwise difficult to gain, beginning with our John Purdue death mask. [Possible research project idea.]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How close can we get 3D models and printing to the originals?&lt;/strong&gt; Teaching archival concerns around authenticity, materiality, and representation (e.g. presentation differs depending on what significant property you’re focusing on) through experimentation with equipment calibration, materials, and post-printing processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How can 3D scanning and modeling improve current archival processing workflows?&lt;/strong&gt; Augment existing digital collection items with 3D files; interactive 360+ degrees animations of artifacts; packaged lesson plans for K-16 including videos explaining archival artifacts, their details, differences in models, and possible discussion questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Students “adopt” significant artifacts to explore multiple paths of documenting, describing, narrating, and the metadata and narratives they create are incorporated into the archive for future learners.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How can we meet the need for archival facsimiles?&lt;/strong&gt; Meet the need for exhibits around Purdue and ASC history for external institutions (e.g. recent Indianapolis Symphony exhibit), the West/Lafayette community, and Purdue’s 2019 dual 50th moon landing / 150th Purdue founding anniversaries. Create facsimiles for hand-outs at Libraries and Alumni events, to pique interest in humanities projects and ASC collections (e.g. wearable facsimiles of Amelia Earhart’s flight goggles, possibly with add-on to hold smartphones a la Google Cardboard and display related Purdue history projects or apps).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tangibility.&lt;/strong&gt; The ability to touch and manipulate objects and representations of data inspires the curiosity and questions of learners. Additionally, tangibility adds accessibility to visualizations, timelines, maps, and graphs for the visually challenged. Building on existing museum work allowing visitor access to facsimiles (e.g. the Art Institute of Chicago offers a range of sculpture with which visitors can feel the differences of various materials and compare the effects of erosion over time), we will attempt to make the learning and research outcomes of tangible access to artifacts more rigorous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Improving active participation with research involving rare and fragile artifacts.&lt;/strong&gt; In addition to increasing access to artifacts, 3D scanning and printing would allow those without archival training to directly handle a fragile object like Neil Armstrong’s model lunar lander module, experiencing first-hand detail, dimensions, and texture. But students could do much more than just touch these artifacts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Digital 3D versions of, for example, the lunar module model can be explored on a computer: magnified to better see details (the Smithsonian was actually able to read eroded engravings on old armor by scanning the armor and then manipulating the scan file on a computer), included in animated tutorials (historical airplane propellers and windflow; orbit paths), labeled and cross-sectioned, and digitally manipulated (e.g. students could see what a statue missing a piece would look like in its complete state, or digital files for objects on which colors had faded or washed away could be colored again).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;These same activities could also happen with the printed-out plastic copy of an artifact.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Access to off-campus artifacts.&lt;/strong&gt; The purchased scanner will be reasonably mobile, so that scans of artifacts held off-campus (e.g. in museums in an astronaut’s hometown) can be made when ASC staff visit them, then brought back to campus and printed so that a class can tangibly experience a remote artifact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Copies of these artifacts could be printed here on-demand when a class requires, and kept for future use by the teacher of that class (we could also provide storage to “check out” already printed versions of artifacts, but we expect teachers will like having their own copy of a few key artifacts to use frequently in their own teaching).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Improving world access to Purdue’s artifacts.&lt;/strong&gt; Purdue Libraries could host downloadable 3D image files of some of our ASC’s artifacts; we’d begin by identifying 5 key objects that are some combination of highly interesting and difficult for non-archivists to access (rare, fragile, not well represented by photograph).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;[Grant project idea]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Specific ASC collections or artifacts tagged for projects include:&lt;/strong&gt;  a 3D tour of the ASC vault, pliable/wearable 3D print of the lunar glove, Earhart flight suit, historical planes/propellers, artists’ books, Armstrong lunar lander module model. Anything that is fragile, rare, dangerous (lunar dust, jet fuel…) in the ASC—things that students or even researchers can’t currently touch or see. Anything in the ASC that would benefit from a cross-section (even if the insides don’t exist or can’tbe scanned, because these can be digitally modeled) or demonstration of them item in context and/or in use (historic propellers).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 31 Jan 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2017/01/31/2017-01-31-3D-digitalhumanities-proposal</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2017/01/31/2017-01-31-3D-digitalhumanities-proposal</guid>
        
        <category>digital-humanities</category>
        
        <category>meta-dh</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Designing a Digital Humanities Initiative: Background &amp; Campus DH Survey</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m designing a digital humanities (DH) initiative here at the Purdue University Libraries, and “initiative” means our whole vision for DH, support for which is now enshrined as a specific point in our department strategic policy. To kick off &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/tag/meta-dh/&quot;&gt;a series of blog posts&lt;/a&gt; covering this infrastructure and community design work I’ve been up to, this post provides some background to the policies and plans I’ll be sharing in later writing, as well as a some of the findings of the campus DH climate survey I conducted over the past year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-role--the-purdue-libraries&quot;&gt;My role &amp;amp; the Purdue Libraries&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m a digital humanities assistant professor and specialist librarian in the Purdue University Libraries. The Libraries here is its own department, including faculty who can teach in other departments. We don’t have an academic program of our own for listing courses within the Libraries, and I don’t believe anyone has a required teaching load. The norm for our faculty and many of our professional staff is to frequently teach/co-teach formal courses, or to do other sorts of teaching and training like leading skill workshops or visiting classes to present “one-shot” lectures on a specific topic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;purdue&quot;&gt;Purdue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Purdue is a Big 10 research university located in West Lafayette, Indiana (an hour northwest of Indianapolis, three hours south of Chicago). My role is focused on designing and realizing our DH initiative (as well as pursuing personal research and achieving tenure, but as my interests tend to community design and infrastructure these days, both parts of the role overlap). I started the role last August—you can read &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2016/02/28/DHjobtalk&quot;&gt;my job talk&lt;/a&gt; in this post, and here’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/assets/DigitalHumanitiesSpecialist.pdf&quot;&gt;the ad for the position&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dh-in-the-purdue-libraries&quot;&gt;DH in the Purdue Libraries&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Purdue has past and existing DH activity, such as History Professor &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/blackdigitalhum&quot;&gt;Kim Gallon&lt;/a&gt;’s extensive work including the &lt;a href=&quot;http://blackpressresearchcollective.org/&quot;&gt;Black Press Research Collective&lt;/a&gt;, recent NEH Institute for Advanced Topics in DH on &lt;a href=&quot;Space and Place in Africana/Black Studies&quot;&gt;Space and Place in Africana/Black Studies&lt;/a&gt; co-organized with Hamilton Professor Angel David Nieves, and a &lt;a href=&quot;http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/55&quot;&gt;recent chapter in &lt;em&gt;Debates in DH.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Another DHer is English Professor Dino Felluga, whose work includes Victorian textual scholarship and the development of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.branchcollective.org/&quot;&gt;BRANCH Collective&lt;/a&gt; as a scholarly publishing alternative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recent DH hiring.&lt;/strong&gt; Libraries department was deliberately slow in hiring for DH, instead waiting and observing as these roles began to proliferate at other institutions. Waiting a bit let the department identify problems with those roles’ designs as these issues became more obvious and slightly more avoidable. The Library Loon’s “&lt;a href=&quot;http://gavialib.com/2011/12/the-c-word/&quot;&gt;Coordinator Syndrome&lt;/a&gt;” seems to be a frequent complaint of the solo DH “&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/elotroalex/status/709495906790408194&quot;&gt;Miracle Worker&lt;/a&gt;” hire (to use &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/elotroalex&quot;&gt;Alex Gil&lt;/a&gt;’s term), and Miriam Posner’s piece &lt;a href=&quot;http://miriamposner.com/blog/money-and-time/&quot;&gt;on DH shortstaffing&lt;/a&gt; and its resulting tiring out of DHers identifies a widespread issue. The Purdue Libraries were able to address some of these issues in the job ad (it’s a tenure-track faculty position, so the research background they required is rewarded by strong support for continuing to do that research), and awareness of other issues is helping me not overextend myself or my scope for the DH we commit to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A healthy department&lt;/strong&gt;. Because Purdue Libraries has a strong ethos of collaboration over service from the dean on down, I’ve been able to enter into reasonable collaborations based on my assessment of projects and people, rather than feel pressured to fulfill all service requests. I deliberately gave &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2016/02/28/DHjobtalk&quot;&gt;my job talk here&lt;/a&gt; on why a collaboration rather than a service model for our DH would be better for everyone, to gauge what their valuing of collaboration meant. The dean’s first comment after I completed my talk was to encourage me to move &lt;em&gt;even closer&lt;/em&gt; to the collaboration end of the collaboration-service spectrum than I’d articulated. It’s empowering to be enfranchised to say “no” to requests that aren’t appropriate to your role or that you don’t have time for, and to define the scope of your role and the DH group you represent. I wish more departments relied enough on the expertise of the DHers they hire to allow these experts to define the terms of their role, and to define where the department’s funding and hiring abilities limit what they can accomplish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;designing-a-libraries-dh-initiative-basic-questions&quot;&gt;Designing a Libraries DH initiative: basic questions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The culmination of my first eight months on the job was to present a proposal for just what we should be doing with our DH initiative (this will be shared in my future posts!). The user testing and project management aspects of my DH experience helped me address questions like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How do we (as Purdue Libraries, and as a DH initiative inside the department) &lt;strong&gt;define ourselves&lt;/strong&gt;, rather than letting others define us?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;At the same time, how do we &lt;strong&gt;listen to and acknowledge others needs for DH&lt;/strong&gt;? How do we responsibly and ethically solicit feedback and advice on campus DH needs? (As &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Literature_Geek/status/774225208676872193&quot;&gt;a librarian&lt;/a&gt; and as a human, I hope I respect the right to privacy and full informed consent in any whose behavior we want to study.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There are many existing and potential audiences for DH on campus, and many desires for what DH can do for those audiences. &lt;strong&gt;We can’t be everyone’s DH&lt;/strong&gt;, and trying to do so will make sure we fail at doing particular things well. We need to balance among doing specific kinds of DH well, and connecting and encouraging people and projects on campus that advance other aspects of DH. How do we define a limited scope for the DH we do?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How do we communicate what our DH means to campus? What kind of public policies and workflows can we design to &lt;strong&gt;communicate what we do and don’t do&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How can we define ourselves not just with some over-general definition of DH (e.g. “we support innovation in humanities via digital scholarship”), but instead &lt;strong&gt;envision the DH we want to work toward&lt;/strong&gt;—making that vision our mission? How do we &lt;strong&gt;stay honest to the values we think we hold by acting on them&lt;/strong&gt; through policies for the kinds of collaboration, education, and other efforts we focus on?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the course of last year, I’ve constantly reshaped how I answer these questions as I learned more about Purdue’s current and past DH culture, resources, and scholars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;campus-dh-survey&quot;&gt;Campus DH survey&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I keep notes on the campus interactions that are part of my role—who I talked to, the conversation topic, the date. These notes are useful for tenure and review purposes (e.g. I can say how many DH consultations I provided in a term, and what departments I’ve been reaching; and I can remember what we talked about or project ideas we brainstormed when we pick up the thread weeks or months later). I’m currently using a Google Spreadsheet for this, but I’ve heard of others using business CRMs (customer management software) to keep track of their campus interactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These interaction records let me take a year of talking and listening (and sometimes asking direct questions about what people want for campus DH) and aggregate these conversations into an overview of our current DH climate on campus, identifying…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;campus-strengths-to-build-on&quot;&gt;Campus strengths to build on&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We already have a number of existing strengths right on campus for doing DH well:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My Libraries department has a strong commitment to &lt;strong&gt;collaboration over service&lt;/strong&gt; (e.g. our dean encourages Libraries faculty to collaborate on grant projects with other campus faculty as PIs or co-PIs). From successful collaborations like the IMPACT Program and two rounds of Mellon funding for “grand challenge” research teams that must include a campus librarian, the campus is already aware of us as potential collaborators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve been pre-emptive in &lt;strong&gt;defining&lt;/strong&gt; what the Libraries is, rather than letting pre-conceived notions of what a campus library does shape our strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From my first conversations with my colleagues, we’ve discussed our DH initiative as providing an interdisciplinary space where we help train people to spread DH knowledge; connect, amplify, and record existing DH; and support other campus communities in imagining and implementing their own local DH. I feel supported in trying at most to develop &lt;strong&gt;a campus hub for DH, rather than trying to hoard (or be all) DH&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our strategic plan includes improving information &lt;strong&gt;access, diversity, and inclusion&lt;/strong&gt;, so my desire to focus on a DH advancing these goals is tied into our department’s founding document. (&lt;em&gt;More on this in later posts on identifying our values and translating these to policies and projects&lt;/em&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many units and roles already exist in the Libraries that support &lt;strong&gt;areas overlapping or adjacent with DH&lt;/strong&gt;, such as our humanities specialist librarians, Digital Programs, Research Data,  our three repositories (PURR, e-Pubs, and e-Archives), the Purdue University Press and Scholarly Publishing Services (which are situated within the Libraries), our Engineering Library’s makerspace, Archives and Special Collections resources and staff research and teaching expertise, a GIS Specialist Librarian and GIS Analyst, and Libraries IT.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are strong &lt;strong&gt;collaborations among these Libraries units&lt;/strong&gt;, too, such as previous course co-taught by the Head of Scholarly Publishing and a faculty librarian where students published a print book based on research in the Archives and Special Collections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of these collaborations were &lt;strong&gt;perfectly set up to add a DH component&lt;/strong&gt;; in particular, collaborating with my colleagues in our Archives and Special Collections and our University Press and Scholarly Publishing Services has helped us work toward a better ASC-&amp;gt;DH-&amp;gt;Press workflow. We’re now exploring how we can make research and teaching with our ASC collections and experts flow into DH teaching, research, and publication forms, and how do these both have a natural extension to the Press’ interest in innovative scholarly communication and born-digital publication?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A history of &lt;strong&gt;well-known and well-funded campus DH research&lt;/strong&gt;: in particular, History Professor Kim Gallon’s and English Professor Dino Felluga’s respective grants-winning scholarship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Collaborative work with other campus DH faculty&lt;/strong&gt; from the start of my job, including successfully co-PIing two grant proposals during my second month here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;strong&gt;decent faculty interest in DH&lt;/strong&gt; in our liberal arts and interdisciplinary studies departments (e.g. ~25 CLA faculty attended a meeting on DH despite it being held during the end of term).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interest from these departments in DH’s contribution to &lt;strong&gt;alternative academic career&lt;/strong&gt; mentorship and teaching for students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A number of &lt;strong&gt;past courses on or including DH&lt;/strong&gt;, and a number of past courses taught, co-taught, or otherwise supported by Libraries staff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The university’s Honors College as &lt;strong&gt;a space for Libraries faculty to propose and list their own courses&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Existing student DH activity&lt;/strong&gt;, such as graduate student independent projects and GA work, student DH and tech working groups in several humanities departments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;campus-needs-dh-might-address&quot;&gt;Campus needs DH might address&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve also identified areas where the Libraries DH initiative can address campus needs, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DH is happening on campus, but largely among collaborators who found each other by chance rather than some kind of DH collaboration support network or center. We don’t yet have a DH Center or other entity that &lt;strong&gt;connects DH on campus&lt;/strong&gt;, to help researchers make connections to other people, get feedback on ideas, or mentorship around learning DH. I’m proposing we act as this connecting hub both through a virtual DH@Purdue website and through a physical space (a DH lab that may eventually become a center).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A resource linking existing or past campus DH projects as well as &lt;strong&gt;modeling different DH project method and publication possibilities&lt;/strong&gt; is needed. (That DH@Purdue website I mentioned.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We don’t have a place safekeeping &lt;strong&gt;institutional memory for DH&lt;/strong&gt; (e.g. no one can easily answer how many DH courses have been taught in the last decade). It can be difficult to &lt;strong&gt;communicate DH workshops, events, or course listings&lt;/strong&gt; to everyone who might be interested in these offerings. (That DH@Purdue website, as well as starting communication sources like the #PurdueDH hashtag, a listserv for event announcements and collaboration requests, and an RSS feed for new DH resources as I add them to the website, mostly directly from DH Twitter.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We could do more to develop and participate in &lt;strong&gt;regional DH&lt;/strong&gt; (e.g. with IU, IUPUI, Notre Dame, Ball State), and particularly with IUPUI’s HILT training and THATCamp Indiana. (E.g. inviting speakers, attending nearby events, conference calls with set topics, creating a regional channel on &lt;a href=&quot;http://tinyurl.com/DHslack&quot;&gt;the DH Slack&lt;/a&gt;?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of our digitized resources could use DHer input to identify the kinds of metadata and processing that would make &lt;strong&gt;DH teaching and research reuse&lt;/strong&gt; easiest. Some of our digitized resources are well-used, but in ways that suggest addition of DH methods such as an annotation framework could further support this use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Students and faculty want easy ways to create websites that include maps, timelines, and annotation. I’ve heard interest in learning Omeka, Neatline, and Scalar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those with funding for DH projects but without technical experience or interest, not knowing &lt;strong&gt;where to find skilled collaborators&lt;/strong&gt; with these characteristics is an issue. (The College of Liberal Arts started a directory of student workers with IT skills in the past, but it proved difficult to keep up-to-date.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some CLA faculty and students aren’t aware of how they might benefit from some Libraries resources, which are sometimes &lt;strong&gt;pitched toward a STEM audience&lt;/strong&gt; or use terms unfamiliar to humanities scholars (e.g. our repository for research datasets has few humanities collections). Part of my work will be translating what our various units, experts, and resources offer to humanists and DHers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to address findings like these, while at the same time &lt;strong&gt;encouraging other departments to fully invest in DH&lt;/strong&gt; through their own hiring and policies. For example, some of the DHy needs I heard expressed were more oriented toward IT service or digital pedagogy expertise, and the best solution would be making our advice available for those departments during their job design and hiring process for such positions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-dh-response-to-this-campus-survey&quot;&gt;A DH response to this campus survey&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My next &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/tag/meta-dh/&quot;&gt;meta-DH&lt;/a&gt; post will discuss identifying the values and goals for our DH initiative, and how those translated into my initial proposal to the department. Thanks for reading, and let me know any questions &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Literature_Geek&quot;&gt;@Literature_Geek&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 09 Sep 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2016/09/11/designing-digital-humanities-initiative-background-campus-survey</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2016/09/11/designing-digital-humanities-initiative-background-campus-survey</guid>
        
        <category>digital-humanities</category>
        
        <category>meta-dh</category>
        
        <category>dh-now</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Meta-DH, or Designing and Building a DH Initiative</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/tag/meta-dh/&quot;&gt;starting a “meta-DH” series of blog posts&lt;/a&gt; to document my work developing a digital humanities initiative here in the Libraries at Purdue University. This work includes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;figuring out what our DH could and should be&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;creating a DH physical space (center? lab? something else?)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the practical considerations of layout and budgeting&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;designing policies and infrastructure for the initiative&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;building DH projects both to test our policies and to model the kinds of scholarship our methods realize&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve been on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.literaturegeek.com&quot;&gt;this blog&lt;/a&gt; before, you might have noticed that I enjoy blogging and other user-friendly &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/tag/advice-tutorial/&quot;&gt;documentation&lt;/a&gt; of DH scholarship. This style of writing helps me think, with the bonus that sometimes that thinking is useful to others. Blogging can also lead to feedback on resources I should check out, potential collaborators, and what I’m doing wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first year on the job meant writing a lot of GoogleDocs and other semi-private stuff: taking notes on meetings and consultations, recording ideas for projects, and explaining my plans to administration. To communicate more clearly (and use my colleagues’ generous donation of their reading time well), I summarize—meaning I generate a lot of documentation that hasn’t reached anyone else yet. I think the non-condensed versions of these ideas could be useful to someone. Thus, this series of posts!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll probably blog:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;✔️ &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2016/02/28/DHjobtalk&quot;&gt;The job talk that put me in this role (already blogged earlier this year)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Creating the website for our DH initiative&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;✔️ &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2016/09/11/designing-digital-humanities-initiative-background-campus-survey&quot;&gt;What I learned during my first year in this role: doing a campus DH survey&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Making good time &amp;amp; resource investments while designing campus DH&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How I’ve interpreted my job description&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Working with my faculty review committee to receive credit for my various kinds of DHy scholarship&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Daily practices (my office setup, software used, consultations, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;DH program identity and choosing what to call our initiative (center? lab? should we even have a physical space?)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My formal DH initiative proposal to department administration&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Designing and following through on a DH mission statement&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Partnerships and collaboration&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Defining DH scope&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Designing timelines and funding requests&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Creating a DH space: layout, equipment, budget&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Grant proposals and sustainable models&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there’s something not on that list you’d like to read about, let me know on Twitter &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.twitter.com/literature_geek&quot;&gt;@literature_geek&lt;/a&gt; or by email aviscont@purdue.edu.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2016/09/05/meta-dh</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2016/09/05/meta-dh</guid>
        
        <category>digital-humanities</category>
        
        <category>advice-tutorial</category>
        
        <category>meta-dh</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
