<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Literature Geek</title>
    <description>digital humanities</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2019 14:06:02 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2019 14:06:02 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.7.4</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>20% Time: Why we make self-initiated research &amp; development part of the job</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Crossposted at &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/&quot;&gt;the Scholars’ Lab blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All Scholars’ Lab staff are encouraged to take 20% of their time to initiate research and professional development. In this post, we’ll share some of what we’ve been working on, and explain the rationale behind making this 20% time a formal part of our job descriptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-20-time&quot;&gt;What is 20% time?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Previously also referred to as “personal R&amp;amp;D time”, we’ve recently shifted to saying &lt;strong&gt;“self-initiated R&amp;amp;D time”&lt;/strong&gt; to emphasize that this work is often collaborative, and always feeds back into the lab: what’s unique about 20% time is special leeway to experiment and fail, and formal support for staff to initiate and direct their own professional and scholarly development on the job. Making this a specific job expectation can help folks feel comfortable pursuing learning that isn’t immediately applicable to scholarship, but probably will be later on. For example, GIS Specialist Drew Macqueen’s “Arduino Chris” (GIF below, courtesy of Drew) used the problem of our office lights (which turn off when folks weren’t moving around much at their desks) to get some practice building electronics, which he can now apply to research consultations and collaborations as part of his spatial technologies toolkit:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/scholarslab/scholarslab.org/blob/master/assets/post-media/2019-01-22-Arduino-Chris.GIF?raw=true&quot; alt=&quot;GIF of Drew Macqueen's &amp;quot;Arduino Chris&amp;quot;, using electronics and a photo of GIS Specialist Chris Gist to turn the office lights back on when they go off from no one moving around.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Above: GIF of Drew Macqueen’s “Arduino Chris”, using electronics and a photo of GIS Specialist Chris Gist to turn the office lights back on when they go off from no one moving around.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that “R&amp;amp;D time” (aka 20% time, personal R&amp;amp;D time, self-initiated R&amp;amp;D time) is distinct from the work of our Research &amp;amp; Development (R&amp;amp;D) unit, which focuses on programming and design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-kinds-of-work-can-it-be-used-for&quot;&gt;What kinds of work can it be used for?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with our other staff work, we hold our use of 20% time to the following 3 commitments (also outlined in our &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/charter/&quot;&gt;team charter&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;At any moment, we should be able to &lt;strong&gt;relate our projects to the larger missions&lt;/strong&gt; of the Scholars’ Lab, the Library, and the University as a whole.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We should be able to &lt;strong&gt;articulate the interest and value&lt;/strong&gt; of our individual and collaborative work.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Our projects – including projects undertaken with UVa faculty and grads – are expected to &lt;strong&gt;enter public conversation&lt;/strong&gt; and to &lt;strong&gt;be shared as broadly as possible&lt;/strong&gt;. We have an expansive and evolving notion of valid “publication” events and public outcomes. We value open source code and open access information.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-is-self-initiated-rd-a-good-investment-in-our-staff&quot;&gt;How is self-initiated R&amp;amp;D a good investment in our staff?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of our greatest strengths is our team of experts, folks with deep scholarly and professional training and experience across the disciplines. Every one of us embodies what I think of as &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/about/#who-are-the-scholars-in-scholars-lab&quot;&gt;full scholarship&lt;/a&gt;—internationally recognized research, combined with a passion for teaching, community care, and social justice that’s necessary for research to function as scholarship. Our department, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.library.virginia.edu/&quot;&gt;UVA Library&lt;/a&gt;, makes an unusually (perhaps uniquely, within DH?) strong investment in digital and experiment scholarship through hard-money (i.e. not grant-dependent) funding of 12 full-time employees in the Scholars’ Lab, plus 1 part-time employee (a full-time UVA staffer, with part of their FTE bought out from the English Department by the Library), and 1 full-time grant-funded employee. Given that Centernet (the international organization of DH centers) defines DH centers with 5+ FTEs as “large”, we are rich indeed in this most important of scholarly resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Self-initiated R&amp;amp;D time helps us make the best use of that staff investment. Formally committing to allowing on-the-job professional development is diffrent than requiring staff to make special proposals to their supervisors if they want to write a paper, learn a skill, or try something that may or may not pan out. Our staff need to stay at the forefront of experimental and digital scholarship, if they’re to do their best in nurturing and collaborating on the campus community’s research in these areas. Often, that means work that may or may not prove to have a scholarly application at UVA (but we wouldn’t know unless we tried).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Former Scholars’ Lab Director Bethany Nowviskie notes, “For software developers, who can command larger salaries outside the academy, [20% time is] a much-valued perk. For alt-ac staff, who trained as scholars, it is almost a psychological necessity” (Nowviskie, 2012, &lt;a href=&quot;http://nowviskie.org/2012/too-small-to-fail/&quot;&gt;“Too Small to Fail”&lt;/a&gt;). 20% time lets us hire and retain folks with strong backgrounds in research and self-initiated experimentation. If we require these skills in a job ad, why wouldn’t we want to structure the role to help staff continue strengthening such work once on the job?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our current staff includes 2 UVA general faculty members, 1 UVA full professor, 3 staff with humanities Ph.D.s, 5 additional staff with Ph.D. A.B.D.s, and 3 staff with terminal M.L.S.s, in addition to professional training and certification in areas such as project management, and teaching as UVA instructors of record. Formal R&amp;amp;D time not only supports strong hiring and retention, it also helps our staff remain or become scholars themselves, so that they can bring that experience to their interactions with other faculty, staff, and student scholars on campus: “R&amp;amp;D time is the thing that ensures that the Scholars’ Lab… can become an interesting intellectual community in its own right, and be perceived as such by our colleagues on the teaching faculty” (Nowviskie). Note that this is important for all our staff, not just those holding degrees or hired with explicit research work in their job description; this “helps the SLab along in our ambition to function as a team of equals—a family, with shared, long-term commitments to our mission together” (Nowviskie).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-is-self-initiated-rd-good-for-not-only-the-lab-but-for-the-library-and-uva-as-well&quot;&gt;How is self-initiated R&amp;amp;D good for not only the Lab, but for the Library and UVA as well?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bethany Nowviskie wrote comprehensively and persuasively about the importance of 20% time, back in 2012 in &lt;a href=&quot;http://nowviskie.org/2012/too-small-to-fail/&quot;&gt;“Too Small to Fail”&lt;/a&gt;, particularly in the section titled “Scholar-Practitioners”. I strongly recommend you read her piece if you’re considering asking for R&amp;amp;D time, supporting colleagues in an R&amp;amp;D time pilot, or have doubts about 20% time being a good choice. In addition to narrating the UVA DH history that led to the formation of the Lab, and the Lab’s rationale for investing heavily in grad students, Bethany covers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A specific 20% time use that went on to impact many libraries: Project Blacklight (“solve[d] a serious problem for libraries dependent on expensive and inflexible vendor-provided catalog interfaces”)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How 20% time helps improve existing projects &amp;amp; create new ones (e.g. our NEH-funded tool for telling stories in space and time, &lt;a href=&quot;https://neatline.org&quot;&gt;Neatline&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Google’s popularization of 20% time in industry, where DH centers frequently lose technical staff&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Scholars’ Lab’s self-initiated R&amp;amp;D time has now been adopted at other DH centers and labs (e.g. Princeton) &amp;amp; is cited as a best practice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Helps us retain a healthy, sustainable working environment: “I’ve watched too many digital humanities centers and projects balloon and then seem to lose their direction, getting caught up in soft-money scrambles and taking on work that is less than ideal for them, just to keep good staff employed” (Nowviskie)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;As Bethany argues, it’s &lt;em&gt;just good&lt;/em&gt;. We work to treat our staff as the experts they are, give them some guidelines but trust them to lead on what/when/where their best work happens, invest in them as humans who love to learn. Not because it’s good for the institution’s missions (although it very much is!), but because we need to take responsibility for making our institutions and communities better at caring for and celebrating people.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our implementation of 20% time directly supports the strategic direction illustrated in UVA Library’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://static.lib.virginia.edu/directory/media/UL3rdCent.pdf&quot;&gt;“Library Entering Its Third Century”&lt;/a&gt; recommendations, particularly: “Deepen subject and methodological expertise across the Library by &lt;strong&gt;developing a culture of R&amp;amp;D&lt;/strong&gt; that strengthens our ability to contribute to the research, scholarly, and artistic enterprise of the University”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;show-me-some-projects&quot;&gt;Show me some projects!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In March 2018, we started what I hope can be an annual practice: getting the team together to eat pizza and share about the self-initiated R&amp;amp;D we’re working on. It was lovely; we easily used up two hours asking questions and making suggestions about future work. (12 of our staff were able to attend, so that’s roughly ten minutes per person.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the staff’s permission, I’m sharing what each of us was working on, to give you a picture of what 20% time can look like. (Please do note I may have lost nuances as a simultaneous note-taker and pizza-eater, and that these were only accurate as of March 2018—folks are working on different things now.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ammon Shepherd (DH Developer):&lt;/strong&gt; make art that’s tactilely responsive; thermal detonator watch with 12 LEDs to show the hour + access big data from somewhere&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Laura Miller (Head of Public Programs):&lt;/strong&gt; Scholars’ Lab alumni network (map, viz) illustrating where our students go on to, showing the impact the lab has on careers and the field; Zoe made a couple Jupyter notebook demos to think through how this might look&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Zoe LeBlanc (DH Developer):&lt;/strong&gt; for her app to store archival images, rewrote the logic and added auto-segmenting for paragraphs of text; work with computer vision scripts (OpenCV?), training dataset creation; was built in Django and AngularJS, she’s now rebuilding in React; statistics methodology by issue of magazines she’s studying; Cairo ’60s anti-colonial ideas change over time, so showing conceptual clustering changing over time; tagging images in her app (e.g. JFK images); interest in building her own OCR engine some day; Shane has possible data-testing set to use (cryptography journals)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Brandon Walsh (Head of Student Programs):&lt;/strong&gt; anxious pedagogies, thinking through how to expect + deal with frustration during classes, and how to apply this thinking with DH projects as well; text analysis cookbook from his frequently used code, with info on how/why cookbook snippets work; “how to learn text analysis” but with your own text&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Drew Macqueen (GIS Specialist):&lt;/strong&gt; keeping a Notepad++ code journal; created the Arduino Chris (GIF above) for keeping the SLab office lights on and practice physical computing skills; learning about georeferencing 3D models with Will and Arin; CityEngine; wants to write a blog post e.g. on modifiable areal unit problem, why zip codes are bad locators; wants to add thermal sensor to Arduino Chris so it works better&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jeremy Boggs (Head of R&amp;amp;D):&lt;/strong&gt; Thinking through distant reading of comic books, e.g. how Batman and the Joker in &lt;em&gt;The Killing Joke&lt;/em&gt; become visually similar, John Walsh’s TEI for Comic Books, (image recognition of?) comic book text to study gender; using Italo Calvino’s writing towards a bibliography of books with their qualities ID’d being used as a framework for text analysis; interest in doing D&amp;amp;D homebrew mashup with other content, e.g. Sarah and James’s characters from Samuel Johnson (http://genuineremains.jeremyboggs.net/)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shane Lin (Senior Developer):&lt;/strong&gt; working on his history dissertation, including writing some code, studying Usenet for how/when cryptography entered into widespread political consciousness, when crypto went from mostly a math discussion to mostly a political one; exploring Usenet metadata e.g. to see whether messages are from people new to the discussion or not; turned OpenScan 2D sketch into 3D model&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Arin Bennett (3D Visualization Specialist):&lt;/strong&gt; Working with Unity as part of his mentorship of the Praxis cohort; augmented reality (AR) mapping via the new Unity asset we purchased; working on a better AR interface for doing his trail running while using the headset, e.g. point of interest along his way, time countdown; AR walking tours; touching 3D print but seeing scan/photo version in headset&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Will Rourk (3D Data and Content Specialist):&lt;/strong&gt; Modular synthesizers; making 3D-printed chocolate molds from any 3D model; writing and researching what CHI (cultural heritage informatics) as a field &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; today e.g. CLIR talk and paper, bibliography creation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chris Gist (GIS Specialist):&lt;/strong&gt; learning new ARCGISonline tech, 3rd rebuild because the tech keeps changing and adding new products; tagging locations on a friend’s property; thinking about siloed research in regional cultural places and building a trail along the historic trail between them, creating new data layers to assist with pitch for new trail&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Amanda Visconti (Managing Director):&lt;/strong&gt; Helping draft possible ACH code of conduct for all platforms/outside of conferences; turned my Drupal dissertation website into a static archival site; article revisions for &lt;em&gt;Debates in DH&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;American Quarterly&lt;/em&gt;; approaching HTML/CSS/web browser functionality as something one can have expertise in, e.g. figuring out what JS stuff I can hack CSS to do; considering writing a textual forgery LARP; building a pneumatic tube message system for the lab; Shane helped me 3D print my actual brain from a brain MRI; learned to use FabLab laser cutters; working as a &lt;em&gt;Programming Historian&lt;/em&gt; editor&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alison Booth (Academic Director):&lt;/strong&gt; Collective Bibliographies of Women and proposing new NEH grant; creating Gothic Walking tour of Grounds with her class; thinking through a DH project extending understanding of the Anne Spencer House&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;challenges&quot;&gt;Challenges&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In practice, 20% time doesn’t happen exactly how we’d like. We’re busy staff, with many interests; because of our mentorship-not-service model, much of our daily work feels like, or is, what we’d personally choose to do R&amp;amp;D on (fulfilling the original goal of making sure folks in service roles could continue to grow as scholars). The desire to use one’s 20% time is something each of our supervisors fully support, so challenges in making this time are never because management won’t let staff make time for this work; I don’t think we’ve ever needed to veto a project idea for not fitting our 3 guidelines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Known issues with 20% time include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Making the time for it&lt;/em&gt;. Blocking out time on our calendars has helped some with this (especially starting 1 term away, when calendars are empty enough you can e.g. grab the same time every week), but I think it’s less a matter of making specific hours, and more emphasizing to ourselves that this self-initiated work is as important as our work that more immediately impacts our community. We often don’t practice the same commitment to our self-initiated R&amp;amp;D projects as we do for student and faculty collaborations. Some ideas for helping with this are a Slack channel to update colleagues on our progress and receive encouragement and help, and establishing writing/research partners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another barrier is needing help from SLab colleagues to move forward with your self-initiated work, but we feel reluctant to ask for that help: knowing how busy everyone is, or feeling uncomfortable using resources for a personally-initiated project. Or folks actually don’t have time during fall and spring terms to help, and internal collaborations needs to wait for the summer. As a small step forward over this barrier, I’ve been trying to recognize the importance of these self-initiated projects by helping schedule meetings where relevant SLab staff can work together to advance a project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Setting a formal amount of time for staff research shifts the conversation from whether a project can happen, to how to best make it happen. Our colleagues in other Library units don’t have 20% time in their job descriptions, although a number do have language about professional development. Many of our library colleagues are very active researchers. I do see an explicit percentage of job time is different from knowing you can propose a self-initiated project to your supervisor, but they may or may not understand its application, and they may or may not support your making time for it during your work day. 20% is equivalent to one day a week, 10% is one day every two weeks; this doesn’t need to happen daily or weekly, and some staff find it best for them and their community to bank this time during fall and spring and use it during winter and summers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Library supports each of its staff with at least $1k of professional development travel funding each year (and extra for the first 2 years on the job); UVA also provides university staff annual funds to take courses and attend conferences. The Library and UVA professional development funds can’t be used for books or equipment, which can be difficult for folks seeking to self-teach or to learn a hands-on skill like electronics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’d like to both better communicate our work to our colleagues and the public, and also back up our colleagues (here and beyond UVA) when they’re articulating why they’d like to self-initiate research as a small but formal part of their jobs. In the last year, we’ve made steps toward these goals including getting pizza and sharing our R&amp;amp;D work and frustrations among SLab staff; scheduling annual summer brownbags just for library colleagues, where we’ll update folks about each of our staffers’ work and discuss potential collaborations throughout the Library; and re-committing to publishing on any conference travel funded by SLab (either a blog post within 6 weeks of the event, or an internal brownbag updating Library colleagues, as a condition of future travel funding).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve also heard some questioning around staff using 20% time to work on dissertations, worded as “paying people to finish their dissertations”. That 20% time helps us hire such scholars and best serve the campus community is discussed above, but I’ll add that as long as dissertational work fits our 3 guidelines (ensuring work benefits the university, is made public), it’s actually particularly suited to 20% time: it’s likely got a clear timeline, mentor, and obvious application to that staffer’s professional growth. I agree with Jeremy Boggs’ argument that whether 20% time is used for work that is part of a dissertation is irrelevant; instead, we should be looking at whether it’s meeting those 3 guidelines, and think of it in terms of what work is being done. For example, Senior Developer and History ABD Shane Lin has used some of his 20% time to learn to scrape Usenet metadata to understand historical community development, sharpening skills around web scraping, text analysis, community research, and historical scholarship critical to his role in the lab (and incidentally, moving his dissertation forward as well).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-do-you-think&quot;&gt;What do you think?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have suggestions for improving our 20% time in policy or practice or questions, let us know! We’re also interested in your own experiences pursuing research and professional development, regardless of your job role; and what, if any, policy about research and professional development your institution offers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Special thanks to Bethany Nowviskie, whose arguments for 20% time still benefit many folks today, and whose excellent 2012 rationale for 20% time, &lt;a href=&quot;http://nowviskie.org/2012/too-small-to-fail/&quot;&gt;“Too Small to Fail”&lt;/a&gt;, is quoted liberally in this post!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2019 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2019/04/26/dh-center-staff-professional-research-and-development-time/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2019/04/26/dh-center-staff-professional-research-and-development-time/</guid>
        
        <category>digital-humanities</category>
        
        <category>meta-dh</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>ScholarsLab.org website relaunch!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally posted on the Scholars’ Lab blog on &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/site-relaunch/&quot;&gt;January 15, 2019&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re happy to announce that our Lab website has a new look and feel, all aimed at making Scholars’ Lab more accessible and the site more useful. The website &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org&quot;&gt;ScholarsLab.org&lt;/a&gt; represents the collective effort of our &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/people&quot;&gt;staff and collaborators&lt;/a&gt;, past and present. It’s existed in multiple forms: most recently, as a WordPress site and now, as of this blog post, as a Jekyll-generated static website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;why-renew-the-website&quot;&gt;Why renew the website?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our previous website was headed by the homepage text “collaborate, &lt;strong&gt;iterate&lt;/strong&gt;, discuss”:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/assets/post-media/2018-11-05-iterate.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of text saying &amp;quot;collaborate, iterate, discuss&amp;quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re a community lab focused on experimental scholarship. We care most about the impact of scholarship on &lt;em&gt;people&lt;/em&gt;, ranking positive human experience as the most important outcome of projects or other work. This means that failure and a journey of many iterations are not just frequent by-products of our work, but essential characteristics. For example, we periodically renew our &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/charter&quot;&gt;lab charter&lt;/a&gt; to reflect our ongoing growth as scholars and professionals; as it was last updated in 2016, we’ll be renewing its text (and even, perhaps, its form) over the coming year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before renewing our charter, though, we worked on synthesizing our many views of what the lab currently is into a coherent, concise mission–visible at the top of our new homepage. Having the website look “newer” wasn’t a priority for us; rather, we used this re-articulated mission to reimagine a site more aligned with our values…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;why-does-the-site-look-this-way&quot;&gt;Why does the site look this way?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We started thinking about a site renewal back in Summer 2017, with two rough goals: a general rethinking of the site to fit our current work, and a migration of platforms from WordPress to a Jekyll-generated static website. (You can see this &lt;a href=&quot;https://programminghistorian.org/en/lessons/building-static-sites-with-jekyll-github-pages&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; for more on what a jekyll-generated static site is, why you might want to use one, and how.) WordPress is a popular blogging platform with the advantage of a user-friendly administrative dashboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the benefits of WYSIWYG (what you see is what you get) blog post editors and easy media uploads come with significant costs of web developer time updating the site’s core, plugin, and theme code and keeping the site secure. Moving to a Jekyll-generated static site helped us think through applying &lt;a href=&quot;https://go-dh.github.io/mincomp/about/&quot;&gt;minimal computing values&lt;/a&gt; to our main online platform. This move means making small content changes to the website (e.g. writing a new blog post) a little harder by requiring some steps we didn’t require before, but… we think these steps:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;are within the grasp of anyone (regardless of technical experience),&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ultimately enfranchise everyone to understand more and do more with our site than WordPress allowed, and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;are in line with our teaching each of our Praxis cohorts the basic steps required to use git, GitHub, and markdown (i.e. by teaching these skills to our team and affiliates more broadly, we hope to also enfranchise folks to create their own websites with the same technologies).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After much discussion and work, these initial goals yielded a more important goal: reimagining our website to more clearly focus on making the lab accessible to folks who wouldn’t otherwise already know about or feel welcome to join us. We already have some friendly and well-trodden paths to reaching the lab, such as through our work and fellowship CFPs, consultations, events, and open office hours; so we decided to aim the website at reaching folks who weren’t already coming into our space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/about&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/assets/post-media/2018-11-21-FAQlist.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of frequently asked Scholars' Lab questions&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some ways we approached this goal:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Encouraging site visitors to feel they’re in the right place&lt;/strong&gt;, by updating textual content and photos to be more explicitly welcoming. For example, we reorganized our &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/makerspace&quot;&gt;Makerspace&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/spatial-technologies&quot;&gt;Spatial Tech&lt;/a&gt; equipment and software inventories into named categories; you might not know what a serger is, but where you’d probably just skim past the word before, you can now see that it’s part of a set of equipment and supplies aimed at making things with fabric. The hope is that by grouping resources like the serger into clearer categories, you might realize that our Makerspace has some resources and folks you can talk to about, for example, your interests in making stuff from textiles, historical costuming, and/or other fabric art approaches.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Making the &lt;strong&gt;info folks need to get more involved easy to find&lt;/strong&gt;, once they feel comfortable with our resources being theirs. We wrote a &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/about&quot;&gt;FAQ&lt;/a&gt; anticipating questions folks often ask us, overhauled the structure of information on our site (e.g. menu order and wording, page titles, layout and order of information on a given page). We also created clear maps showing how to get to the specific locations within our somewhat large space (the west wing of the 4th floor of Alderman Library).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Accurately capturing the &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/work&quot;&gt;work&lt;/a&gt; of all our current staff, including recent hires and folks welcomed into the lab during the library reorganization (who hadn’t had their work represented on the old site), to &lt;strong&gt;show the true breadth of disciplines and approaches we cover&lt;/strong&gt;. We also reworked the metadata on each of our current and past Scholars’ Lab folks, so that we could more easily and accurately show what roles folks have held and who has contributed anything to a given project—again, more accurately showing how the Scholars’ Lab is itself a digital scholarship project, one built together by many people over the years.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;More clearly showing that &lt;strong&gt;we’re part of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://library.virginia.edu&quot;&gt;UVA Library&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, so folks understand that we’re part of the Library’s mission to provide equitable access to knowledge and learning to everyone. This work includes an FAQ question, a section of the homepage with text and the UVA Library logo, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/library&quot;&gt;a new SLab “Library” page&lt;/a&gt; highlighting the work of Library colleagues that helps us do what we do, and that may feature stories about intralibrary collaborations in the future.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;who-made-this&quot;&gt;Who made this?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 2017-2018 renewal of this website incorporates text, suggestions, and feedback from everyone on &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/people&quot;&gt;the Scholars’ Lab staff&lt;/a&gt;. Additionally, the following folks put in significant extra effort on the site’s design, coding, content, project management, and documentation: Katherine Donnally, Jeremy Boggs, Brandon Walsh, Ronda Grizzle, Laura Miller, Zoe LeBlanc, Ammon Shepherd, Shane Lin, Beth Mitchell, and Amanda Visconti.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to especially highlight the leadership and labor of &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/people/katherine-donnally/&quot;&gt;Katherine Donnally&lt;/a&gt; (Scholars’ Lab DH Designer 2017-2018) in realizing this site. Katherine’s thinking and work gave the renewal project a coherent focus around making the lab more accessible and supportive of folks who might not otherwise feel part of our community; in addition to design and development work, she created structures and documentation (e.g. goal and progress tracker, code commenting, analysis of the old website, articulation of the purpose of the new site) that were instrumental in both imagining the new site and seeing it to the finish line.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 15 Apr 2019 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2019/04/15/scholarslab-website-relaunch/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2019/04/15/scholarslab-website-relaunch/</guid>
        
        <category>digital-humanities</category>
        
        <category>meta-dh</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A Moderate Proposal: Healthier Systems for Running Online Digital Humanities Communities</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally posted on the Scholars’ Lab blog on &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/moderation-running-dh-online-communities/&quot;&gt;February 27, 2019&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Healthy, diverse online learning communities depend on the labor of community design: unseen and often stressful work such as moderation, shaping discussions, and encouraging positive community behavior. As more opportunities emerge for learning online as part of a virtual community, how can we:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;recognize (credit, publicize, reward, treat as scholarly work) and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reinforce (design, automate, fairly distribute the labor, deal with mental health impacts)&lt;br /&gt;
the labor of community design? As marginalized identities are most at risk for harm when interacting with others online, support for moderation is support for community inclusion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I write from my experiences moderating both my digital dissertation project Infinite Ulysses (a social platform for annotating/commenting on James Joyce’s novel) and the Digital Humanities Slack I started (a set of themed chat rooms with over 2,000 digital humanist members; co-moderated by Alan G. Pike, Sam Abrams, Alex Gil, Brandon Walsh, Ed Summers, Paige C. Morgan, Jeremy Boggs, Eleanor Dickson, Liz Rodrigues, and Erin Pappas). It’s been exhilarating using technology to collaborate with folks I don’t know: if you’ve taught DH, think of the students who respond to your lessons like “DH is exactly what I want to do, I just didn’t have a term for it before”, but expand to include folks from all over the world and more diverse walks of life. But it’s also been a significant source of anxiety, balancing my responsibility to the community with my desire to help folks learn to be more positive influences on that community. That stress was half of why I moved Infinite Ulysses from a Drupal site allowing commenting, to a static archived version without commenting (the other half was some serious thinking about how I could best contribute to the DH I want to see, and realizing that just for me personally, I need to move away from Joyce and Modernist studies to best accomplish that).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do want to note that the challenges of moderating online DH and other academic/professional communities are, at least for me, privileged through my ability to choose my level of work (or opt out completely) without hurting my livelihood or family; compared with the pain, lack of compensation, lack of respect, and more evils experienced by folks like those who moderate YoutTube and Facebook, working with smaller communities that have some norms (though inequitable) and professional consequences (though often used as a weapon against rather than a protector of folks with marginalized identities) are less pressing problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-im-blogging-today&quot;&gt;Why I’m blogging today&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post is largely drawn from a non-successful IMLS pre-proposal I PI’d (Spring 2018) for an NLG planning grant to explore, identify key challenges, and plan pilot community experimental approaches to aid the foundational labor of moderators underpinning online learning communities, titled “&lt;strong&gt;A Moderate Proposal&lt;/strong&gt;: Recognizing and Reinforcing Online Community Moderation to Benefit Diverse Learners” and co-designed with colleagues Jeremy Boggs, Katherine Donnally, Shane Lin, Laura Miller, and Brandon Walsh. (If you like the title pun, you may also appreciate that our proposal drafting GDoc was titled “DigitalHumanities.club”, after the domain that I own because it’s awesome, but that I was also using to explore Mastodon and Mattermost for better communities.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I finally got around to this post due to cool stuff two DHers are up to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/scott_bot/status/1100387484930854913&quot;&gt;Scott Weingart’s Twitter thread&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theverge.com/2019/2/25/18229714/cognizant-facebook-content-moderator-interviews-trauma-working-conditions-arizona&quot;&gt;Casey Newton’s recent article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve only skimmed Newton’s piece, but I’ve read and admired Sarah T. Robert’s more longstanding work in this area:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a &lt;em&gt;Maclean’s&lt;/em&gt; article in Summer 2018, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.macleans.ca/opinion/meet-the-people-who-scar-themselves-to-clean-up-our-social-media-networks/&quot;&gt;“Meet the people who scar themselves to clean up our social media networks”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;an article in &lt;em&gt;The Atlantic&lt;/em&gt; in Spring 2017, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2017/03/commercial-content-moderation/518796/&quot;&gt;“Social Media’s Silent Filter”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And now &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ubiquity75/status/1045552839819505664&quot;&gt;a book!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.org/people/ammon-shepherd/&quot;&gt;SLab colleague Ammon Shepherd&lt;/a&gt; has kicked off a series of blog posts around the challenges of archiving DH work, with what promises to be a special focus on the technical and especially sysadmin work unlerying these challenges. You can read &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.org/blog/archiving-dh-part-one/&quot;&gt;the first post in the series&lt;/a&gt; now, but Ammon’s also orchestrating a really cool system of inviting UVA Library colleagues to co-write the rest of the series with him, complete with clear documentation on how to take part and make the discussion better.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Scott and Ammon for being awesome scholars doing work collaboratively and in public!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-moderate-proposal&quot;&gt;A moderate proposal&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Community design requires &lt;strong&gt;moderation&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;scaffolding&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;Moderation&lt;/strong&gt; is both the work of controlling spam and intentional harassment in a community, as well as designing and implementing a code of conduct (e.g. working behind the scenes with a community member whose words impact others negatively, but who wants to become a better community member). &lt;strong&gt;Scaffolding&lt;/strong&gt; is the work of maintaining and nurturing a community: suggesting conversation topics, encouraging community member involvement, amplifying marginalized voices, and otherwise enacting strategies to grow a healthy and active community. Creating the technical platform for an online community is relatively simple, given existing open-source versions of popular social media platforms. Rather, the challenge to improving moderation is a social project: habituating community members to behavior that reduces harassment, encourages real accountability to others in your community, distributes the stress of moderating, and recognizes/credits/rewards people who moderate and otherwise advance positive community design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve focused on Twitter, Slack, and Mastodon as text-heavy platforms with public and frequent use by digital humanists, plus Civil Comments and the Mozilla Coral Project as technical solutions to online community challenges. I’m also interested in these past or current DHy communities and the scholars shaping them: DH Q&amp;amp;A, Humanities Commons, DHthis, DH Commons, the DLF Forum, DH Slack, HASTAC, DHNow, the AADHUM Slack, and the Documenting the Now Slack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve since updated our thinking and planning, but when I submitted our grant preproposal a year ago, we imagined the following activites and outcomes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;activities&quot;&gt;Activities&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project team would identify and invite 10 experts in online learning community-building, with diverse representation of gender, race, and other identities, from libraries, archives, museums, and academia. Our initial work draws on a symposium with these advisors to spark collaborations, identify key challenges, and plan out steps for piloting and assessing improvements to social systems of moderation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Project team reviews literature and existing communities:&lt;/em&gt; Distribute Twitter and DH Slack surveys to gather anecdotes about good and bad online academic communities and their moderation systems. Use team’s existing text analysis skills to explore frequent vocabulary and sentiment in the discussions on a sample community, the Digital Humanities Slack (2k+ community members), if* DH Slack community decides this is an acceptable analysis (read more about the community’s decision to keep the Slack ephemeral via a non-paid Slack plan &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2016/07/06/digital-humanities-slack-community-design&quot;&gt;in this post&lt;/a&gt;). Create an annotated bibliography plus pre-symposium reading list. Assign each advisory board member to read 3 articles and report useful takeaway ideas from these at the symposium.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;2-day symposium of 10 advisory board members with Scholars’ Lab staff and UVA Library colleagues:&lt;/em&gt; Project team presents results of the DH Slack message text analysis* as a grounding case study. Advisory board gives lightning talks summarizing their assigned readings. Goals set for the rest of the symposium. Facilitated design jam sessions, paper prototyping, breakout groups addressing specific challenges, such as&lt;br /&gt;
1: amplifying credit for moderators, making their labor institutionally legible for promotion, addressing gendering of work;&lt;br /&gt;
2: templates for difficult moderation conversations with community members, tech features that could support social needs such as shadow-banning, moderator self-care.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;After symposium:&lt;/em&gt; Project team prepares report of best practices to support online learning community moderation, shares with advisory board for feedback, disseminates to public. Team outlines next steps, shares with advisory board for feedback. Probable steps include identifying both technical and social solutions to pilot, formally approaching communities to collaborate on testing practices (e.g. MLA/Humanities Commons, ACH, DLF), scheduling pilots and assessment, prototyping and testing ideas, and reporting back to public. We take the NEH “Off the Tracks” workshop resulting in &lt;a href=&quot;https://mith.umd.edu/offthetracks/recommendations&quot;&gt;recommendations for ethically crediting collaborators&lt;/a&gt; as a model for all of this work, and commit to thoroughly and accurately crediting all participants in these projects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;outcomes&quot;&gt;Outcomes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will identify project staffers with expertise in ethical design practices, and charge them with holding our focus on improving online communities for marginalized identities, while also documenting and publishing the conversations and findings occurring through the planning phase to ensure others can build on our work. During this grant’s planning phase we will create:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An annotated bibliography and reading list&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A symposium whitepaper covering the ideas, best practice suggestions, and conversations a diverse advisory board of experts generate during the symposium&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A public conversation around crediting moderation labor and improving community moderation, connecting scholars interested in this work&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A written plan outlining next steps for pilot projects designing, building, and assessing various technical and social features for their impact on online community moderation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Experimental approaches may include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Strategies to protect users from one another, unwanted surveillance, or commercial interests&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Documented design-driven approaches to building more ethical academic social media platforms&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A code of conduct template in support of community design labor&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Model a technical platform for online learning communities that is designed from the start with an ethic of care, with particular focus on making the system useful to those identities usually marginalized by commercial social media platforms&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Text analysis results discussion from analysis of DH Slack community vocabulary and sentiment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interested-know-things&quot;&gt;Interested? Know things?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If anything in this post interests you (future collaboration?), overlaps with your current work, or could benefit from my reading and citing you or others, please let me know at visconti@virginia.edu. Thank you!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks to colleagues Jeremy Boggs, Katherine Donnally, Shane Lin, Laura Miller, and Brandon Walsh for co-designing of the grant proposal, and to Ammon Shepherd for helping me think about the technical sustainability aspects of better online moderation experiences.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 15 Apr 2019 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2019/04/15/moderation-running-dh-online-communities/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2019/04/15/moderation-running-dh-online-communities/</guid>
        
        <category>digital-humanities</category>
        
        <category>meta-dh</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>DH Dissertation to Director: Notes connecting my student and staff experiences</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally posted on the Scholars’ Lab blog on &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/dh-dissertation-to-director/&quot;&gt;February 21, 2019&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A colleague recently asked me about how I draw on my DH dissertation experience (&lt;a href=&quot;https://dr.amandavisconti.com&quot;&gt;dr.amandavisconti.com&lt;/a&gt;) in my work co-directing the Scholars’ Lab. Below, I share the rough notes I typed up in response about the first couple such dissertation-director connections that came to mind:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;digital-humanities--experimental-humanities&quot;&gt;Digital humanities &amp;lt; experimental humanities&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting to do an &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/tag/dissertation/&quot;&gt;unusually shaped dissertation&lt;/a&gt; meant doing a lot of meta-dissertational work analyzing and synthesizing precedents for making as scholarship, dissertations that didn’t produce written chapters, and experimental scholarly methods and formats more generally. I not only needed to prove that such work could reach the goals of a dissertation, but that my research design choices also fit tmy particular research questions. It was profoundly useful to work through what I thought was the best research design for my questions, and then also find the language to convince others of this as well. I do not want to add more barriers to the dissertation process for anyone, but it does seem mildly unfortunate to me that most humanities dissertation creators aren’t encouraged and supported to explore multiple research aproaches and argue for why their project format is the best fit for their research questions, rather than treating written chapters as the only choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Scholars’ Lab has historical prominence as a DH center, but we also offer strong expertise in other areas, such as GIS/spatial reasoning and cultural heritage informatics. Some of my work as a Lab director has been collaborating with my colleagues to update our understanding of what’s most important to us, articulate that in a concise and memorable way, and relaunching our Lab website (ScholarsLab.org) to better communicate that updated mission. I think my dissertation experience helped me do a better job of hearing and synthesizing our staff’s visions for the Lab: rather than forcing everything to fit under the rubric of DH, we’ve identified a shared lab commitment to questioning assumptions around the methods and publication formats of scholarship, to cultivating a readiness to experiment and create new approaches where existing ones don’t best fit our research questions. It’s the &lt;em&gt;experimental&lt;/em&gt; mindset of DH that drives us and connects our team members’ many skillsets—as you can see in partially or wholly analog work like our Makerspace and campus community design work—rather than something particular to the Digital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;passing-it-on&quot;&gt;Passing it on&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been extremely lucky, from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://mith.umd.edu&quot;&gt;MITH&lt;/a&gt; and UMD English Department smart and caring mentorship that allowed me to realize my unusual dissertation, to getting to work at the Scholars’ Lab, where the amazing staff have long, successfully made it their mission to model and nurture a generous and human-centered digital humanities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My dissertation experience was an extremely lucky one: I had incredible mentors as my dissertation committee (Matt Kirschenbaum as advisor; Kari Kraus, Neil Fraistat, Melanie Kill, Brian Richardson). They met with me throughout the dissertation process to give me feedback and help us make sure that, for a very non-traditionally shaped dissertation, we were all on the same page as to expectations for the final outcome. They all had this unusual combination of innovative scholarship mixed with humanity and generosity. I’ve heard people say that either your advisor is nice to you but doesn’t push your work forward, or they’re mean (how is this not just a thing, but a fairly common one?) but make your work better. Every interaction I had with my committee was a kind one, and yet they &lt;em&gt;constantly&lt;/em&gt; challenged me to do better, with their full faith, and both the support and space necessary to figuring out what scholarship is to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having mentors modeling this approach to scholarship made me determined to pass on the impact of their gift to other folks I encounter, as best I can. To work so that the luck and privilege that allowed me to do my dissertation might become standard resources for anyone. To put my heart into Scholars’ Lab’s goal of training the next generation of scholars to be the scholarly community we want to exist, and to take responsibility for my tiny snowflake in the storm of what DH is (e.g. think through the impact of my doing my &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2014/05/27/inclusivityeditioncanon&quot;&gt;dissertation around a canon work&lt;/a&gt; by a white, male, Anglo, cis author; and change my scholarly trajectory to respond to the problems that investigation raised for me—please note that I no longer agree with that blog post, but haven’t yet written up how my thinking has evolved since then…).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;scholarship-is-people&quot;&gt;Scholarship is people&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read Mark Sample’s excellent &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.samplereality.com/2013/02/08/when-does-service-become-scholarship/&quot;&gt;“When does service become scholarship?”&lt;/a&gt; while dissertating, and I’ve paraphrased his argument into my preferred definition of “scholarship”:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;one part critical thinking + one part communicating the results of that thinking&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Critical thinking&lt;/em&gt; can be accomplished through many methods, including research, writing, coding, building, designing, experimenting, and play. &lt;em&gt;Communicating critical thinking&lt;/em&gt; can take the form of traditional publishing or other forms of “making public” such as tweeting and blogging, teaching, sharing open source code, or any other way for your intellectual community to learn from, critique, evaluate, and/or build on your work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Decompressing this definition:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Anyone trying to think well and share their work is part of the scholarly conversation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Making research just half of scholarship rather than synonymous brings the scholarly community into focus as the goal of our research work—with the implicit belief that the work of care, respect, mentoring, amplifying of your community members is not just a “nice” characteristic taking second place to the completely broken concepts of “rigor” or “brilliance”, not just “eulogy worthy”, but definitionally a necessary part of being a scholar&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I don’t have time for a definition of scholarship that doesn’t recognize the brilliant contributions of project managers, teachers, students, librarians, fanfic writers, book club members, more folks than I can list: all as much a part of building intellectual communities’ knowledge and abilities as academic faculty.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A scholarship that fits with the Scholars’ Lab’s unofficial moto of “people over projects”: focusing on community knowledge and health as the goal, and research as the means, rather than the other way around.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;documentation-of-scholarships-process-is-scholarship&quot;&gt;Documentation of scholarship’s process is scholarship&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent around six months of my dissertation building something on an Islandora-based framework, and then ended up not using those months of my server and code work in the final digital edition I produced. But because I documented throughout why I was making certain technical and design choices, how the technical work developed my critical thinking, I had that research to share with my intellectual community, and I wasn’t six months behind on my dissertation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my work today, I encourage others to share their notes, design choices, and other documentation as they go; it’s better for the community, and I think it’s also better for scholars new to a method to know they can start giving back to the community right away (e.g. What do you know now that you didn’t understand a week ago? Write for that person).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 15 Apr 2019 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2019/04/15/dh-dissertation-to-director/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2019/04/15/dh-dissertation-to-director/</guid>
        
        <category>digital-humanities</category>
        
        <category>meta-dh</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Automating Webpage &amp; Tweet Screencaptures</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally posted on the Scholars’ Lab blog on &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/automating-webpage-tweet-screencaptures/&quot;&gt;January 30, 2019&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you have a list of webpage URLs for which you’d like screencaps (aka screenshots)?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(&lt;em&gt;Know this tutorial fits your needs? &lt;a href=&quot;#how-to-automate-screencapping&quot;&gt;Jump to the instructions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe you study social media: you can capture all the data about a tweet using &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.docnow.io/&quot;&gt;Documenting the Now’s tools&lt;/a&gt; and get a spreadsheet listing all of a hashtag’s tweets with text, file names for any image attachments, publication date, RT/like counts…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But maybe you’d also like to have screencaps of the webpage per each tweet as they appeared at a given time:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;keep an offline folder of all your faved tweets? (before time passes and some of them are deleted)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;record how tweets &lt;em&gt;looked&lt;/em&gt; on Twitter.com at a given point in time, e.g. the avatars of folks who interacted with the tweet (using the avatar images current—at least as of the time of screencap—since people change these over time), or what metadata was viewable to the casual observer at a given time, as with this example tweet screencap:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://scholarslab.org/assets/post-media/2019-01-31-tweetscreenshot1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having screencaps of tweets can be useful for Twitter receipts, conducting a user study where you want to gauge folk’s reactions to seeing a tweet as it looked on Twitter.com (without needing to be online), or keep a folder of motivating tweets to refer to when you need encouragement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post will help you also automate taking screencaps from a list of URLs, by pointing you two tutorials plus some advice on combining these. This tutorial is written from a Mac user’s perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;my-uses-cases&quot;&gt;My uses cases&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently had two needs for a workflow automating screencaps:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Screencapping faved tweets (aka motivation)&lt;/strong&gt;: I used to “like” tweets where folks said useful things about my work, for later encouragement when I needed it. I wanted to switch to just screencapping these tweets as I saw them, saving the “like” function to indicate interest in others’ tweets, but that meant I need a way to get all those previous likes as screencaps. This workflow gave me a folder of over 2k screencapped tweets! (Now I just need to make a bot to show me a random one each time I log in…)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figuring out how many of our posts were amplified by a DH aggregator&lt;/strong&gt;: For an external review of DH at UVA, we’re drafting a report on Scholars’ Lab as a DH unit. As a small part of this, I wanted to include the number of times SLab staff or students have had a blog post highlighted by &lt;a href=&quot;http://digitalhumanitiesnow.org/&quot;&gt;Digital Humanities Now&lt;/a&gt;. Searching the &lt;em&gt;DH Now&lt;/em&gt; with a variety of search terms (e.g. Praxis, Neatline, variants of “Scholars’ Lab”, names of former staff) turned up a bunch of posts, but without opening each result in a browser to skim that post, I couldn’t be sure that these were all actually either SLab-authored or citing SLab work (vs. e.g. happening to use the word “praxis”). By automating screencaps of all the links my search turned up, instead of opening each link in a browser, I could use Preview to bulk-open screencaps and glance over the top of each webpage, seeing more quickly whether a post was related to SLab or not.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;credits&quot;&gt;Credits&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an extremely light repackaging of two sets of advice, for which I am grateful:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ryan Bauman’s (&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ryanfb&quot;&gt;twitter.com/ryanfb&lt;/a&gt;) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ryanfb/status/1014302804796731393&quot;&gt;tweets on how to get a list of URLs for your faved tweets&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Joshua Johnson’s 2011 post &lt;a href=&quot;https://mac.appstorm.net/general/applescript-automatically-create-screenshots-from-a-list-of-websites/&quot;&gt;“AppleScript: Automatically Create Screenshots from a List of Websites”&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may also wish to explore &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.docnow.io/&quot;&gt;Documenting the Now&lt;/a&gt;’s tools for ethical preservation and research with social media, including the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.docnow.io/catalog/&quot;&gt;Tweet Catalogue&lt;/a&gt; to locate datasets of tweets using a given hashtag, and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/DocNow/hydrator&quot;&gt;Hydrator&lt;/a&gt; tool for turning those datasets back into a list of tweets and their metadata.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;how-to-automate-screencapping&quot;&gt;How to automate screencapping&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;1.&lt;/span&gt; You’ll need a text document (plain text / .txt) with each URL you want to be screencapped listed on a separate line:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://scholarslab.org/assets/post-media/2019-01-31-tweet-screenhot-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to create a list of just your faved tweets, see &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ryanfb/status/1014302804796731393&quot;&gt;this tweet by Ryan Bauman tweet&lt;/a&gt; to get just the liked tweets from your Twitter &amp;gt; Settings &amp;gt; “Your Twitter Data” download.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have a bunch of bookmarked URLs you want to screenshot (possibly in one bookmarks subfolder?), you can export your whole set of bookmarks from the browser, then edit the resulting HTML file (using search+replace or regular expressions; sorry, that’s a whole separate lengthy tutorial, but &lt;a href=&quot;https://programminghistorian.org/en/lessons/understanding-regular-expressions&quot;&gt;Doug Knox’s tutorial here&lt;/a&gt;’s a good place to get started understanding regular expressions) to strip it to just a list of the URLs you want to screencap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;2.&lt;/span&gt; Next, we’ll use Joshua Johnson’s 2011 post &lt;a href=&quot;https://mac.appstorm.net/general/applescript-automatically-create-screenshots-from-a-list-of-websites/&quot;&gt;“AppleScript: Automatically Create Screenshots from a List of Websites”&lt;/a&gt; to actually take the screencaps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re going to use the Mac “Script Editor” tool to tell our computer to take that list of URLs, open each in Safari, take a screencap of that screen, and save it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open the Script Editor app (Applications &amp;gt; Utilities &amp;gt; Script Editor).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;3.&lt;/span&gt; Grab the text from &lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/amandavisconti/ffc05d293b9fed70a7378421f7c818f0&quot;&gt;this page&lt;/a&gt;, which puts Joshua Johnson’s script in an easy-to-find place (to understand what the script does, read &lt;a href=&quot;https://mac.appstorm.net/general/applescript-automatically-create-screenshots-from-a-list-of-websites/&quot;&gt;his post&lt;/a&gt; where he walks you through adding and adjusting the different pieces). Paste the text into the top text field:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://scholarslab.org/assets/post-media/2019-01-31-tweet-screenshot-3.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have a slow internet connection or want to screencap pages on websites that load slowly, you may wish to find and adjust the piece of the script that says “delay 5”, to a larger number than 5 (this controls the time the script waits between directing safari to visit a given URL, and taking a screencap of whatever is then currently on the Safari screen).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;4.&lt;/span&gt; Open the Applications &amp;gt; Safari browser, and drag its screen to be as large as possible. Depending on what level of zoomed-in/zoomed-out you usually use the Safari browser at, you may wish to adjust for the purpose of taking the screencaps; the screencaps will only capture what’s showing in the window you’ve opened (not stuff you’d need to scroll down to see).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;5.&lt;/span&gt; Open the Applications &amp;gt; TextEdit app (not a different text editor, unless you want to figure out how to edit the script’s &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;tell application &quot;TextEdit&quot;&lt;/code&gt; how to point to a different application). Paste in your list of URLs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have other TextEdit windows/tabs, make sure that the one with the URL list is the topmost/frontmost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;6.&lt;/span&gt; You’re ready to take screencaps! You’ll want to do this when you’re okay not having access to your computer for a while, because the screenshots will be of whatever is at the front of your screen. If you step away from your computer, the script knows to leave a Safari browser window open at the front of your screen, take a screencap, then move to the next webpage in your list and screencap that. If you hide the Safari window or have other stuff open over it, you won’t get the screencaps you want. (I’m sure there’s a way to make this not the case, but I didn’t need to figure that out for my use cases.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back on the Script Editor, press the “red dot” record icon to begin automatically taking a screencap of each of the URLs in your list:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://scholarslab.org/assets/post-media/2019-01-31-tweet-screenshot-3.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the script finishes running, you’ll have screencaps of all the URLs!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 15 Apr 2019 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2019/04/15/automating-webpage-tweet-screencaptures/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2019/04/15/automating-webpage-tweet-screencaptures/</guid>
        
        <category>digital-humanities</category>
        
        <category>advice-tutorial</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>DH archiving on the Scholars' Lab Blog</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally posted on the Scholars’ Lab blog on &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/archiving-dh-part-2-the-problem-in-detail/&quot;&gt;March 11, 2019&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/archiving-dh-part-2-the-problem-in-detail/&quot;&gt;Scholars’ Lab blog&lt;/a&gt;, Ammon Shepherd has been leading a series of collaborative blog posts about the challenges of archiving or preserving digital humanities projects. The first post in the series, by Ammon, is &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/archiving-dh-part-one/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Ammon and UVA Library colleagues Lauren Work and Brandon Butler, I co-authored a piece of the second post in the series, which goes into the challenges of archiving DH projects in more detail. I recommend you read that whole post &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/archiving-dh-part-2-the-problem-in-detail/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, but I’ve also copied my piece (on the issues resulting from the humans that underlie all technology) below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The human labor underlying technology is not easily sustainable; even when you have folks committed to the work, the kind and amount of labor required to maintain and update a project can shift away from what someone is willing or able to support, and external pressures (job changes, family, other projects, aging, retirement) also arise. I (Amanda, hi!) am particularly interested in how technical sustainability is impacted by the human labor of moderating online spaces, from my experiences moderating both my digital dissertation project &lt;a href=&quot;https://infiniteulysses.com&quot;&gt;Infinite Ulysses&lt;/a&gt; (a social platform for annotating/commenting on James Joyce’s novel) and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://tinyurl.com/DHSlack&quot;&gt;Digital Humanities Slack&lt;/a&gt; I started (a set of themed chat rooms with over 2,000 digital humanist members; co-moderated by Alan G. Pike, Sam Abrams, Alex Gil, Brandon Walsh, Ed Summers, Paige C. Morgan, Jeremy Boggs, Eleanor Dickson, Liz Rodrigues, and Erin Pappas).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moderation is both the work of controlling spam and intentional harassment in a community, as well as designing and implementing practices such as a code of conduct to both address the negative and encourage positive community behaviors. It’s been exhilarating using technology to collaborate with folks I don’t know and create online communities together with them: if you’ve taught DH in the classroom, think of the students who respond along the lines of “DH is exactly what I do or want to do, I just didn’t have a term for it before” but expand them to include folks from all over the world and more diverse walks of life. But this work has also been a significant source of anxiety, balancing my responsibility to the community with my desire to help folks learn to be more positive influences on that community, and needing to enforce the line after which a community member cannot healthfully continue as a community member. That stress was largely why I moved Infinite Ulysses from a Drupal site allowing commenting, to a static archived version without commenting. (Relatedly, I’ve &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.org/blog/moderation-running-dh-online-communities&quot;&gt;just blogged&lt;/a&gt; on some of the work I’ve been doing to make online moderation of academic communities more sustainable!)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 15 Apr 2019 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2019/04/15/archiving-dh-part-2-the-problem-in-detail/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2019/04/15/archiving-dh-part-2-the-problem-in-detail/</guid>
        
        <category>digital-humanities</category>
        
        <category>meta-dh</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Notes: Workflows to consider before opening a DH lab (Purdue version)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part of &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/tag/meta-dh/&quot;&gt;my meta-DH series&lt;/a&gt; documenting DH/DS infrastructure: the hows &amp;amp; whys of treating a project team, lab, department, or campus as itself a DH project.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Caveat&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;This post consists of notes taken during my former &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/tag/purdue-dh/&quot;&gt;DH Librarian role at Purdue&lt;/a&gt; (2015-2017), rather than my latest thinking at Scholars’ Lab. I’ll be sharing that updated thinking here soon!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What workflows should I think through before the Purdue Libraries DH Lab can open its doors?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;IP policy: okay to post work to GitHub? using what license?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Project management: Basecamp? Asana? Trello? something that can connect to GitHub, IFTTT or Zapier, or the Archives &amp;amp; Special Collections unit’s Drupal workflow if it’s created there&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Code of conduct for events, interactions, collaborations, social media (including commitment to equitable representation via speakers and event participants)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How do new or learning coders participate in technical work?: Development/experimentation server, checklists for coders and whoever is approving moves to the production site&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;General server workflow: production, test, staff development, learner experimentation servers/VMs and flow among servers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Policy on what projects we host ourselves&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Policy on best practices: usability, accessibility, public participation, outreach, research publication, technical stack (e.g. when possible build a static site)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Workflow for preserving projects: Webrecorder, BagIt, video of narrated exploration; LOCKSS; Purdue repo’s and Archives &amp;amp; Special Collections unit; workflow for collapsing dynamic sites into static ones&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sample contract for working with DH Lab staff: mutual agreements&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sample contract with Libraries IT concerning technical coverage and ASC on web archiving (if interested)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Web design and development checklist&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Usability and accessibility checklist (web, events, publications)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Best practices doc for digital editions: who locates, transcribes/digitizes/proofs, uploads (as individual pages) text?; signed documentation of IP right for use of text?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Workflow for working with Archives &amp;amp; Special Collections artifacts: security, moving objects between offices/buildings&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Workflow for staff adding resources, people, etc. to “DH at Purdue” site&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Social media policy: tone, etiquette, access, schedule for Twitter, blog, Facebook&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;IT workflow (negotiating how we work alongside the Libraries’ existing IT team): meet early in project/grant design, accessibility/video captioning, service contract, data plan w/security, accessibility compliance, longterm hosting plans&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 25 Nov 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/11/25/workflows-before-opening-DH/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/11/25/workflows-before-opening-DH/</guid>
        
        <category>digital-humanities</category>
        
        <category>meta-dh</category>
        
        <category>notes</category>
        
        <category>purdue-dh</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Notes: Wise resource investments for a DH initiative (Purdue version)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part of &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/tag/meta-dh/&quot;&gt;my meta-DH series&lt;/a&gt; documenting DH/DS infrastructure: the hows &amp;amp; whys of treating a project team, lab, department, or campus as itself a DH project.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Caveat&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;This post consists of notes taken during my former &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/tag/purdue-dh/&quot;&gt;DH Librarian role at Purdue&lt;/a&gt; (2015-2017), rather than my latest thinking at Scholars’ Lab. I’ll be sharing that updated thinking here soon!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ideas about making wise resource investments:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ask “Should we even build a center?” and explore other metaphors/options&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Convene a Libraries DH initiative advisory committee: not oversight/supervision, but resource and advocates for my DH in the department (e.g. on the hiring committee)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Require potential faculty fellows/project members to attend one term of “introduction to DH” workshops first before committing to collaboration, using MITH’s DH Incubator model (lessons in finding, creating, cleaning, sharing, documenting data; collaboration best practices, why and how to credit everyone involved in your work: how to use GoogleDocs, Trello, Doodle polls; common mistakes using new methodologies; joining the DH online community via blogging and Twitter)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sign mutual contract with collaborators indicating expected deliverables and deadlines, checkpoints and what will happen if work not done, and expectations for crediting and citing all team members in publications and presentations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Send Purdue DHers at all levels out to train (HILT in Indianapolis, RBS), then bring back to campus to give a presentation on what they learned&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Invest in collaborators, not projects&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Train the trainers (peer review, personal research &amp;amp; professionalism time for all)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Publications (questions by Geoffrey Pullum, “To co-author, or not to co-author?” with slight alterations to fit our needs): What names will appear on title page? What order? Who/what has IP rights? Can any team members recycle paper’s content for conference presentation or for inclusion/adaptation in other work including journal articles and books? What happens if the project is dropped or one member fails to uphold their contract? Would other team members be allowed to wrap up the project or publications about the project as desired (and publish under what names)? For continuing projects, how long should all team members names stay on the front page? (All names should always stay on a history or about page).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;See also students’ (UCLA) and collaborators’ (MITH) bills of rights. Include info on assuring student mentorship for all assistance, internships, jobs, teaching, and mentoring—not e.g. data entry.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;All panels, sets of conference keynotes, and hiring should look for unconscious bias and be structured to support inclusion.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CRM for consultation/campus DH tracking?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Consultation appointment set up includes consent to code of conduct, optional inclusion in campus DH directory&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Public workflows a la Guelph (what we do/don’t do, what effort involved…)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 25 Nov 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/11/25/wise-resource-investments-digital-humanities-initiative/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/11/25/wise-resource-investments-digital-humanities-initiative/</guid>
        
        <category>digital-humanities</category>
        
        <category>meta-dh</category>
        
        <category>notes</category>
        
        <category>purdue-dh</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Notes: Planning a DH lab's physical location (Purdue version)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part of &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/tag/meta-dh/&quot;&gt;my meta-DH series&lt;/a&gt; documenting DH/DS infrastructure: the hows &amp;amp; whys of treating a project team, lab, department, or campus as itself a DH project.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Caveat&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;This post consists of notes taken during my former &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/tag/purdue-dh/&quot;&gt;DH Librarian role at Purdue&lt;/a&gt; (2015-2017), rather than my latest thinking at Scholars’ Lab. I’ll be sharing that updated thinking here soon!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dh-lab-physical-space&quot;&gt;DH Lab physical space&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have strong need for a space for project work (e.g. 3D scanning and printing), team meetings, class demonstrations, events, and the ability to livestream and record (e.g. for later DH website hosting, classroom watching, sharing with Archives &amp;amp; Special Collections [ASC] donors) project work, demos, and presentations. I propose we initially identify an interim location that could be used over the next 1-3 years while we pilot the projects outlined above and seek major external funding—preferably somewhere we could begin occupying with a minimum of renovation, cost, and time (the newly arrived 3D setup cannot be unpacked until we have a dedicated space). I’m calling this initial, low-cost space a “DH Lab” as we’ll be focused on research and development there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;DH Center (3-6 years in)&lt;/em&gt;. We’ll also apply for external funding for a formal “DH Center”, which could increase the types of DH we nurture from Libraries-focused R&amp;amp;D to broader campus work such as classroom tours and one-off class visits to the center.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In the long run&lt;/em&gt;, there’s strong mutual interest from the ASC and DH in locating a more formal DH Center side-by-side with the ASC, turning the HSSE 4th floor non-ASC space into the DH Center. This would both ease our daily collaborations, and visually demonstrate to the campus the flow of possible scholarship from acquisition, processing, teaching, and research in the ASC through research, teaching, and diverse publication in the DH Center. Much of our initial DH work will develop from the expertise and collaboration of the ASC, and we should improve the DH conversation (where archival expertise and labor are sometimes left out of the conversation) by visibly showcasing the ASC’s critical partnership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;DH position in the org chart&lt;/em&gt;. I’m not advocating the DH Center being positioned within the ASC, to allow for autonomy and partnerships with other campus units. However, we discussed (in the DSC) exploring changes to the current department organization structure that make collaborations and reporting better represent our developing cohesion as partnered curation and digital creation spaces. In particular, I’d like to think about where we’d be placed as a potential research center with its own staff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-a-dedicated-dh-space-provides&quot;&gt;What a dedicated DH space provides&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s important to have a space where work can be left as-is without needing to be secured or tidied away; to visibly associate a set location with our DH initiative, rather than using random campus spaces for different events; and where we can customize the space to specific DH needs (including video capture and live-streaming of project work and presentations).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A dedicated physical DH space would&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;provide a visible, fixed physical location for DH presentations, workshops, and teaching from which the audience would always leave aware of our Libraries DH initiative, and knowing where to return (or point colleagues) with any future DH needs of their own&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;include space tailored to digital project research and discussion, 3D equipment use, and both livestreaming and video-recording of project work and presentations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;showcase our own Libraries DH (and related) research as both model projects and opportunities for collaborating with us, and model best practices for collaboration&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;develop space where interdisciplinary projects can grow and people across Purdue are incentivized to cross paths and locate shared interests&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;allow informal overlap among Libraries staff working or interested in DH, growing DH expertise in-department via drop-in times and informal reading groups and coffee sessions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;provide the equipment necessary to DH presentation and iterative publishing needs (good projection monitors, demo’ing live websites and tools, supporting audience members downloading and tweeting, capturing a live video feed and better audio/video for later hosting on the DH website)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A dedicated/non-reservable space&lt;/em&gt;. If we convert the CSC to a DH lab, I would like to model the room on Swaim and make the space non-reservable. This allows us to leave leave our expensive 3D equipment out when in the middle of use (because of how hot the printer gets and potential for liquid filament to stain other areas), use the space for informal ASC+Press+DH work (in addition to formal meetings) without needing to schedule these impromptu sessions, and keep areas where we’ll be working with ASC collections and 3D prints free from food and drink.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A social and experimental space&lt;/em&gt;. Longtime DHer Stephen Ramsay has said, “I cannot think of a successful digital humanities center — anywhere in the world — that did not begin with a bunch of people who had found each other through various means and who were committed to the bold and revolutionary project of talking to one another about their common interests.” DH labs thrive on supporting collaboration, not service. To accomplish this, we need to leave unscheduled, unplanned space for unexpected opportunities to arise, designing a space where you can come to chat about DH, find partners and mentors, and get help jumpstarting your research. I’ll work with Libraries strategic communication, outreach, and marketing experts to publicize our work and these opportunities once we’re ready.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;floorplan-and-major-purchases&quot;&gt;Floorplan and major purchases&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following approval, I would continue working with Candy on a proposed room layout, identifying furnishings we already have in the attic, and budgeting for any additional items needed from preferred vendors. I would also work with RaeLynn and Sarah to change the room’s scheduling status.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a more specific list of furnishings and proposed layout, but below is a summary of the work spaces I’m anticipating:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Individual work desks (4, pending additional DH staff and 2 post-docs, and can also be used by project collaborators)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A conference table and seating that can be re-arranged for large group meetings, demos, and presentations (and, if we have the furniture in the attic already, a separate informal area with armchairs)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Station for 3D imaging and printing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Station for livestreaming, video-recording work and presentations, and video editing; including a computer and monitor that can be swiveled for use at the 3D scanning and printing station, and two dedicated external hard drives for 3D and video file backup&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And the major purchases anticipated:&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Webcam for livestreaming&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Video camera (and accessories speakers, microphone, tripods, disks, 2 HDs to store videos and 3D scans, video editing software; both cameras could be checked out by Libraries staff for non-DH events)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Computer stations: at least one dedicated computer for 3D imaging and video editing (plus accessories: keyboard, mouse, monitor, dock)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A presentation-size wall-mounted digital monitor (as an alternative to the projector screens that allow higher definition and better color fidelity)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Optional: 1-2 computer monitors facing through the glass walls into the library, for display of Purdue Libraries DH projects and other interesting DH projects and visualizations to passerby&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dh-lab-users&quot;&gt;DH Lab users&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I envision our DH Lab as an R&amp;amp;D space for DH prototyping projects, teaching, and events, not as an open service space that can be booked by others. Its earliest users would be project work including experimentation with the 3D setup and formal meetings and demos (which can be livestreamed and.or video-recorded for teaching and publicity uses), a drop-in space for collaborators working on this year’s major grant proposals toward a DH Center and ASC+DH+Press/SPS co-evolution, and room for group DH consultations. If we begin to add DH graduate research assistants, staff, and/or post-docs, this will be space to work together (although retaining private offices for each staffer would allow for sometimes necessary focus or conference calls). In the near future, the space could support invited DH speakers and workshop leaders,a s well as Libraries-led intensive summer workshops for faculty and graduate students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Future uses could include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;As a drop-in space, possibly jumpstarted by partnerships with student groups such as the English Department’s Graduate Technology Working Group, or by creating a new digital dissertations in Africana Studies cohort with Ron Stephens (AASRC director and professor)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Scheduled class visits for lessons and project demos&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hosting an experimental, Libraries-taught DH and ASC and/or Press class and associated drop-in space for students working on their class project&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We need to exist in the Libraries to increase access and cross-disciplinary collaboration in ways individual departments cannot. An actual physical space associated with regular DH speakers and training opportunities fosters a community that’s both interdisciplinary and can reduce barriers among different university roles (student, staff, faculty, librarian).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;initial-basic-physical-space-setup&quot;&gt;Initial, basic physical space setup&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Space rental cost?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Basic renovations &amp;amp; space cleanup&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If possible, small rooms or cubicles (one director’s office, one huddle room for sharing by other staff; both with desks, desk chairs, computers, monitors, peripherals)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Large conference table and chairs (collapsible/rolling tables to allow for different room setups)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lockable area for artifacts, 3D equipment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Basic furniture (chairs, tables)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Signage outside&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Projector, screen, large monitors, livestreaming camera, conference phone setup, presentation podium with speakers, microphone&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cheap coffee maker (invite people to hang out and chat, rather than leave the space for coffee or chat in non-DH spaces like Starbucks)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clarity on who can access the space, whether the space can be booked by others or used for after-hours events by others; generally no other use should be made of the DH space, with requests for use needing to come through the DH Specialist and uses that are actually particularly in need of what the DH space uniquely offers supported if/when they don’t interrupt normal work (e.g. class visits, speakers and livestreaming talks)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ideal-room-setup-furniture&quot;&gt;Ideal room setup, furniture&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(&lt;em&gt;After large external grant for renovation/model DH center.&lt;/em&gt;)
We would need keys or key cards and a list of everyone with access to these spaces; ideally, we’d use IDs as key cards that could let people into the class/meeting space but not into offices or areas with equipment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Twitter scroller/blink(1) setup for server/project use status, social media oversight&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;DH books and shelving&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Waiting space armchairs and coffee table&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Shelves/display for old books, old computing stuff&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Etsy neon signs with DH terms&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Window blinds&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Framed posters of cool and/or Purdue DH projects&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Door and over-door signs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In/out/ring bell signs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Security/rekeying of main doors&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Locked space for 3d equipment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“This is an office; here’s how to sign up for a consultation” sign. If space is highly visible, this will deflect random walk-ins from interrupting work and inform those actually interested in DH to get in touch without interrupting work; we’ll probably have a mix of days with no sign/doors open (Mondays and Tuesdays, when consultations are scheduled or on days with visiting speakers), and days with doors closed so project team members can concentrate on their work. Will need further thinking to balance desire for a space that increases visibility and draws in passersby, with need for researchers to have interrupted focus.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Large digital screen (like at Brown) instead of projector+screen, for presentations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Podium, speakers, microphone, pointer, dongles&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Conference table and chairs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Video camera + webcam&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Demo computer and monitor and peripherals&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Special ASC transport cart/checklist&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dry-erase boards and markers and erasers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Water, garbage, recycling, fridge, microwave, coffee maker&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Branded stickers, bookmarks, mugs/shirts for presenters only&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Office with door for director&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Analyst office?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cave/commons desk and 3rd huddle room with telephone and internet&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Monitors for outside walls&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Inside monitors (Big DIVA, IU, DH projects, Twitter)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Folding chairs/tables for events&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Monitors and desk space for personal laptop hookups&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Water/fridge/microwave and coffee maker, informal area for watercooler-style chats, snacks, eating lunch together&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 25 Nov 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/11/25/planning-dh-lab-physical-location/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/11/25/planning-dh-lab-physical-location/</guid>
        
        <category>digital-humanities</category>
        
        <category>meta-dh</category>
        
        <category>purdue-dh</category>
        
        <category>notes</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Notes: A mission statement for digital humanities (Purdue version)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part of &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/tag/meta-dh/&quot;&gt;my meta-DH series&lt;/a&gt; documenting DH/DS infrastructure: the hows &amp;amp; whys of treating a project team, lab, department, or campus as itself a DH project.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Caveat&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;This post consists of notes taken during my former &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/tag/purdue-dh/&quot;&gt;DH Librarian role at Purdue&lt;/a&gt; (2015-2017), rather than my latest thinking at Scholars’ Lab. I’ll be sharing that updated thinking here soon!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post (everything below) is from a post I was drafting back when I was designing Purdue Libraries’ DH initiative; some parts weren’t completely fleshed out, and the “values” list doesn’t reflect my current thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stuff below—identifying what our values are, and stating that we mean to prioritize them—doesn’t mean that prioritizing or “doing the work” of those values will happen. This isn’t the work. The work is doing stuff that performs, amplifies, shares, teaches, argues for these values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with a code of conduct, it’s more dangerous to say you’re going to do (or are doing) something and then not stand by that promise, than to not make the promise at all. Lots of institutions say they value diversity, but either they don’t follow up on that claim at all (or enough), or they define the term so broadly as to neutralize any benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s easy to say you’re going to do a thing, and harder to imbue your work with the values you think you care about. I’m sharing this publicly now for a couple reasons: I want to be held publicly accountable to show I value these things. As we get deeper into specific projects, I hope to post what each project aims for, and to follow up with periodic analysis of whether we’ve held to those goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My dissertational &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.infinteulysses.com&quot;&gt;Infinite Ulysses&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; work, for example, has failed at doing its best to support all the values I list below—but &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2013/12/02/valuespost&quot;&gt;stating my values at the beginning of that project&lt;/a&gt; was essential to helping me realize the project’s shortcomings later on, and to build my knowledge so my future work can do better. (You can read about the most obvious problem from &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2014/05/27/inclusivityeditioncanon&quot;&gt;a mid-dissertation post here&lt;/a&gt;, the conclusion of which I no longer agree with.) I also want to encourage others to document and self-reflect on their work, by contributing to the existing pool of statements and charters holding scholars to their values—just as I’ve been encouraged by work like Scott Weingart’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://scottbot.net/pledges/&quot;&gt;Pledges&lt;/a&gt; page and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/about/charter&quot;&gt;Scholars’ Lab charter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;identifying-values&quot;&gt;Identifying values&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I built on past mission statements and charters I’ve encountered (DH or otherwise). On my dry-erase board, I made a list of things I think I care about and/or I think our DH initiative should value, given our experts, resources, and department and campus mission and strategic statements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a more public and participatory humanities through DH, with engagement with non-academics recognized as scholarship&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;topic, practitioner, and audience diversity and inclusion, pervasively rather than as an add-on&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;move beyond the idea that libraries can be neutral: choose work that is actively good, not just not-bad (e.g. explicit anti-racist approaches)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;accessibility and universal design from the beginning of projects&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;participatory design with a project’s intended audience from the beginning of projects, not just user testing at the end&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;listening and amplification, e.g. through&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;full credit and IP retention for all involved in making a project regardless of professional role, affiliation, or type of work performed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;fully citing &amp;amp; crediting the resources we build on (with especial care for under-cited digital resources and alt-ac scholars)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;care to not accidentally nor intentionally overstate, when stating our involvement in collaborative projects or in other scholars’ projects (and knowledge that the larger our initiative grows, the more potential there is for people to incorrectly assume any DHer or DH project on campus involves us or is ours)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;recognition of multiple publics, and funding and designing with under-supported publics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;recording today’s campus through the eyes of our community (e.g. the students who use our Archive to study past students), but only when we can do so in a rewarding, respectful, safe way&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;open access, reuse, remix, and user-friendly documentation allowing these&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;share about our project work during and after the work to help others understand the choices and effort that goes into various kinds of DH&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;making project IP, privacy, data management clear to users (including any tracking such as Google Analytics) and a public plan for how data and site users will be impacted if funding or maintenance of the site are cut off&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;projects that are sustainable &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; explicitly ephemeral and well documented; create space for experimentation and failure&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;clear ways to accept, credit, and incorporate user feedback&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;only involve or build communities if you can commit to tending them well and enforcing a code of conduct that protects community members&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;student mentorship, and funding and professional development support for non-tenure-track-faculty such as adjuncts, continuing lecturers, and students&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;evaluable mission statements for projects&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;time for reflection on past work and realigning new strategy to fix previous failures&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;prioritize work that supports collaboration and offers potential for a branching impact (invest in training the trainers)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;participate in and support broader DH initiatives beyond our campus&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;if-we-think-these-are-what-we-value-how-are-we-acting-on-these-values&quot;&gt;If we think these are what we value, how are we acting on these values?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ID specific actions and/or policies supporting these&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I’ll keep track of any DH visitors/speakers and ensure we’re using our funds and time to support a diverse representation of DH; projects must explicitly advance one of our stated core values (access, diversity, inclusion), with a preference for projects that include mentorship for students and credit for all team members&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What do we study? We’ll likely want to work with our many Objects That Have Been in Space and other neat aerospace history stuff—how do we keep that from pulling us toward work by and for white dudes?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Initial philosophy-heavy proposal focused on foundational policies: what would we do, and what wouldn’t we do? how would we interact with campus IT? what funding needs will we have?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Next step is report/request/objectives &amp;amp; goals doc that outlines how we’ll do the work over the next two years&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-dh-mission-statement&quot;&gt;A DH mission statement&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This was originally the abstract for my first proposal to the Purdue Libraries on where our DH initiative should go. I’m thinking it will evolve into charters for major projects here (like a possible DH space, and a DH team-taught course), so I’m capturing each version in a GitHub repo so we can track changes over time.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I propose we initially focus our digital humanities initiative on a collaboration among DH, the ASC (&lt;em&gt;note: Purdue Archives &amp;amp; Special Collections, a Libraries unit&lt;/em&gt;), and the University Press &amp;amp; Scholarly Publishing Services (&lt;em&gt;also located in the Libraries!&lt;/em&gt;), with a focus on &lt;strong&gt;co-evolving these units while developing infrastructure toward a more open (diverse, inclusive, accessible, participatory, real-time, relevant) humanities.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I envision a DH Center for the Open Humanities in the Purdue Libraries, serving as the hub of the campus DH community. We will build a culture of digital scholarship, assisting through incubation rather than service: connecting potential collaborators, recording DH work for institutional memory, modeling best practices and inspiring other DH work with our own experiments, showcasing the Libraries’ strengths, and raising visibility for Purdue’s digital humanities successes through diverse publication forms and audiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I take the Libraries’ valuing of diversity, inclusion, and access as core motivating ideals, and plan strong demonstrations in all three areas of the latest (2016-2019) strategic plan (particularly 1:3, 2, and 3:2-4). We should proactively develop what we want the digital humanities to be, by pursuing and publicizing projects that advance all our strategic values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In practical terms, our activities will include modeling DH research and publication best practices through collaborative internal projects, cross-campus collaboration and outreach, consultations and mentorship, and hosting events including a DH visiting speaker series, a day of talks by DHers from all over campus (co-hosted with the CLA), and intensive methodological training workshops. We will additionally maintain an information-rich “DH @ Purdue” website (including a campus DH directory), and design and co-teach pilot DH+ASC+Press courses giving students theoretical, technical, and alternative academic experience in building a DH project as a collaborator. Our work will emphasize collaboration and mentorship, value a more public and inclusive humanities, and lead by modeling effective DH research and teaching for other departments. Because we currently have limited staff time and resources, we’ll focus on building a sustainable funding model, doing a few specific pilot projects extremely well, and DH networking on campus through events and consultations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I propose a two-phase approach:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[3 sentences on specific plans for fund allocation in the next two years]&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[3 sentences on specific plans for fund allocation years 3-5]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During Phase 1, [paragraph on specific major grant project idea].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of this document offers details on specific activities we could pursue, longterm goals for the initiative, reasoning for requested funding and hiring, and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;next-steps&quot;&gt;Next steps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rewrite this philosophy-heavy proposal into an objectives and goals report with specific requests, actions, and timeline.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 25 Nov 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/11/25/mission-statement-digital-humanities-purdue/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/11/25/mission-statement-digital-humanities-purdue/</guid>
        
        <category>digital-humanities</category>
        
        <category>meta-dh</category>
        
        <category>purdue-dh</category>
        
        <category>notes</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
