<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Literature Geek</title>
    <description>digital humanities</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2019 10:06:35 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2019 10:06:35 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.7.4</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>How We Talk and Write about DH Jobs</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post was co-authored with &lt;a href=&quot;https://walshbr.com/&quot;&gt;Brandon Walsh&lt;/a&gt; and originally posted on the Scholars’ Lab blog on &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/dh-cover-letters/&quot;&gt;October 10, 2019&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early this summer, we (authors Brandon and Amanda!) planned a post about job search materials, but finishing up the draft got delayed by several weeks. In the intervening time, a small Twitter debate on the subject of academic job advice occurred, and we ended up holding off this post for a few months while discussing how to do it well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The debate in question: someone shared the job advice they generally give students on the academic job market, and folks responded with frustrations about the prescriptiveness, privilege, and goals of the academic job advice genre. Since then, we’ve also appreciated &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hralperta/status/1143557245168476160?s=21&quot;&gt;inspiring work being done on the topic by Hannah Alpert-Abrams&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://hcommons.org/groups/academic-job-market-support-network/&quot;&gt;The Academic Job Market Support Network&lt;/a&gt; that she spearheads shares a lot of the spirit behind what we intended to do with our job search materials, so we’re taking this as an opportunity to revisit the post we had planned. We have both uploaded cover letters from our pasts to the AJMSN (Brandon’s letter &lt;a href=&quot;https://hcommons.org/?get_group_doc=1003473/1570202258-HeadofGraduateProgramsCoverLetter.docx&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and Amanda’s letter &lt;a href=&quot;https://hcommons.org/?get_group_doc=1003473/1570038081-CoverLetter.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), and we talk a bit about our reasoning below. We’ll offer some general thoughts about job searches in digital humanities, and annotate each other’s cover letters. We thought the latter might be a useful exercise beyond just sharing them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;slightly-better-job-advice-take-two&quot;&gt;Slightly Better Job Advice, Take Two&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Framing an academic job search exclusively in terms of handy tips undervalues the degree of luck that goes into any search. &lt;em&gt;Do these things&lt;/em&gt;, such advice seems to suggest, &lt;em&gt;and the just and right meritocracy will reward you with a job&lt;/em&gt;. But the academic job market is anything but just, and anything but a pure measure of merit&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The same is true, of course, for job markets beyond academia. Digital humanities job searches, be they for faculty positions or otherwise, suffer from the same issues. Internally we’ve had a lot of conversation about how to share job advice with our students. We’re frequently called upon to do so, and we want to do it well. So we thought it worth sharing a few of the things we try to consider below. Keep in mind, of course, that this is not an exhaustive list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The academic job market is not identical with all job markets in academia. There is a range of different careers that engage in intellectual work, careers that might be called alt-ac (though there are good reasons for not using that term to describe them). Paths to these careers are often just as obscured as paths to professorships, and resources for how to navigate these types of job searches are scarce. Resources for finding and thinking about these kinds of careers are one of the key things we can provide students.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Students need our support. In particular, refusing to share resources about job searches, even if the act is well meaning, can reinforce privileged access to those same materials. Our initial reason for writing this post was that we noticed we were repeatedly sharing the same cover letters with folks looking for work. We found ourselves wondering how many other people at UVA or elsewhere might not know to ask for such resources.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Offers to aid in job searches, on and off the tenure track, are better when they go beyond lists of advice. In particular, we try to help folks think through backup plans and suggest talking with a career center as part of the conversation about how to seek positions in the digital humanities. We try to speak from our own experiences but also to recognize our own limitations as resources. We do not have all the answers, but we still might be able to help in some way.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Student support like this necessarily includes emotional labor. For us (the authors), this has proven unavoidable. In conversations we try to emphasize that the student is smart enough and good enough for this work, that the job market is not a reflection on them, and that our current jobs are the results of luck in a lottery system (where every time you win a lottery it makes winning future lotteries a bit more tipped in your favor…). The fact that we have jobs does not necessarily mean our advice will be helpful (CW for war: see e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Survivorship_bias#In_the_military&quot;&gt;Abraham Wald on survivorship bias&lt;/a&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;). In short, it is not enough to tell students that they need do X and Y in order to be successful. In the Lab we believe these conversations need to engage with the messy work of what the job search entails.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Advice about any job market should come with a frank discussion about all the factors involved in being offered a job (i.e. how many factors are out of candidates’ hands), and about the precarious nature of employment in the field that the particular position may or may not play into.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re not sure how we share our cover letters given this context, but it still seems worth doing; we’re going to continue advising the local students who work with us, and we’d like to help students who are elsewhere if we can. Some of the ways we try to make our advising do more good than harm include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thinking about intent vs. impact: job advice is often “well meaning”, but what matters is the environment it builds up or dismantles, who it tells is worthwhile as they already are vs. who it tells to change, who it empowers with information. Consider whether telling a student that &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; don’t judge them for XYZ, but that interviewers will, has the same impact as you judging them.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Not posting job ads to the SLab Slack fellows channels (where they might be regular, unwanted reminders of job market stress to folks who aren’t even looking for work right now, or otherwise want to limit when they’re thinking about jobs). We’ve moved to including a list of interesting jobs to the end of our lab newsletter instead, where students can regularly choose to look at them if they choose.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Moving to a public newsletter as a means of distributing these posts means that students can opt in without self-declaring themselves as on the job market, which allows for greater transparency about the process. It becomes less about knowing who you have to ask - anyone (even non-UVA people) can get access to that newsletter if they choose.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Focusing our commentary not on “what others will expect” or “the right way to do things” (e.g. how to write the salutation), but instead on examples of how to best communicate one’s personal strengths via cover letter. In this way, we hope to keep the focus on the individual person and how they can take ownership of their own background rather than on how to please an anonymous committee (this can be a moving target).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Leavening advice with affirmation of students as scholars and humans; helping them think about how to do what they value in life, even if they can’t do that as their main job. In short, academia has a way of encouraging people to think about their academic work and academic “merit” as deep reflections of their “worth” as a person. We try to reaffirm the fact that every person is worthwhile&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;thoughts-on-some-specific-dh-cover-letters&quot;&gt;Thoughts on some specific DH cover letters&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below, each of us shares the text of one of our cover letters for the other to annotate. The comments below reflect what we’ve tried to do when we have served on hiring committees and reviewed cover letters: avoid the stuff we feel we &lt;em&gt;shouldn’t&lt;/em&gt; evaluate on, and what we &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; look for. Of course, these should be taken with a grain of salt. Our hope is that sharing the letters in this format will offer a bit more insight into how we think about DH job searches. It’s also worth noting that we each clearly read for different things. Similarly, other people serving on DH hiring committees might look for different things. We’ll focus on the hiring experience for:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Brandon’s current role: Head of Student Programs at the University of Virginia Library’s Scholars’ Lab&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Amanda’s previous role: tenure-track assistant professor and DH specialist at Purdue University Libraries&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While our comments below are about our cover letters, you might be interested in checking out other hiring and school info we’ve shared: Brandon’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/in-out-across-with-collaborative-education-and-digital-humanities-job-talk-for-head-of-graduate-programs/&quot;&gt;job talk&lt;/a&gt; for his current role, Amanda’s job talks for &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/disrupt-the-humanities-managing-director-job-talk/&quot;&gt;her current role&lt;/a&gt; (with links to job talks shared by three other scholars as well!) and &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2016/02/28/DHjobtalk&quot;&gt;her previous faculty role&lt;/a&gt;; and Amanda’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2016/06/20/digital-humanities-dissertation-defense-talk&quot;&gt;doctoral defense talk&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2016/06/14/digital-humanities-dissertation-defense-advice&quot;&gt;advice about defense talks&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2012/11/27/info-dump-humanities-doctoral-candidacy-exams-advice/&quot;&gt;literature/DH PhD exams list and advice&lt;/a&gt;. We’ve added the cover letters to &lt;a href=&quot;https://academicjobmarketsupportnetwork.hcommons.org/&quot;&gt;an existing effort&lt;/a&gt; to gather and contextualize job materials led by Hannah Alpert-Abrams on &lt;em&gt;Humanities Commons&lt;/em&gt;—check out their &lt;a href=&quot;https://hcommons.org/groups/academic-job-market-support-network/documents/&quot;&gt;files page&lt;/a&gt; for other cover letters, various types of written statement, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started working at SLab on the same day and were not involved in the hiring of each other, so all comments are views from outside the search committee. You can check out the full cover letters on &lt;em&gt;Humanities Commons&lt;/em&gt;, and reading them in full first might be useful: &lt;a href=&quot;https://hcommons.org/?get_group_doc=1003473/1570202258-HeadofGraduateProgramsCoverLetter.docx&quot;&gt;Brandon’s cover letter&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://hcommons.org/?get_group_doc=1003473/1570038081-CoverLetter.pdf&quot;&gt;Amanda’s cover letter&lt;/a&gt;. You might wish to compare these to how the job ads described these roles: &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/are-you-our-next-head-of-graduate-programs/&quot;&gt;Head of Graduate Programs&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/assets/DigitalHumanitiesSpecialist.pdf&quot;&gt;Digital Humanities Specialist Assistant or Associate Professor&lt;/a&gt;. In what follows, we intersperse inset text of our letters with short, bulleted lists of comments from the other person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;brandons-cover-letter&quot;&gt;Brandon’s cover letter&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://hcommons.org/?get_group_doc=1003473/1570202258-HeadofGraduateProgramsCoverLetter.docx&quot;&gt;Brandon’s cover letter&lt;/a&gt;, notes by Amanda&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;I am writing to apply for the position of Head of Graduate Programs in the Scholars’ Lab at the University of Virginia. As an alumnus of both the Praxis Program and the Graduate Fellowship in Digital Humanities, I have a deep appreciation for the Scholars’ Lab’s commitment to experimental forms of collaborative, project-based pedagogy.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you have past experience or knowledge of what the place does, share that! You don’t have to have worked/learned at the place (as Brandon did at UVA) to speak to what specifically draws you there. E.g. maybe you’ve gotten a sense from their social media, a project or conference talk, or a blog post about what’s important to how the place works?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Brandon shows awareness and mutual commitment to some of the lab’s values here; he shares this in a way that lets the search committee learn something about &lt;em&gt;him&lt;/em&gt; (that he digs experimentation, collaboration), rather than something more abstract like “I would be honored to work at such a great place” that doesn’t give the committee info but does take up some of your limited space.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Most of the cover letters I’ve seen use the first paragraph to deliver information that isn’t really new—&lt;em&gt;this is my name, I’m not confused what position I’m applying for, I think I would be a good fit&lt;/em&gt;—so I like how he leads with a framing that &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; tell us more about him as a candidate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;I believe that my own extensive teaching record and my experiences as a digital humanities developer and project manager, all of which are shaped by my understanding of the Scholars’ Lab’s values, make me uniquely qualified for this position.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There’s limited space to tell the search committee about yourself, so rather than make his cover letter repeat his CV, Brandon connects up items in his past that could help him successfully fill this role’s goals. Rather than using himself as a reference (e.g. “I am very good at x” or “I am xyz adjectives”), Brandon points out that the past roles listed on his CV are connected as different approaches in DH, suggesting he’s both learned skills from being in a variety of different roles, and can probably work in an informed way with colleagues in those roles.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;He again recognizes specifics about the lab—that through our staff charter, choices, etc. we try to be attentive to how our values shape our work. Some institutions make learning about how they do work difficult, unfortunately.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Student mentoring has been my first priority for the duration of my career.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Brandon shares who he is as a professional and community member: articulating what matters to him, showing he understands what matters to this job, and going on to explicitly demonstrate how the two overlap.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;I have taught a number of digital humanities workshops and classes, but I am proudest of my recent work as co-administrator of the Undergraduate Digital Humanities Fellows program at Washington and Lee University, where I currently serve as Mellon Digital Humanities Fellow. This initiative attempts to adapt the principles of the Praxis Program to a liberal arts context by allowing undergraduates to engage in collaborative research projects of their own design. I serve in both supervisory and technical roles in this program, and my daily tasks range from scoping student projects to teaching technical lessons on GitHub or programming concepts in PHP. During the past year, I have worked with humanities students to design and implement digital archives, editions, and storytelling projects through a combination of hands-on training and mentoring.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The first half of this sentence (“I have taught a number of digital humanities workshops and classes”) could mean anything from teaching two small workshops ever, to multiple courses designed and taught himself—when hiring, readers may assume the lowest possible situation that your statement might mean, unless shown otherwise via specifics. Brandon helps us not need to guess—he doesn’t rehash his whole list of DHy skills here, but mentions a few in context in a way that suggests familiarity with other DH practices as well.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Specific examples, including names of methods, tech, approaches showing familiarity. A good way to demonstrate knowledge of an area is to describe what daily work practices look like—specific tools or methods, what your involvement in a project specifically looked like.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;I recognize that the vitality of a program depends upon a student community that extends beyond the bounds of the fellowship years, so I have created an outreach plan that builds our student network by having fellows visit other courses and mentor others as digital experts.
This student community can – and should – contribute to life beyond the walls of the academy: this year I am piloting a program that sends our fellows to a local High School AP Computer Science class to collaborate on digital projects. Drawing on the lessons I learned during my own training, my efforts always aim to teach the person not the material. Helping students to find the confidence to speak, act, and sometimes fail productively in public in roles like these is as important to me as any temporary success afforded by a project.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Brandon states some of his values and goals, then immediately identifies how he acted on these. This both backs up claimed values in his letter, and demonstrates experience reflecting on and iterating one’s practices to bring them into line with what you identify as important.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There’s use in defining commonplace terms. Everyone knows what “teaching” means, right? But is this someone who cares about “filling young minds” and also mocks their current students on social media, vs. someone who sees students as colleagues, fellow scholars, humans? Brandon’s approach in this paragraph helps the reader see if we’re actually talking about the same thing when we say “teaching” (same for “research”, “scholarship”, “service”, etc.).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;As a member of Washington and Lee’s digital humanities faculty committee, I have helped to develop the school’s digital humanities curriculum, which aims to provide students at all levels of expertise with an intellectual and practical understanding of innovative digital work. In particular, I have focused on collaborations that raise the skillsets of my colleagues as long-term investments in growing our resources. Working with Professor Sarah Horowitz and a student researcher on her interest in text analysis, for example, has led to both a co-taught class on digital history as well as a co-authored open access textbook.

The book is, foremost, a pedagogical exploration, an attempt to write an accessible introduction to digital text analysis for complete newcomers. The writing of this textbook was also, in itself, a teaching exercise: the writing process required Professor Horowitz to learn version control and Markdown in addition to a number of text analysis techniques. These experiences were part of a larger experiment that I spearheaded in collaborative writing and publishing that has led to invitations for presentations and workshops at DLF and Bucknell Digital Scholarship with our Digital Humanities Librarian.

As an experienced project manager and digital humanities developer, I also offer an advanced skillset to augment my teaching.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Brandon shows how he invests in people around him, making the place he works better for colleagues in different roles (here: student, staff, faculty).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When applying for a staff job from a doctoral and/or faculty background, it can be useful to demonstrate how those experiences don’t disadvantage you—i.e.  you don’t understand what the staff position will be like. Brandon manages to both show the skills he learned from his past work experiences, while also aiming them at the kinds of work he’d be doing if hired.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Brandon notes skills that might not be in the job ad, but are critical: collaboration, managing projects, a broad understanding of tech.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;I served for several years as the project manager of NINES, and I have given invited talks on project development at the University of Michigan, SUNY New Paltz, the University of Central Florida, and the Center for Networked Information. I have consistently worked to supplement this supervisory experience with the skills necessary to implement projects myself. During my time at Washington and Lee, I have deployed and maintained three Rails applications, supervised Omeka customizations, and designed text analyses in Python, in addition to carrying out my own research in machine learning and sound studies. These skills will allow me not only to lead workshops on the technical aspects of digital humanities research, but also to supplement the resources of the Scholars’ Lab by providing technical support to fellows myself.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It’s very good to share things you’re proud of! If you don’t highlight these, your search committee might never know about them. If you have trouble doing this, you might have friends or a supportive teacher who can help you remember experiences or decisions worth sharing here. Julia Evans has a good &lt;a href=&quot;https://jvns.ca/blog/brag-documents/&quot;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; about how to get comfortable talking about your strengths.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Brandon does a good job pitching his achievements for this staff role—sharing the things faculty hiring committees value, like invited talks, but coupling those with tech skills and his broader learning from those experiences. He comes across as someone who wants to be in a staff job that’s heavy on mentoring, collaborating, experimenting, rather than someone treating this job as an alternative to another career goal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;I know first-hand how transformative the right interventions can be in the lives of graduate students. The Scholars’ Lab’s commitment to equipping students at all levels for both the kinds of careers that they will find and the intellectual provocations they can make in the digital age has shaped my own thinking, and it continues to inform all of my work. I see this position in the Scholars’ Lab as the perfect opportunity for me to help others learn as I once did, and to use my skills and experiences to extend the excellent work of the Scholars’ Lab’s fellowship programs.

I look forward to discussing the great potential of the position with you.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I like the wording in the final sentence—”great potential” reminds me that I’ve gotten a sense from this letter that this is someone who’s thought hard about the strategy and tactics of student-focused DH, who is ready to do good in this role.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;amandas-cover-letter&quot;&gt;Amanda’s cover letter&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://hcommons.org/?get_group_doc=1003473/1570038081-CoverLetter.pdf&quot;&gt;Amanda’s cover letter&lt;/a&gt;, notes by Brandon&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Dear Purdue University Libraries team,

I'm a digital humanist with an Information M.S. (University of Michigan), new Literature Ph.D. (University of Maryland), and over eight years as a professional DH web developer and public-focused DH scholar, working since 2009 in multiple staff roles at the Maryland Institute for Technology in the Humanities (MITH). I write to apply for the Digital Humanities Specialist role.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The first thing I notice is how Amanda structured her letter differently than how I typically do so. I tend to treat cover letters like essays, where the structure of the thing to come will be laid out in the final sentence of the first paragraph. Amanda leads with her experience here, which is likely to make sure her cover letter gets past an initial quick read.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It’s perhaps also worth noting how wild and varied the paths often are for digital humanists. In this field maybe more than others it is not uncommon to tie together many seemingly disconnected life experiences into a narrative about yourself. The connections between library degrees, and PhD in English, and positions at a DH center all speak to each other in clear ways. But I can easily imagine a need to pull together a variety of different experiences that might not parse so easily for people. This seems fine to me. More on diverse life experiences below!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Another thing that stands out here is that Amanda does not just point out what she has done - she points out different experiences from very different contexts. Research experience as a graduate student, library experience, and hands-on experiences. It’s helpful to think in these terms when presenting yourself to a search committee. It’s not just about the work you’ve done. It’s also about the kinds of contexts and audiences to which this work exposes you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;As an example of my work, my recent dissertation project is InfiniteUlysses.com—an interface that brings scholars, teachers, and readers of all backgrounds together in annotating and discussing a challenging book, personalizing the annotations displayed to any given reader by their backgrounds, interests, and needs. Infinite Ulysses achieved sizable impact for a literature dissertation, with over 13,000 unique visitors during its first month of open beta. The challenge of helping everyone feel empowered to participate in the humanities drives my research and project design.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To underscore what Amanda says above - I usually tell people to make sure their letter is not an extension of their CV. When addressing things that appear in both, I usually try to make sure the things in the letter expand or provide context that you might not otherwise get in a CV. This text is great, because she expands on a project that might otherwise only get a line and not have the same impact.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I also like how she takes the work and expands upon it to describe what she learned from it. That sort of self-reflection is something I usually look for in cover letters and try to represent in my own.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Amanda’s accomplishments here and as articulated in the letter are impressive, but I often think it’s a matter of selling yourself regardless of whether or not you have done a lot, whether or not your blog has thousands of hits. Take the things you have done and use them as an opportunity to spin a story about yourself.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Successfully completing a non-monograph dissertation taught me how to champion others embarking on digital scholarship, both in educating their colleagues on their digital work, and in the practical aspects of project design, technical learning, and planning for the full life cycle of the project. I dealt with this last—DH long-term thinking and digital preservation—as MITH's Webmaster, auditing our two servers full of projects, files, and databases ranging back to 1999, and in my training and experience doing digital preservation work with MITH's early e-lit collection.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Another thing I often look for - the letter is a space to offer reflections on your experience. I like that Amanda takes the experience with the dissertation and goes a step further to show what it means in the broader narrative of how she approaches people and her work. In other words - it answers the “so what?” question. These moments of reflection can also be a chance to connect yourself to the values of the institution and position for which you are applying.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;As a student, it can often feel like you have no experience. But you do! It’s just a matter of taking those experiences you do have and extrapolating to how they would apply to other circumstances. So in this case, Amanda does a great job of showing how working as a dissertation and webmaster apply to other circumstances and to the position for which she’s applying. I often tell students to think of it like roleplaying. If you were in the position, what experiences have you had that you could imagine helping you? Write about them. Sometimes trying to imagine yourself doing the work can help you think further about how to present yourself for the application.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lastly I would note that it’s important to consider the practical skills you gain from doing digital work as distinct from the research aspects of that work. To be sure, they’re both tightly joined in practice. But it’s all too easy to get to the end of a digital project on Victorian archives and think, “this has given me experience with Victorian research and digital archives.” But there is also a whole range of other “soft skills” that such work gives you experience in - project management, software development, project promotion, etc. These are all things you can have experience in and they are also things you can discuss critically! Reflections on these parts of the process are often of immense use to other scholar practitioners. Think of them as experiences but also as potential objects of scholarly inquiry.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;My work has always been interdisciplinary in both topic and methodology. A few of my diverse past DH projects include:

* Co-organizing the first digital humanities and games unconference (THATCamp Games)  
* Developer on the &quot;Making DH More Open&quot; team's Braille Wordpress plugin  
* Data visualization and topic modeling of Digital Humanities Quarterly to explore DH citation networks (recipient of the inaugural ACH Microgrant)  
* Team teaching and design of a DH course for UMD's Digital Cultures and Creativity undergrads  
* Librarian-aimed user testing and documentation for BitCurator's archival digital forensics tools  

I offer excellent communication, teaching, and presentation skills, and am especially deft at research use of social media (over 2,000 Twitter followers) and blogging (over 22,000 unique blog visitors to date). I’ve worked in a number of pertinent roles: as a librarian and digital archivist, university teacher and student, web developer, and DH center staff, as well as alongside others in these roles. This background gives me inside experience of the different needs and values of these important scholarly constituents. After working on interdisciplinary teams for six years at one of the world's top digital humanities research centers, I'm a skilled translator between tech and non-tech colleagues, and my research best thrives through collaboration.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I think the reference to social media work here is useful. When I was hired at the Lab, they specifically cited my blogging and presence on Twitter as assets. You might not think about that kind of public outreach as tangible work, but it is! It’s often helpful to think about the value you bring to the institution beyond your research and teaching. This framing can be especially useful for positions beyond the tenure track in libraries or otherwise.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;One thing I notice about Amanda’s letter is that it really speaks to the diverse experiences she had when she applied to the position. That’s great! In academia I think we are sometimes challenged to think of ourselves as this coherent narrative where all roads lead to a single path. But, in practice, we have all sorts of experiences. And that broad background can be part of your narrative. We don’t all fit into neat boxes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;I'd love to discuss how my background in digital humanities service, training, research, and building would complement the Purdue University Libraries' learner-centered mission! Thank you for your time and consideration.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Small point, but it’s often quite clear when a single cover letter has been sent out to multiple institutions with the name of one simply subbed for another. There are small ways to flag that you actually are applying for this &lt;em&gt;specific position at this specific place&lt;/em&gt;, and this is an example of them. That’s to say, I like that Amanda doesn’t just say she is a good fit, she connects her experience to the mission of the institution in this last moment. It can be difficult to figure out what that mission is (in the Scholars’ Lab we have an explicit statement about &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.org/charter&quot;&gt;our values&lt;/a&gt;), but you could get clues from events, projects, research, and similar initiatives undertaken by the institution. If they’re committing time and energy to it, they care about it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In terms of thinking about how to find out the character of an institution, specific events or projects can help. But there are often large, general questions you could ask about a place that could help you think about their mission. Is it a small liberal arts college or an R1 institution? Is this a DH center you would be hired into or a single position apart from a larger network of support? Is the position part of a library? Is the position hired for a particular grant or is it sourced on hard money? Are we talking about an institution of teaching? higher education? cultural heritage? What sort of audience / public does the institution tend to cater to? There are a number of large buckets like these that institutions tend to fall into. While each organization is unique, thinking about large categories like these can help provide clues to what this particular one is about.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;endnotes&quot;&gt;Endnotes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The coiner of the word “meritocracy” intended it to ridicule the very ideas folks now use the term to convey. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I remember seeing a tweet recently where someone connected the infamous image of the bullet hole locations on the surviving planes to listening to some kind of job advice selectively—maybe listening to folks who got hired about what not to ask during interviews? If you know who tweeted this and wouldn’t mind, please let me know so I can cite them (@literature_geek on Twitter/visconti@virginia.edu). It’s important to record where ideas came from, even in smaller things like this post. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Brandon’s title has been expanded over the course of his work here; at the time of hiring, it was “Head of Graduate Programs”. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We thought this be more broadly useful to students than the cover letter for her current job, as that fits leaving a faculty role to direct a lab, rather than locating one’s first post-PhD job. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2019 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2019/10/10/digital-humanities-cover-letters-job-advice</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2019/10/10/digital-humanities-cover-letters-job-advice</guid>
        
        <category>digital-humanities</category>
        
        <category>meta-dh</category>
        
        <category>advice-tutorial</category>
        
        <category>grad-advice</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>DH Archiving: Data Policies for Small DH Projects</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally posted on the Scholars’ Lab blog on &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/archiving-dh-part-3-the-long-view/&quot;&gt;April 30, 2019&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/archiving-dh-part-3-the-long-view/&quot;&gt;Scholars’ Lab blog&lt;/a&gt;, Ammon Shepherd has been leading a series of collaborative blog posts about the challenges of archiving or preserving digital humanities projects. The first post in the series, by Ammon, is &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/archiving-dh-part-one/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Ammon led UVA Library colleagues Lauren Work and Brandon Butler and me on co-authoring a &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/archiving-dh-part-2-the-problem-in-detail/&quot;&gt;second piece in the series&lt;/a&gt;, which goes into the challenges of archiving DH projects in more detail. Ammon, Brandon Butler, and I have just co-authored a third piece in the series on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/archiving-dh-part-3-the-long-view/&quot;&gt;Scholars’ Lab blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recommend you read that whole post &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/archiving-dh-part-3-the-long-view/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, but I’ve also copied my piece (on creating a data policy for a smaller DH project) below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your project will most likely use data or generate data. You need to be clear up front on how you expect and desire others to be able to use, or not use, the data from your project. For a smaller, not institutionally supported DH project, a data policy can be a simple set of public commitments about the possible futures of your project. The following is a practical example of implementing a data policy for a small digital project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/assets/post-media/2019-04-30-infiniteulysses.png&quot; alt=&quot;Infinite Ulysses&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My (hey, this is Amanda!) &lt;a href=&quot;http://infiniteulysses.com/&quot;&gt;Infinite Ulysses&lt;/a&gt; project was dissertational research supported by a single person, but it also had a wide and varied audience for such a small project (12k unique visitors during the first couple weeks of beta opening) and hosted user-created content (1k annotations). Its focus on interface design and user studies, and the use of social media encouraging testing of the site, were important in inviting use by enough users from both inside and outside academia to address my questions about the impact of such a shared space on literary reading and learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, the site looking nice and having some publicity probably conveyed a permanency for the site that I was hopeful for at the time, and had some real plans and resources for continuing post-PhD, but was ultimately the dissertation project of a single person contributing their own limited time, money, and moderation stress to running the site. I should have done better making sure folks were clear that there was one person behind the project and no presumption of ongoing hosting, for example for folks planning long term or repeat readings (likely, given Ulysses’ length, difficulty, and rewards for rereadings) or planning to demo or use the site in a class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am happy that the project, from the start, did include a public document addressing both data privacy and data preservation plans for the project. For example, because the site invited and stored user annotations as they were reading a long and difficult novel, I had a responsibility to let folks know possible disasters (aka “I lose all your comments”) and what I was doing to prepare against those calamities. My public data policy stated: “This site has an automated daily backup that includes all user annotations and comments, as well as weekly server backups. In addition, the site is regularly replicated on a development and local server.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Critically, this public data policy included plans for if I needed to stop site interaction or take down the site for some reason. Even if your plan is for your project to exist in its current or an improved form ongoing, sharing a contingency plan from the start lets users make informed decisions about their activity with your project. My policy stated: “If the site ever needs to be shut down, go offline indefinitely, or be transferred to substantially different ownership, I’ll contact all users through the email address given on your user profile page with directions for downloading your content. Users will be given at least one month’s notice to export their content. Should such a situation ever occur, I’d prioritize keeping the site up but in static form (i.e. you can’t change or add to the annotations and comments anymore) so that it’s still available as a resource; users could then opt to use the Annotator.js browser plugin to continue the annotation of the text using an AnnotateIt account. If that ever becomes the case, I’ll post instructions to the front page of this site on how to continue using the site.” I did end up first shutting the site to new users, then to new annotations, and eventually migrating from Drupal to a static archived version of the site. I felt better about doing this given there was never an explicit promise to always run the site the way it currently ran (though see above caveats about site shininess and social media).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My data policy also helped project users protect and own their labor through documented paths to export their own work for use elsewhere or personal preservation: “users should be able to export their content with the push of a button”, ideally, in multiple non-proprietary formats that support both reading (e.g. HTML or TXT) and data manipulation (e.g. JSON or CSV).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To create a similar public data policy for a small DH project, you’ll want to ask yourself the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What might people build off this? Think about ways your site/data might be treated as a feed, API, or permanent fixture that you might not hear about, e.g. if folks could be running Twitter bots off the presumption of continuous new content or activity on your website, or use in a classroom.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What have people built on this? Uses you know about; on Infinite Ulysses, this meant users’ textual annotations, but also: the community they help build and constitute, and their reputation, scholarly or otherwise, in that community; any scholarship citing and/or depending on folks being able to look at or interact with your project as it currently appears.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2019 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2019/04/30/archiving-dh-data-policy</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2019/04/30/archiving-dh-data-policy</guid>
        
        <category>digital-humanities</category>
        
        <category>meta-dh</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>20% Time: Why we make self-initiated research &amp; development part of the job</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Crossposted at &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/&quot;&gt;the Scholars’ Lab blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All Scholars’ Lab staff are encouraged to take 20% of their time to initiate research and professional development. In this post, we’ll share some of what we’ve been working on, and explain the rationale behind making this 20% time a formal part of our job descriptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-20-time&quot;&gt;What is 20% time?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Previously also referred to as “personal R&amp;amp;D time”, we’ve recently shifted to saying &lt;strong&gt;“self-initiated R&amp;amp;D time”&lt;/strong&gt; to emphasize that this work is often collaborative, and always feeds back into the lab: what’s unique about 20% time is special leeway to experiment and fail, and formal support for staff to initiate and direct their own professional and scholarly development on the job. Making this a specific job expectation can help folks feel comfortable pursuing learning that isn’t immediately applicable to scholarship, but probably will be later on. For example, GIS Specialist Drew Macqueen’s “Arduino Chris” (GIF below, courtesy of Drew) used the problem of our office lights (which turn off when folks weren’t moving around much at their desks) to get some practice building electronics, which he can now apply to research consultations and collaborations as part of his spatial technologies toolkit:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/scholarslab/scholarslab.org/blob/master/assets/post-media/2019-01-22-Arduino-Chris.GIF?raw=true&quot; alt=&quot;GIF of Drew Macqueen's &amp;quot;Arduino Chris&amp;quot;, using electronics and a photo of GIS Specialist Chris Gist to turn the office lights back on when they go off from no one moving around.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Above: GIF of Drew Macqueen’s “Arduino Chris”, using electronics and a photo of GIS Specialist Chris Gist to turn the office lights back on when they go off from no one moving around.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that “R&amp;amp;D time” (aka 20% time, personal R&amp;amp;D time, self-initiated R&amp;amp;D time) is distinct from the work of our Research &amp;amp; Development (R&amp;amp;D) unit, which focuses on programming and design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-kinds-of-work-can-it-be-used-for&quot;&gt;What kinds of work can it be used for?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with our other staff work, we hold our use of 20% time to the following 3 commitments (also outlined in our &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/charter/&quot;&gt;team charter&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;At any moment, we should be able to &lt;strong&gt;relate our projects to the larger missions&lt;/strong&gt; of the Scholars’ Lab, the Library, and the University as a whole.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We should be able to &lt;strong&gt;articulate the interest and value&lt;/strong&gt; of our individual and collaborative work.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Our projects – including projects undertaken with UVa faculty and grads – are expected to &lt;strong&gt;enter public conversation&lt;/strong&gt; and to &lt;strong&gt;be shared as broadly as possible&lt;/strong&gt;. We have an expansive and evolving notion of valid “publication” events and public outcomes. We value open source code and open access information.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-is-self-initiated-rd-a-good-investment-in-our-staff&quot;&gt;How is self-initiated R&amp;amp;D a good investment in our staff?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of our greatest strengths is our team of experts, folks with deep scholarly and professional training and experience across the disciplines. Every one of us embodies what I think of as &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/about/#who-are-the-scholars-in-scholars-lab&quot;&gt;full scholarship&lt;/a&gt;—internationally recognized research, combined with a passion for teaching, community care, and social justice that’s necessary for research to function as scholarship. Our department, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.library.virginia.edu/&quot;&gt;UVA Library&lt;/a&gt;, makes an unusually (perhaps uniquely, within DH?) strong investment in digital and experiment scholarship through hard-money (i.e. not grant-dependent) funding of 12 full-time employees in the Scholars’ Lab, plus 1 part-time employee (a full-time UVA staffer, with part of their FTE bought out from the English Department by the Library), and 1 full-time grant-funded employee. Given that Centernet (the international organization of DH centers) defines DH centers with 5+ FTEs as “large”, we are rich indeed in this most important of scholarly resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Self-initiated R&amp;amp;D time helps us make the best use of that staff investment. Formally committing to allowing on-the-job professional development is diffrent than requiring staff to make special proposals to their supervisors if they want to write a paper, learn a skill, or try something that may or may not pan out. Our staff need to stay at the forefront of experimental and digital scholarship, if they’re to do their best in nurturing and collaborating on the campus community’s research in these areas. Often, that means work that may or may not prove to have a scholarly application at UVA (but we wouldn’t know unless we tried).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Former Scholars’ Lab Director Bethany Nowviskie notes, “For software developers, who can command larger salaries outside the academy, [20% time is] a much-valued perk. For alt-ac staff, who trained as scholars, it is almost a psychological necessity” (Nowviskie, 2012, &lt;a href=&quot;http://nowviskie.org/2012/too-small-to-fail/&quot;&gt;“Too Small to Fail”&lt;/a&gt;). 20% time lets us hire and retain folks with strong backgrounds in research and self-initiated experimentation. If we require these skills in a job ad, why wouldn’t we want to structure the role to help staff continue strengthening such work once on the job?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our current staff includes 2 UVA general faculty members, 1 UVA full professor, 3 staff with humanities Ph.D.s, 5 additional staff with Ph.D. A.B.D.s, and 3 staff with terminal M.L.S.s, in addition to professional training and certification in areas such as project management, and teaching as UVA instructors of record. Formal R&amp;amp;D time not only supports strong hiring and retention, it also helps our staff remain or become scholars themselves, so that they can bring that experience to their interactions with other faculty, staff, and student scholars on campus: “R&amp;amp;D time is the thing that ensures that the Scholars’ Lab… can become an interesting intellectual community in its own right, and be perceived as such by our colleagues on the teaching faculty” (Nowviskie). Note that this is important for all our staff, not just those holding degrees or hired with explicit research work in their job description; this “helps the SLab along in our ambition to function as a team of equals—a family, with shared, long-term commitments to our mission together” (Nowviskie).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-is-self-initiated-rd-good-for-not-only-the-lab-but-for-the-library-and-uva-as-well&quot;&gt;How is self-initiated R&amp;amp;D good for not only the Lab, but for the Library and UVA as well?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bethany Nowviskie wrote comprehensively and persuasively about the importance of 20% time, back in 2012 in &lt;a href=&quot;http://nowviskie.org/2012/too-small-to-fail/&quot;&gt;“Too Small to Fail”&lt;/a&gt;, particularly in the section titled “Scholar-Practitioners”. I strongly recommend you read her piece if you’re considering asking for R&amp;amp;D time, supporting colleagues in an R&amp;amp;D time pilot, or have doubts about 20% time being a good choice. In addition to narrating the UVA DH history that led to the formation of the Lab, and the Lab’s rationale for investing heavily in grad students, Bethany covers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A specific 20% time use that went on to impact many libraries: Project Blacklight (“solve[d] a serious problem for libraries dependent on expensive and inflexible vendor-provided catalog interfaces”)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How 20% time helps improve existing projects &amp;amp; create new ones (e.g. our NEH-funded tool for telling stories in space and time, &lt;a href=&quot;https://neatline.org&quot;&gt;Neatline&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Google’s popularization of 20% time in industry, where DH centers frequently lose technical staff&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Scholars’ Lab’s self-initiated R&amp;amp;D time has now been adopted at other DH centers and labs (e.g. Princeton) &amp;amp; is cited as a best practice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Helps us retain a healthy, sustainable working environment: “I’ve watched too many digital humanities centers and projects balloon and then seem to lose their direction, getting caught up in soft-money scrambles and taking on work that is less than ideal for them, just to keep good staff employed” (Nowviskie)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;As Bethany argues, it’s &lt;em&gt;just good&lt;/em&gt;. We work to treat our staff as the experts they are, give them some guidelines but trust them to lead on what/when/where their best work happens, invest in them as humans who love to learn. Not because it’s good for the institution’s missions (although it very much is!), but because we need to take responsibility for making our institutions and communities better at caring for and celebrating people.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our implementation of 20% time directly supports the strategic direction illustrated in UVA Library’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://static.lib.virginia.edu/directory/media/UL3rdCent.pdf&quot;&gt;“Library Entering Its Third Century”&lt;/a&gt; recommendations, particularly: “Deepen subject and methodological expertise across the Library by &lt;strong&gt;developing a culture of R&amp;amp;D&lt;/strong&gt; that strengthens our ability to contribute to the research, scholarly, and artistic enterprise of the University”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;show-me-some-projects&quot;&gt;Show me some projects!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In March 2018, we started what I hope can be an annual practice: getting the team together to eat pizza and share about the self-initiated R&amp;amp;D we’re working on. It was lovely; we easily used up two hours asking questions and making suggestions about future work. (12 of our staff were able to attend, so that’s roughly ten minutes per person.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the staff’s permission, I’m sharing what each of us was working on, to give you a picture of what 20% time can look like. (Please do note I may have lost nuances as a simultaneous note-taker and pizza-eater, and that these were only accurate as of March 2018—folks are working on different things now.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ammon Shepherd (DH Developer):&lt;/strong&gt; make art that’s tactilely responsive; thermal detonator watch with 12 LEDs to show the hour + access big data from somewhere&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Laura Miller (Head of Public Programs):&lt;/strong&gt; Scholars’ Lab alumni network (map, viz) illustrating where our students go on to, showing the impact the lab has on careers and the field; Zoe made a couple Jupyter notebook demos to think through how this might look&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Zoe LeBlanc (DH Developer):&lt;/strong&gt; for her app to store archival images, rewrote the logic and added auto-segmenting for paragraphs of text; work with computer vision scripts (OpenCV?), training dataset creation; was built in Django and AngularJS, she’s now rebuilding in React; statistics methodology by issue of magazines she’s studying; Cairo ’60s anti-colonial ideas change over time, so showing conceptual clustering changing over time; tagging images in her app (e.g. JFK images); interest in building her own OCR engine some day; Shane has possible data-testing set to use (cryptography journals)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Brandon Walsh (Head of Student Programs):&lt;/strong&gt; anxious pedagogies, thinking through how to expect + deal with frustration during classes, and how to apply this thinking with DH projects as well; text analysis cookbook from his frequently used code, with info on how/why cookbook snippets work; “how to learn text analysis” but with your own text&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Drew Macqueen (GIS Specialist):&lt;/strong&gt; keeping a Notepad++ code journal; created the Arduino Chris (GIF above) for keeping the SLab office lights on and practice physical computing skills; learning about georeferencing 3D models with Will and Arin; CityEngine; wants to write a blog post e.g. on modifiable areal unit problem, why zip codes are bad locators; wants to add thermal sensor to Arduino Chris so it works better&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jeremy Boggs (Head of R&amp;amp;D):&lt;/strong&gt; Thinking through distant reading of comic books, e.g. how Batman and the Joker in &lt;em&gt;The Killing Joke&lt;/em&gt; become visually similar, John Walsh’s TEI for Comic Books, (image recognition of?) comic book text to study gender; using Italo Calvino’s writing towards a bibliography of books with their qualities ID’d being used as a framework for text analysis; interest in doing D&amp;amp;D homebrew mashup with other content, e.g. Sarah and James’s characters from Samuel Johnson (http://genuineremains.jeremyboggs.net/)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shane Lin (Senior Developer):&lt;/strong&gt; working on his history dissertation, including writing some code, studying Usenet for how/when cryptography entered into widespread political consciousness, when crypto went from mostly a math discussion to mostly a political one; exploring Usenet metadata e.g. to see whether messages are from people new to the discussion or not; turned OpenScan 2D sketch into 3D model&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Arin Bennett (3D Visualization Specialist):&lt;/strong&gt; Working with Unity as part of his mentorship of the Praxis cohort; augmented reality (AR) mapping via the new Unity asset we purchased; working on a better AR interface for doing his trail running while using the headset, e.g. point of interest along his way, time countdown; AR walking tours; touching 3D print but seeing scan/photo version in headset&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Will Rourk (3D Data and Content Specialist):&lt;/strong&gt; Modular synthesizers; making 3D-printed chocolate molds from any 3D model; writing and researching what CHI (cultural heritage informatics) as a field &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; today e.g. CLIR talk and paper, bibliography creation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chris Gist (GIS Specialist):&lt;/strong&gt; learning new ARCGISonline tech, 3rd rebuild because the tech keeps changing and adding new products; tagging locations on a friend’s property; thinking about siloed research in regional cultural places and building a trail along the historic trail between them, creating new data layers to assist with pitch for new trail&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Amanda Visconti (Managing Director):&lt;/strong&gt; Helping draft possible ACH code of conduct for all platforms/outside of conferences; turned my Drupal dissertation website into a static archival site; article revisions for &lt;em&gt;Debates in DH&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;American Quarterly&lt;/em&gt;; approaching HTML/CSS/web browser functionality as something one can have expertise in, e.g. figuring out what JS stuff I can hack CSS to do; considering writing a textual forgery LARP; building a pneumatic tube message system for the lab; Shane helped me 3D print my actual brain from a brain MRI; learned to use FabLab laser cutters; working as a &lt;em&gt;Programming Historian&lt;/em&gt; editor&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alison Booth (Academic Director):&lt;/strong&gt; Collective Bibliographies of Women and proposing new NEH grant; creating Gothic Walking tour of Grounds with her class; thinking through a DH project extending understanding of the Anne Spencer House&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;challenges&quot;&gt;Challenges&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In practice, 20% time doesn’t happen exactly how we’d like. We’re busy staff, with many interests; because of our mentorship-not-service model, much of our daily work feels like, or is, what we’d personally choose to do R&amp;amp;D on (fulfilling the original goal of making sure folks in service roles could continue to grow as scholars). The desire to use one’s 20% time is something each of our supervisors fully support, so challenges in making this time are never because management won’t let staff make time for this work; I don’t think we’ve ever needed to veto a project idea for not fitting our 3 guidelines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Known issues with 20% time include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Making the time for it&lt;/em&gt;. Blocking out time on our calendars has helped some with this (especially starting 1 term away, when calendars are empty enough you can e.g. grab the same time every week), but I think it’s less a matter of making specific hours, and more emphasizing to ourselves that this self-initiated work is as important as our work that more immediately impacts our community. We often don’t practice the same commitment to our self-initiated R&amp;amp;D projects as we do for student and faculty collaborations. Some ideas for helping with this are a Slack channel to update colleagues on our progress and receive encouragement and help, and establishing writing/research partners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another barrier is needing help from SLab colleagues to move forward with your self-initiated work, but we feel reluctant to ask for that help: knowing how busy everyone is, or feeling uncomfortable using resources for a personally-initiated project. Or folks actually don’t have time during fall and spring terms to help, and internal collaborations needs to wait for the summer. As a small step forward over this barrier, I’ve been trying to recognize the importance of these self-initiated projects by helping schedule meetings where relevant SLab staff can work together to advance a project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Setting a formal amount of time for staff research shifts the conversation from whether a project can happen, to how to best make it happen. Our colleagues in other Library units don’t have 20% time in their job descriptions, although a number do have language about professional development. Many of our library colleagues are very active researchers. I do see an explicit percentage of job time is different from knowing you can propose a self-initiated project to your supervisor, but they may or may not understand its application, and they may or may not support your making time for it during your work day. 20% is equivalent to one day a week, 10% is one day every two weeks; this doesn’t need to happen daily or weekly, and some staff find it best for them and their community to bank this time during fall and spring and use it during winter and summers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Library supports each of its staff with at least $1k of professional development travel funding each year (and extra for the first 2 years on the job); UVA also provides university staff annual funds to take courses and attend conferences. The Library and UVA professional development funds can’t be used for books or equipment, which can be difficult for folks seeking to self-teach or to learn a hands-on skill like electronics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’d like to both better communicate our work to our colleagues and the public, and also back up our colleagues (here and beyond UVA) when they’re articulating why they’d like to self-initiate research as a small but formal part of their jobs. In the last year, we’ve made steps toward these goals including getting pizza and sharing our R&amp;amp;D work and frustrations among SLab staff; scheduling annual summer brownbags just for library colleagues, where we’ll update folks about each of our staffers’ work and discuss potential collaborations throughout the Library; and re-committing to publishing on any conference travel funded by SLab (either a blog post within 6 weeks of the event, or an internal brownbag updating Library colleagues, as a condition of future travel funding).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve also heard some questioning around staff using 20% time to work on dissertations, worded as “paying people to finish their dissertations”. That 20% time helps us hire such scholars and best serve the campus community is discussed above, but I’ll add that as long as dissertational work fits our 3 guidelines (ensuring work benefits the university, is made public), it’s actually particularly suited to 20% time: it’s likely got a clear timeline, mentor, and obvious application to that staffer’s professional growth. I agree with Jeremy Boggs’ argument that whether 20% time is used for work that is part of a dissertation is irrelevant; instead, we should be looking at whether it’s meeting those 3 guidelines, and think of it in terms of what work is being done. For example, Senior Developer and History ABD Shane Lin has used some of his 20% time to learn to scrape Usenet metadata to understand historical community development, sharpening skills around web scraping, text analysis, community research, and historical scholarship critical to his role in the lab (and incidentally, moving his dissertation forward as well).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-do-you-think&quot;&gt;What do you think?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have suggestions for improving our 20% time in policy or practice or questions, let us know! We’re also interested in your own experiences pursuing research and professional development, regardless of your job role; and what, if any, policy about research and professional development your institution offers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Special thanks to Bethany Nowviskie, whose arguments for 20% time still benefit many folks today, and whose excellent 2012 rationale for 20% time, &lt;a href=&quot;http://nowviskie.org/2012/too-small-to-fail/&quot;&gt;“Too Small to Fail”&lt;/a&gt;, is quoted liberally in this post!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2019 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2019/04/26/dh-center-staff-professional-research-and-development-time/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2019/04/26/dh-center-staff-professional-research-and-development-time/</guid>
        
        <category>digital-humanities</category>
        
        <category>meta-dh</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>ScholarsLab.org website relaunch!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally posted on the Scholars’ Lab blog on &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/site-relaunch/&quot;&gt;January 15, 2019&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re happy to announce that our Lab website has a new look and feel, all aimed at making Scholars’ Lab more accessible and the site more useful. The website &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org&quot;&gt;ScholarsLab.org&lt;/a&gt; represents the collective effort of our &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/people&quot;&gt;staff and collaborators&lt;/a&gt;, past and present. It’s existed in multiple forms: most recently, as a WordPress site and now, as of this blog post, as a Jekyll-generated static website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;why-renew-the-website&quot;&gt;Why renew the website?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our previous website was headed by the homepage text “collaborate, &lt;strong&gt;iterate&lt;/strong&gt;, discuss”:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/assets/post-media/2018-11-05-iterate.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of text saying &amp;quot;collaborate, iterate, discuss&amp;quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re a community lab focused on experimental scholarship. We care most about the impact of scholarship on &lt;em&gt;people&lt;/em&gt;, ranking positive human experience as the most important outcome of projects or other work. This means that failure and a journey of many iterations are not just frequent by-products of our work, but essential characteristics. For example, we periodically renew our &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/charter&quot;&gt;lab charter&lt;/a&gt; to reflect our ongoing growth as scholars and professionals; as it was last updated in 2016, we’ll be renewing its text (and even, perhaps, its form) over the coming year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before renewing our charter, though, we worked on synthesizing our many views of what the lab currently is into a coherent, concise mission–visible at the top of our new homepage. Having the website look “newer” wasn’t a priority for us; rather, we used this re-articulated mission to reimagine a site more aligned with our values…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;why-does-the-site-look-this-way&quot;&gt;Why does the site look this way?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We started thinking about a site renewal back in Summer 2017, with two rough goals: a general rethinking of the site to fit our current work, and a migration of platforms from WordPress to a Jekyll-generated static website. (You can see this &lt;a href=&quot;https://programminghistorian.org/en/lessons/building-static-sites-with-jekyll-github-pages&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; for more on what a jekyll-generated static site is, why you might want to use one, and how.) WordPress is a popular blogging platform with the advantage of a user-friendly administrative dashboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the benefits of WYSIWYG (what you see is what you get) blog post editors and easy media uploads come with significant costs of web developer time updating the site’s core, plugin, and theme code and keeping the site secure. Moving to a Jekyll-generated static site helped us think through applying &lt;a href=&quot;https://go-dh.github.io/mincomp/about/&quot;&gt;minimal computing values&lt;/a&gt; to our main online platform. This move means making small content changes to the website (e.g. writing a new blog post) a little harder by requiring some steps we didn’t require before, but… we think these steps:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;are within the grasp of anyone (regardless of technical experience),&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ultimately enfranchise everyone to understand more and do more with our site than WordPress allowed, and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;are in line with our teaching each of our Praxis cohorts the basic steps required to use git, GitHub, and markdown (i.e. by teaching these skills to our team and affiliates more broadly, we hope to also enfranchise folks to create their own websites with the same technologies).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After much discussion and work, these initial goals yielded a more important goal: reimagining our website to more clearly focus on making the lab accessible to folks who wouldn’t otherwise already know about or feel welcome to join us. We already have some friendly and well-trodden paths to reaching the lab, such as through our work and fellowship CFPs, consultations, events, and open office hours; so we decided to aim the website at reaching folks who weren’t already coming into our space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/about&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/assets/post-media/2018-11-21-FAQlist.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of frequently asked Scholars' Lab questions&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some ways we approached this goal:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Encouraging site visitors to feel they’re in the right place&lt;/strong&gt;, by updating textual content and photos to be more explicitly welcoming. For example, we reorganized our &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/makerspace&quot;&gt;Makerspace&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/spatial-technologies&quot;&gt;Spatial Tech&lt;/a&gt; equipment and software inventories into named categories; you might not know what a serger is, but where you’d probably just skim past the word before, you can now see that it’s part of a set of equipment and supplies aimed at making things with fabric. The hope is that by grouping resources like the serger into clearer categories, you might realize that our Makerspace has some resources and folks you can talk to about, for example, your interests in making stuff from textiles, historical costuming, and/or other fabric art approaches.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Making the &lt;strong&gt;info folks need to get more involved easy to find&lt;/strong&gt;, once they feel comfortable with our resources being theirs. We wrote a &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/about&quot;&gt;FAQ&lt;/a&gt; anticipating questions folks often ask us, overhauled the structure of information on our site (e.g. menu order and wording, page titles, layout and order of information on a given page). We also created clear maps showing how to get to the specific locations within our somewhat large space (the west wing of the 4th floor of Alderman Library).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Accurately capturing the &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/work&quot;&gt;work&lt;/a&gt; of all our current staff, including recent hires and folks welcomed into the lab during the library reorganization (who hadn’t had their work represented on the old site), to &lt;strong&gt;show the true breadth of disciplines and approaches we cover&lt;/strong&gt;. We also reworked the metadata on each of our current and past Scholars’ Lab folks, so that we could more easily and accurately show what roles folks have held and who has contributed anything to a given project—again, more accurately showing how the Scholars’ Lab is itself a digital scholarship project, one built together by many people over the years.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;More clearly showing that &lt;strong&gt;we’re part of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://library.virginia.edu&quot;&gt;UVA Library&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, so folks understand that we’re part of the Library’s mission to provide equitable access to knowledge and learning to everyone. This work includes an FAQ question, a section of the homepage with text and the UVA Library logo, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/library&quot;&gt;a new SLab “Library” page&lt;/a&gt; highlighting the work of Library colleagues that helps us do what we do, and that may feature stories about intralibrary collaborations in the future.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;who-made-this&quot;&gt;Who made this?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 2017-2018 renewal of this website incorporates text, suggestions, and feedback from everyone on &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/people&quot;&gt;the Scholars’ Lab staff&lt;/a&gt;. Additionally, the following folks put in significant extra effort on the site’s design, coding, content, project management, and documentation: Katherine Donnally, Jeremy Boggs, Brandon Walsh, Ronda Grizzle, Laura Miller, Zoe LeBlanc, Ammon Shepherd, Shane Lin, Beth Mitchell, and Amanda Visconti.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to especially highlight the leadership and labor of &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/people/katherine-donnally/&quot;&gt;Katherine Donnally&lt;/a&gt; (Scholars’ Lab DH Designer 2017-2018) in realizing this site. Katherine’s thinking and work gave the renewal project a coherent focus around making the lab more accessible and supportive of folks who might not otherwise feel part of our community; in addition to design and development work, she created structures and documentation (e.g. goal and progress tracker, code commenting, analysis of the old website, articulation of the purpose of the new site) that were instrumental in both imagining the new site and seeing it to the finish line.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 15 Apr 2019 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2019/04/15/scholarslab-website-relaunch/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2019/04/15/scholarslab-website-relaunch/</guid>
        
        <category>digital-humanities</category>
        
        <category>meta-dh</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A Moderate Proposal: Healthier Systems for Running Online Digital Humanities Communities</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally posted on the Scholars’ Lab blog on &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/moderation-running-dh-online-communities/&quot;&gt;February 27, 2019&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Healthy, diverse online learning communities depend on the labor of community design: unseen and often stressful work such as moderation, shaping discussions, and encouraging positive community behavior. As more opportunities emerge for learning online as part of a virtual community, how can we:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;recognize (credit, publicize, reward, treat as scholarly work) and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reinforce (design, automate, fairly distribute the labor, deal with mental health impacts)&lt;br /&gt;
the labor of community design? As marginalized identities are most at risk for harm when interacting with others online, support for moderation is support for community inclusion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I write from my experiences moderating both my digital dissertation project Infinite Ulysses (a social platform for annotating/commenting on James Joyce’s novel) and the Digital Humanities Slack I started (a set of themed chat rooms with over 2,000 digital humanist members; co-moderated by Alan G. Pike, Sam Abrams, Alex Gil, Brandon Walsh, Ed Summers, Paige C. Morgan, Jeremy Boggs, Eleanor Dickson, Liz Rodrigues, and Erin Pappas). It’s been exhilarating using technology to collaborate with folks I don’t know: if you’ve taught DH, think of the students who respond to your lessons like “DH is exactly what I want to do, I just didn’t have a term for it before”, but expand to include folks from all over the world and more diverse walks of life. But it’s also been a significant source of anxiety, balancing my responsibility to the community with my desire to help folks learn to be more positive influences on that community. That stress was half of why I moved Infinite Ulysses from a Drupal site allowing commenting, to a static archived version without commenting (the other half was some serious thinking about how I could best contribute to the DH I want to see, and realizing that just for me personally, I need to move away from Joyce and Modernist studies to best accomplish that).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do want to note that the challenges of moderating online DH and other academic/professional communities are, at least for me, privileged through my ability to choose my level of work (or opt out completely) without hurting my livelihood or family; compared with the pain, lack of compensation, lack of respect, and more evils experienced by folks like those who moderate YoutTube and Facebook, working with smaller communities that have some norms (though inequitable) and professional consequences (though often used as a weapon against rather than a protector of folks with marginalized identities) are less pressing problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-im-blogging-today&quot;&gt;Why I’m blogging today&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post is largely drawn from a non-successful IMLS pre-proposal I PI’d (Spring 2018) for an NLG planning grant to explore, identify key challenges, and plan pilot community experimental approaches to aid the foundational labor of moderators underpinning online learning communities, titled “&lt;strong&gt;A Moderate Proposal&lt;/strong&gt;: Recognizing and Reinforcing Online Community Moderation to Benefit Diverse Learners” and co-designed with colleagues Jeremy Boggs, Katherine Donnally, Shane Lin, Laura Miller, and Brandon Walsh. (If you like the title pun, you may also appreciate that our proposal drafting GDoc was titled “DigitalHumanities.club”, after the domain that I own because it’s awesome, but that I was also using to explore Mastodon and Mattermost for better communities.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I finally got around to this post due to cool stuff two DHers are up to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/scott_bot/status/1100387484930854913&quot;&gt;Scott Weingart’s Twitter thread&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theverge.com/2019/2/25/18229714/cognizant-facebook-content-moderator-interviews-trauma-working-conditions-arizona&quot;&gt;Casey Newton’s recent article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve only skimmed Newton’s piece, but I’ve read and admired Sarah T. Robert’s more longstanding work in this area:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a &lt;em&gt;Maclean’s&lt;/em&gt; article in Summer 2018, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.macleans.ca/opinion/meet-the-people-who-scar-themselves-to-clean-up-our-social-media-networks/&quot;&gt;“Meet the people who scar themselves to clean up our social media networks”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;an article in &lt;em&gt;The Atlantic&lt;/em&gt; in Spring 2017, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2017/03/commercial-content-moderation/518796/&quot;&gt;“Social Media’s Silent Filter”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And now &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ubiquity75/status/1045552839819505664&quot;&gt;a book!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.org/people/ammon-shepherd/&quot;&gt;SLab colleague Ammon Shepherd&lt;/a&gt; has kicked off a series of blog posts around the challenges of archiving DH work, with what promises to be a special focus on the technical and especially sysadmin work unlerying these challenges. You can read &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.org/blog/archiving-dh-part-one/&quot;&gt;the first post in the series&lt;/a&gt; now, but Ammon’s also orchestrating a really cool system of inviting UVA Library colleagues to co-write the rest of the series with him, complete with clear documentation on how to take part and make the discussion better.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Scott and Ammon for being awesome scholars doing work collaboratively and in public!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-moderate-proposal&quot;&gt;A moderate proposal&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Community design requires &lt;strong&gt;moderation&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;scaffolding&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;Moderation&lt;/strong&gt; is both the work of controlling spam and intentional harassment in a community, as well as designing and implementing a code of conduct (e.g. working behind the scenes with a community member whose words impact others negatively, but who wants to become a better community member). &lt;strong&gt;Scaffolding&lt;/strong&gt; is the work of maintaining and nurturing a community: suggesting conversation topics, encouraging community member involvement, amplifying marginalized voices, and otherwise enacting strategies to grow a healthy and active community. Creating the technical platform for an online community is relatively simple, given existing open-source versions of popular social media platforms. Rather, the challenge to improving moderation is a social project: habituating community members to behavior that reduces harassment, encourages real accountability to others in your community, distributes the stress of moderating, and recognizes/credits/rewards people who moderate and otherwise advance positive community design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve focused on Twitter, Slack, and Mastodon as text-heavy platforms with public and frequent use by digital humanists, plus Civil Comments and the Mozilla Coral Project as technical solutions to online community challenges. I’m also interested in these past or current DHy communities and the scholars shaping them: DH Q&amp;amp;A, Humanities Commons, DHthis, DH Commons, the DLF Forum, DH Slack, HASTAC, DHNow, the AADHUM Slack, and the Documenting the Now Slack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve since updated our thinking and planning, but when I submitted our grant preproposal a year ago, we imagined the following activites and outcomes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;activities&quot;&gt;Activities&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project team would identify and invite 10 experts in online learning community-building, with diverse representation of gender, race, and other identities, from libraries, archives, museums, and academia. Our initial work draws on a symposium with these advisors to spark collaborations, identify key challenges, and plan out steps for piloting and assessing improvements to social systems of moderation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Project team reviews literature and existing communities:&lt;/em&gt; Distribute Twitter and DH Slack surveys to gather anecdotes about good and bad online academic communities and their moderation systems. Use team’s existing text analysis skills to explore frequent vocabulary and sentiment in the discussions on a sample community, the Digital Humanities Slack (2k+ community members), if* DH Slack community decides this is an acceptable analysis (read more about the community’s decision to keep the Slack ephemeral via a non-paid Slack plan &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2016/07/06/digital-humanities-slack-community-design&quot;&gt;in this post&lt;/a&gt;). Create an annotated bibliography plus pre-symposium reading list. Assign each advisory board member to read 3 articles and report useful takeaway ideas from these at the symposium.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;2-day symposium of 10 advisory board members with Scholars’ Lab staff and UVA Library colleagues:&lt;/em&gt; Project team presents results of the DH Slack message text analysis* as a grounding case study. Advisory board gives lightning talks summarizing their assigned readings. Goals set for the rest of the symposium. Facilitated design jam sessions, paper prototyping, breakout groups addressing specific challenges, such as&lt;br /&gt;
1: amplifying credit for moderators, making their labor institutionally legible for promotion, addressing gendering of work;&lt;br /&gt;
2: templates for difficult moderation conversations with community members, tech features that could support social needs such as shadow-banning, moderator self-care.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;After symposium:&lt;/em&gt; Project team prepares report of best practices to support online learning community moderation, shares with advisory board for feedback, disseminates to public. Team outlines next steps, shares with advisory board for feedback. Probable steps include identifying both technical and social solutions to pilot, formally approaching communities to collaborate on testing practices (e.g. MLA/Humanities Commons, ACH, DLF), scheduling pilots and assessment, prototyping and testing ideas, and reporting back to public. We take the NEH “Off the Tracks” workshop resulting in &lt;a href=&quot;https://mith.umd.edu/offthetracks/recommendations&quot;&gt;recommendations for ethically crediting collaborators&lt;/a&gt; as a model for all of this work, and commit to thoroughly and accurately crediting all participants in these projects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;outcomes&quot;&gt;Outcomes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will identify project staffers with expertise in ethical design practices, and charge them with holding our focus on improving online communities for marginalized identities, while also documenting and publishing the conversations and findings occurring through the planning phase to ensure others can build on our work. During this grant’s planning phase we will create:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An annotated bibliography and reading list&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A symposium whitepaper covering the ideas, best practice suggestions, and conversations a diverse advisory board of experts generate during the symposium&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A public conversation around crediting moderation labor and improving community moderation, connecting scholars interested in this work&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A written plan outlining next steps for pilot projects designing, building, and assessing various technical and social features for their impact on online community moderation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Experimental approaches may include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Strategies to protect users from one another, unwanted surveillance, or commercial interests&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Documented design-driven approaches to building more ethical academic social media platforms&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A code of conduct template in support of community design labor&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Model a technical platform for online learning communities that is designed from the start with an ethic of care, with particular focus on making the system useful to those identities usually marginalized by commercial social media platforms&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Text analysis results discussion from analysis of DH Slack community vocabulary and sentiment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interested-know-things&quot;&gt;Interested? Know things?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If anything in this post interests you (future collaboration?), overlaps with your current work, or could benefit from my reading and citing you or others, please let me know at visconti@virginia.edu. Thank you!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks to colleagues Jeremy Boggs, Katherine Donnally, Shane Lin, Laura Miller, and Brandon Walsh for co-designing of the grant proposal, and to Ammon Shepherd for helping me think about the technical sustainability aspects of better online moderation experiences.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 15 Apr 2019 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2019/04/15/moderation-running-dh-online-communities/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2019/04/15/moderation-running-dh-online-communities/</guid>
        
        <category>digital-humanities</category>
        
        <category>meta-dh</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>DH Dissertation to Director: Notes connecting my student and staff experiences</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally posted on the Scholars’ Lab blog on &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/dh-dissertation-to-director/&quot;&gt;February 21, 2019&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A colleague recently asked me about how I draw on my DH dissertation experience (&lt;a href=&quot;https://dr.amandavisconti.com&quot;&gt;dr.amandavisconti.com&lt;/a&gt;) in my work co-directing the Scholars’ Lab. Below, I share the rough notes I typed up in response about the first couple such dissertation-director connections that came to mind:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;digital-humanities--experimental-humanities&quot;&gt;Digital humanities &amp;lt; experimental humanities&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting to do an &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/tag/dissertation/&quot;&gt;unusually shaped dissertation&lt;/a&gt; meant doing a lot of meta-dissertational work analyzing and synthesizing precedents for making as scholarship, dissertations that didn’t produce written chapters, and experimental scholarly methods and formats more generally. I not only needed to prove that such work could reach the goals of a dissertation, but that my research design choices also fit tmy particular research questions. It was profoundly useful to work through what I thought was the best research design for my questions, and then also find the language to convince others of this as well. I do not want to add more barriers to the dissertation process for anyone, but it does seem mildly unfortunate to me that most humanities dissertation creators aren’t encouraged and supported to explore multiple research aproaches and argue for why their project format is the best fit for their research questions, rather than treating written chapters as the only choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Scholars’ Lab has historical prominence as a DH center, but we also offer strong expertise in other areas, such as GIS/spatial reasoning and cultural heritage informatics. Some of my work as a Lab director has been collaborating with my colleagues to update our understanding of what’s most important to us, articulate that in a concise and memorable way, and relaunching our Lab website (ScholarsLab.org) to better communicate that updated mission. I think my dissertation experience helped me do a better job of hearing and synthesizing our staff’s visions for the Lab: rather than forcing everything to fit under the rubric of DH, we’ve identified a shared lab commitment to questioning assumptions around the methods and publication formats of scholarship, to cultivating a readiness to experiment and create new approaches where existing ones don’t best fit our research questions. It’s the &lt;em&gt;experimental&lt;/em&gt; mindset of DH that drives us and connects our team members’ many skillsets—as you can see in partially or wholly analog work like our Makerspace and campus community design work—rather than something particular to the Digital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;passing-it-on&quot;&gt;Passing it on&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been extremely lucky, from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://mith.umd.edu&quot;&gt;MITH&lt;/a&gt; and UMD English Department smart and caring mentorship that allowed me to realize my unusual dissertation, to getting to work at the Scholars’ Lab, where the amazing staff have long, successfully made it their mission to model and nurture a generous and human-centered digital humanities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My dissertation experience was an extremely lucky one: I had incredible mentors as my dissertation committee (Matt Kirschenbaum as advisor; Kari Kraus, Neil Fraistat, Melanie Kill, Brian Richardson). They met with me throughout the dissertation process to give me feedback and help us make sure that, for a very non-traditionally shaped dissertation, we were all on the same page as to expectations for the final outcome. They all had this unusual combination of innovative scholarship mixed with humanity and generosity. I’ve heard people say that either your advisor is nice to you but doesn’t push your work forward, or they’re mean (how is this not just a thing, but a fairly common one?) but make your work better. Every interaction I had with my committee was a kind one, and yet they &lt;em&gt;constantly&lt;/em&gt; challenged me to do better, with their full faith, and both the support and space necessary to figuring out what scholarship is to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having mentors modeling this approach to scholarship made me determined to pass on the impact of their gift to other folks I encounter, as best I can. To work so that the luck and privilege that allowed me to do my dissertation might become standard resources for anyone. To put my heart into Scholars’ Lab’s goal of training the next generation of scholars to be the scholarly community we want to exist, and to take responsibility for my tiny snowflake in the storm of what DH is (e.g. think through the impact of my doing my &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2014/05/27/inclusivityeditioncanon&quot;&gt;dissertation around a canon work&lt;/a&gt; by a white, male, Anglo, cis author; and change my scholarly trajectory to respond to the problems that investigation raised for me—please note that I no longer agree with that blog post, but haven’t yet written up how my thinking has evolved since then…).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;scholarship-is-people&quot;&gt;Scholarship is people&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read Mark Sample’s excellent &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.samplereality.com/2013/02/08/when-does-service-become-scholarship/&quot;&gt;“When does service become scholarship?”&lt;/a&gt; while dissertating, and I’ve paraphrased his argument into my preferred definition of “scholarship”:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;one part critical thinking + one part communicating the results of that thinking&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Critical thinking&lt;/em&gt; can be accomplished through many methods, including research, writing, coding, building, designing, experimenting, and play. &lt;em&gt;Communicating critical thinking&lt;/em&gt; can take the form of traditional publishing or other forms of “making public” such as tweeting and blogging, teaching, sharing open source code, or any other way for your intellectual community to learn from, critique, evaluate, and/or build on your work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Decompressing this definition:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Anyone trying to think well and share their work is part of the scholarly conversation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Making research just half of scholarship rather than synonymous brings the scholarly community into focus as the goal of our research work—with the implicit belief that the work of care, respect, mentoring, amplifying of your community members is not just a “nice” characteristic taking second place to the completely broken concepts of “rigor” or “brilliance”, not just “eulogy worthy”, but definitionally a necessary part of being a scholar&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I don’t have time for a definition of scholarship that doesn’t recognize the brilliant contributions of project managers, teachers, students, librarians, fanfic writers, book club members, more folks than I can list: all as much a part of building intellectual communities’ knowledge and abilities as academic faculty.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A scholarship that fits with the Scholars’ Lab’s unofficial moto of “people over projects”: focusing on community knowledge and health as the goal, and research as the means, rather than the other way around.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;documentation-of-scholarships-process-is-scholarship&quot;&gt;Documentation of scholarship’s process is scholarship&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent around six months of my dissertation building something on an Islandora-based framework, and then ended up not using those months of my server and code work in the final digital edition I produced. But because I documented throughout why I was making certain technical and design choices, how the technical work developed my critical thinking, I had that research to share with my intellectual community, and I wasn’t six months behind on my dissertation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my work today, I encourage others to share their notes, design choices, and other documentation as they go; it’s better for the community, and I think it’s also better for scholars new to a method to know they can start giving back to the community right away (e.g. What do you know now that you didn’t understand a week ago? Write for that person).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 15 Apr 2019 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2019/04/15/dh-dissertation-to-director/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2019/04/15/dh-dissertation-to-director/</guid>
        
        <category>digital-humanities</category>
        
        <category>meta-dh</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Automating Webpage &amp; Tweet Screencaptures</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally posted on the Scholars’ Lab blog on &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/automating-webpage-tweet-screencaptures/&quot;&gt;January 30, 2019&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you have a list of webpage URLs for which you’d like screencaps (aka screenshots)?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(&lt;em&gt;Know this tutorial fits your needs? &lt;a href=&quot;#how-to-automate-screencapping&quot;&gt;Jump to the instructions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe you study social media: you can capture all the data about a tweet using &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.docnow.io/&quot;&gt;Documenting the Now’s tools&lt;/a&gt; and get a spreadsheet listing all of a hashtag’s tweets with text, file names for any image attachments, publication date, RT/like counts…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But maybe you’d also like to have screencaps of the webpage per each tweet as they appeared at a given time:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;keep an offline folder of all your faved tweets? (before time passes and some of them are deleted)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;record how tweets &lt;em&gt;looked&lt;/em&gt; on Twitter.com at a given point in time, e.g. the avatars of folks who interacted with the tweet (using the avatar images current—at least as of the time of screencap—since people change these over time), or what metadata was viewable to the casual observer at a given time, as with this example tweet screencap:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://scholarslab.org/assets/post-media/2019-01-31-tweetscreenshot1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having screencaps of tweets can be useful for Twitter receipts, conducting a user study where you want to gauge folk’s reactions to seeing a tweet as it looked on Twitter.com (without needing to be online), or keep a folder of motivating tweets to refer to when you need encouragement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post will help you also automate taking screencaps from a list of URLs, by pointing you two tutorials plus some advice on combining these. This tutorial is written from a Mac user’s perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;my-uses-cases&quot;&gt;My uses cases&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently had two needs for a workflow automating screencaps:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Screencapping faved tweets (aka motivation)&lt;/strong&gt;: I used to “like” tweets where folks said useful things about my work, for later encouragement when I needed it. I wanted to switch to just screencapping these tweets as I saw them, saving the “like” function to indicate interest in others’ tweets, but that meant I need a way to get all those previous likes as screencaps. This workflow gave me a folder of over 2k screencapped tweets! (Now I just need to make a bot to show me a random one each time I log in…)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figuring out how many of our posts were amplified by a DH aggregator&lt;/strong&gt;: For an external review of DH at UVA, we’re drafting a report on Scholars’ Lab as a DH unit. As a small part of this, I wanted to include the number of times SLab staff or students have had a blog post highlighted by &lt;a href=&quot;http://digitalhumanitiesnow.org/&quot;&gt;Digital Humanities Now&lt;/a&gt;. Searching the &lt;em&gt;DH Now&lt;/em&gt; with a variety of search terms (e.g. Praxis, Neatline, variants of “Scholars’ Lab”, names of former staff) turned up a bunch of posts, but without opening each result in a browser to skim that post, I couldn’t be sure that these were all actually either SLab-authored or citing SLab work (vs. e.g. happening to use the word “praxis”). By automating screencaps of all the links my search turned up, instead of opening each link in a browser, I could use Preview to bulk-open screencaps and glance over the top of each webpage, seeing more quickly whether a post was related to SLab or not.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;credits&quot;&gt;Credits&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an extremely light repackaging of two sets of advice, for which I am grateful:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ryan Bauman’s (&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ryanfb&quot;&gt;twitter.com/ryanfb&lt;/a&gt;) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ryanfb/status/1014302804796731393&quot;&gt;tweets on how to get a list of URLs for your faved tweets&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Joshua Johnson’s 2011 post &lt;a href=&quot;https://mac.appstorm.net/general/applescript-automatically-create-screenshots-from-a-list-of-websites/&quot;&gt;“AppleScript: Automatically Create Screenshots from a List of Websites”&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may also wish to explore &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.docnow.io/&quot;&gt;Documenting the Now&lt;/a&gt;’s tools for ethical preservation and research with social media, including the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.docnow.io/catalog/&quot;&gt;Tweet Catalogue&lt;/a&gt; to locate datasets of tweets using a given hashtag, and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/DocNow/hydrator&quot;&gt;Hydrator&lt;/a&gt; tool for turning those datasets back into a list of tweets and their metadata.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;how-to-automate-screencapping&quot;&gt;How to automate screencapping&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;1.&lt;/span&gt; You’ll need a text document (plain text / .txt) with each URL you want to be screencapped listed on a separate line:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://scholarslab.org/assets/post-media/2019-01-31-tweet-screenhot-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to create a list of just your faved tweets, see &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ryanfb/status/1014302804796731393&quot;&gt;this tweet by Ryan Bauman tweet&lt;/a&gt; to get just the liked tweets from your Twitter &amp;gt; Settings &amp;gt; “Your Twitter Data” download.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have a bunch of bookmarked URLs you want to screenshot (possibly in one bookmarks subfolder?), you can export your whole set of bookmarks from the browser, then edit the resulting HTML file (using search+replace or regular expressions; sorry, that’s a whole separate lengthy tutorial, but &lt;a href=&quot;https://programminghistorian.org/en/lessons/understanding-regular-expressions&quot;&gt;Doug Knox’s tutorial here&lt;/a&gt;’s a good place to get started understanding regular expressions) to strip it to just a list of the URLs you want to screencap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;2.&lt;/span&gt; Next, we’ll use Joshua Johnson’s 2011 post &lt;a href=&quot;https://mac.appstorm.net/general/applescript-automatically-create-screenshots-from-a-list-of-websites/&quot;&gt;“AppleScript: Automatically Create Screenshots from a List of Websites”&lt;/a&gt; to actually take the screencaps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re going to use the Mac “Script Editor” tool to tell our computer to take that list of URLs, open each in Safari, take a screencap of that screen, and save it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open the Script Editor app (Applications &amp;gt; Utilities &amp;gt; Script Editor).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;3.&lt;/span&gt; Grab the text from &lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/amandavisconti/ffc05d293b9fed70a7378421f7c818f0&quot;&gt;this page&lt;/a&gt;, which puts Joshua Johnson’s script in an easy-to-find place (to understand what the script does, read &lt;a href=&quot;https://mac.appstorm.net/general/applescript-automatically-create-screenshots-from-a-list-of-websites/&quot;&gt;his post&lt;/a&gt; where he walks you through adding and adjusting the different pieces). Paste the text into the top text field:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://scholarslab.org/assets/post-media/2019-01-31-tweet-screenshot-3.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have a slow internet connection or want to screencap pages on websites that load slowly, you may wish to find and adjust the piece of the script that says “delay 5”, to a larger number than 5 (this controls the time the script waits between directing safari to visit a given URL, and taking a screencap of whatever is then currently on the Safari screen).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;4.&lt;/span&gt; Open the Applications &amp;gt; Safari browser, and drag its screen to be as large as possible. Depending on what level of zoomed-in/zoomed-out you usually use the Safari browser at, you may wish to adjust for the purpose of taking the screencaps; the screencaps will only capture what’s showing in the window you’ve opened (not stuff you’d need to scroll down to see).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;5.&lt;/span&gt; Open the Applications &amp;gt; TextEdit app (not a different text editor, unless you want to figure out how to edit the script’s &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;tell application &quot;TextEdit&quot;&lt;/code&gt; how to point to a different application). Paste in your list of URLs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have other TextEdit windows/tabs, make sure that the one with the URL list is the topmost/frontmost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;6.&lt;/span&gt; You’re ready to take screencaps! You’ll want to do this when you’re okay not having access to your computer for a while, because the screenshots will be of whatever is at the front of your screen. If you step away from your computer, the script knows to leave a Safari browser window open at the front of your screen, take a screencap, then move to the next webpage in your list and screencap that. If you hide the Safari window or have other stuff open over it, you won’t get the screencaps you want. (I’m sure there’s a way to make this not the case, but I didn’t need to figure that out for my use cases.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back on the Script Editor, press the “red dot” record icon to begin automatically taking a screencap of each of the URLs in your list:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://scholarslab.org/assets/post-media/2019-01-31-tweet-screenshot-3.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the script finishes running, you’ll have screencaps of all the URLs!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 15 Apr 2019 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2019/04/15/automating-webpage-tweet-screencaptures/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2019/04/15/automating-webpage-tweet-screencaptures/</guid>
        
        <category>digital-humanities</category>
        
        <category>advice-tutorial</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>DH archiving on the Scholars' Lab Blog</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally posted on the Scholars’ Lab blog on &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/archiving-dh-part-2-the-problem-in-detail/&quot;&gt;March 11, 2019&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/archiving-dh-part-2-the-problem-in-detail/&quot;&gt;Scholars’ Lab blog&lt;/a&gt;, Ammon Shepherd has been leading a series of collaborative blog posts about the challenges of archiving or preserving digital humanities projects. The first post in the series, by Ammon, is &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/archiving-dh-part-one/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Ammon and UVA Library colleagues Lauren Work and Brandon Butler, I co-authored a piece of the second post in the series, which goes into the challenges of archiving DH projects in more detail. I recommend you read that whole post &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/archiving-dh-part-2-the-problem-in-detail/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, but I’ve also copied my piece (on the issues resulting from the humans that underlie all technology) below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The human labor underlying technology is not easily sustainable; even when you have folks committed to the work, the kind and amount of labor required to maintain and update a project can shift away from what someone is willing or able to support, and external pressures (job changes, family, other projects, aging, retirement) also arise. I (Amanda, hi!) am particularly interested in how technical sustainability is impacted by the human labor of moderating online spaces, from my experiences moderating both my digital dissertation project &lt;a href=&quot;https://infiniteulysses.com&quot;&gt;Infinite Ulysses&lt;/a&gt; (a social platform for annotating/commenting on James Joyce’s novel) and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://tinyurl.com/DHSlack&quot;&gt;Digital Humanities Slack&lt;/a&gt; I started (a set of themed chat rooms with over 2,000 digital humanist members; co-moderated by Alan G. Pike, Sam Abrams, Alex Gil, Brandon Walsh, Ed Summers, Paige C. Morgan, Jeremy Boggs, Eleanor Dickson, Liz Rodrigues, and Erin Pappas).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moderation is both the work of controlling spam and intentional harassment in a community, as well as designing and implementing practices such as a code of conduct to both address the negative and encourage positive community behaviors. It’s been exhilarating using technology to collaborate with folks I don’t know and create online communities together with them: if you’ve taught DH in the classroom, think of the students who respond along the lines of “DH is exactly what I do or want to do, I just didn’t have a term for it before” but expand them to include folks from all over the world and more diverse walks of life. But this work has also been a significant source of anxiety, balancing my responsibility to the community with my desire to help folks learn to be more positive influences on that community, and needing to enforce the line after which a community member cannot healthfully continue as a community member. That stress was largely why I moved Infinite Ulysses from a Drupal site allowing commenting, to a static archived version without commenting. (Relatedly, I’ve &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarslab.org/blog/moderation-running-dh-online-communities&quot;&gt;just blogged&lt;/a&gt; on some of the work I’ve been doing to make online moderation of academic communities more sustainable!)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 15 Apr 2019 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2019/04/15/archiving-dh-part-2-the-problem-in-detail/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2019/04/15/archiving-dh-part-2-the-problem-in-detail/</guid>
        
        <category>digital-humanities</category>
        
        <category>meta-dh</category>
        
        <category>dh-now</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Notes: Workflows to consider before opening a DH lab (Purdue version)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part of &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/tag/meta-dh/&quot;&gt;my meta-DH series&lt;/a&gt; documenting DH/DS infrastructure: the hows &amp;amp; whys of treating a project team, lab, department, or campus as itself a DH project.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Caveat&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;This post consists of notes taken during my former &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/tag/purdue-dh/&quot;&gt;DH Librarian role at Purdue&lt;/a&gt; (2015-2017), rather than my latest thinking at Scholars’ Lab. I’ll be sharing that updated thinking here soon!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What workflows should I think through before the Purdue Libraries DH Lab can open its doors?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;IP policy: okay to post work to GitHub? using what license?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Project management: Basecamp? Asana? Trello? something that can connect to GitHub, IFTTT or Zapier, or the Archives &amp;amp; Special Collections unit’s Drupal workflow if it’s created there&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Code of conduct for events, interactions, collaborations, social media (including commitment to equitable representation via speakers and event participants)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How do new or learning coders participate in technical work?: Development/experimentation server, checklists for coders and whoever is approving moves to the production site&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;General server workflow: production, test, staff development, learner experimentation servers/VMs and flow among servers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Policy on what projects we host ourselves&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Policy on best practices: usability, accessibility, public participation, outreach, research publication, technical stack (e.g. when possible build a static site)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Workflow for preserving projects: Webrecorder, BagIt, video of narrated exploration; LOCKSS; Purdue repo’s and Archives &amp;amp; Special Collections unit; workflow for collapsing dynamic sites into static ones&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sample contract for working with DH Lab staff: mutual agreements&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sample contract with Libraries IT concerning technical coverage and ASC on web archiving (if interested)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Web design and development checklist&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Usability and accessibility checklist (web, events, publications)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Best practices doc for digital editions: who locates, transcribes/digitizes/proofs, uploads (as individual pages) text?; signed documentation of IP right for use of text?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Workflow for working with Archives &amp;amp; Special Collections artifacts: security, moving objects between offices/buildings&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Workflow for staff adding resources, people, etc. to “DH at Purdue” site&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Social media policy: tone, etiquette, access, schedule for Twitter, blog, Facebook&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;IT workflow (negotiating how we work alongside the Libraries’ existing IT team): meet early in project/grant design, accessibility/video captioning, service contract, data plan w/security, accessibility compliance, longterm hosting plans&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 25 Nov 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/11/25/workflows-before-opening-DH/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/11/25/workflows-before-opening-DH/</guid>
        
        <category>digital-humanities</category>
        
        <category>meta-dh</category>
        
        <category>notes</category>
        
        <category>purdue-dh</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Notes: Wise resource investments for a DH initiative (Purdue version)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part of &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/tag/meta-dh/&quot;&gt;my meta-DH series&lt;/a&gt; documenting DH/DS infrastructure: the hows &amp;amp; whys of treating a project team, lab, department, or campus as itself a DH project.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Caveat&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;This post consists of notes taken during my former &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/tag/purdue-dh/&quot;&gt;DH Librarian role at Purdue&lt;/a&gt; (2015-2017), rather than my latest thinking at Scholars’ Lab. I’ll be sharing that updated thinking here soon!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ideas about making wise resource investments:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ask “Should we even build a center?” and explore other metaphors/options&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Convene a Libraries DH initiative advisory committee: not oversight/supervision, but resource and advocates for my DH in the department (e.g. on the hiring committee)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Require potential faculty fellows/project members to attend one term of “introduction to DH” workshops first before committing to collaboration, using MITH’s DH Incubator model (lessons in finding, creating, cleaning, sharing, documenting data; collaboration best practices, why and how to credit everyone involved in your work: how to use GoogleDocs, Trello, Doodle polls; common mistakes using new methodologies; joining the DH online community via blogging and Twitter)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sign mutual contract with collaborators indicating expected deliverables and deadlines, checkpoints and what will happen if work not done, and expectations for crediting and citing all team members in publications and presentations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Send Purdue DHers at all levels out to train (HILT in Indianapolis, RBS), then bring back to campus to give a presentation on what they learned&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Invest in collaborators, not projects&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Train the trainers (peer review, personal research &amp;amp; professionalism time for all)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Publications (questions by Geoffrey Pullum, “To co-author, or not to co-author?” with slight alterations to fit our needs): What names will appear on title page? What order? Who/what has IP rights? Can any team members recycle paper’s content for conference presentation or for inclusion/adaptation in other work including journal articles and books? What happens if the project is dropped or one member fails to uphold their contract? Would other team members be allowed to wrap up the project or publications about the project as desired (and publish under what names)? For continuing projects, how long should all team members names stay on the front page? (All names should always stay on a history or about page).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;See also students’ (UCLA) and collaborators’ (MITH) bills of rights. Include info on assuring student mentorship for all assistance, internships, jobs, teaching, and mentoring—not e.g. data entry.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;All panels, sets of conference keynotes, and hiring should look for unconscious bias and be structured to support inclusion.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CRM for consultation/campus DH tracking?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Consultation appointment set up includes consent to code of conduct, optional inclusion in campus DH directory&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Public workflows a la Guelph (what we do/don’t do, what effort involved…)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 25 Nov 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/11/25/wise-resource-investments-digital-humanities-initiative/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/11/25/wise-resource-investments-digital-humanities-initiative/</guid>
        
        <category>digital-humanities</category>
        
        <category>meta-dh</category>
        
        <category>notes</category>
        
        <category>purdue-dh</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
