<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Literature Geek</title>
    <description>smarter online communities via digital humanities</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2016 12:25:44 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2016 12:25:44 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.0.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Meta-DH, or Designing and Building a DH Initiative</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/tag/meta-dh/&quot;&gt;starting a “meta-DH” series of blog posts&lt;/a&gt; to document my work developing a digital humanities initiative here in the Libraries at Purdue University. This work includes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;figuring out what our DH could and should be&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;creating a DH physical space (center? lab? something else?)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the practical considerations of layout and budgeting&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;designing policies and infrastructure for the initiative&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;building DH projects both to test our policies and to model the kinds of scholarship our methods realize&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve been on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.literaturegeek.com&quot;&gt;this blog&lt;/a&gt; before, you might have noticed that I enjoy blogging and other user-friendly &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/tag/advice-tutorial/&quot;&gt;documentation&lt;/a&gt; of DH scholarship. This style of writing helps me think, with the bonus that sometimes that thinking is useful to others. Blogging can also lead to feedback on resources I should check out, potential collaborators, and what I’m doing wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first year on the job meant writing a lot of GoogleDocs and other semi-private stuff: taking notes on meetings and consultations, recording ideas for projects, and explaining my plans to administration. To communicate more clearly (and use my colleagues’ generous donation of their reading time well), I summarize—meaning I generate a lot of documentation that hasn’t reached anyone else yet. I think the non-condensed versions of these ideas could be useful to someone. Thus, this series of posts!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll probably blog:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;✔️ &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2016/02/28/DHjobtalk&quot;&gt;The job talk that put me in this role (already blogged earlier this year)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Creating the website for our DH initiative&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What I learned during my first year in this role: doing a campus DH survey &amp;amp; making good time &amp;amp; resource investments&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How I’ve interpreted my job description&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Working with my faculty review committee to receive credit for my various kinds of DHy scholarship&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Daily practices (my office setup, software used, consultations, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;DH program identity and choosing what to call our initiative (center? lab? should we even have a physical space?)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My formal DH initiative proposal to department administration&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Designing and following through on a DH mission statement&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Partnerships and collaboration&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Defining DH scope&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Designing timelines and funding requests&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Creating a DH space: layout, equipment, budget&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Grant proposals and sustainable models&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there’s something not on that list you’d like to read about, let me know on Twitter &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.twitter.com/literature_geek&quot;&gt;@literature_geek&lt;/a&gt; or by email aviscont@purdue.edu.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/2016/09/05/meta-dh</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2016/09/05/meta-dh</guid>
        
        <category>digital-humanities</category>
        
        <category>advice-tutorial</category>
        
        <category>meta-dh</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Teaching with Omeka (DH consultation notes)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;When I provide DH consultations via email or in person, I try to also share the resources mentioned as a blog post here when they seem broadly useful. These notes aren’t representative of everything available on a topic, just some info for those new to a topic getting their feet wet. See this blog’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/tag/advice-tutorial/&quot;&gt;advice category&lt;/a&gt; for more posts with advice and tutorials, and let me know if you’d like more in-depth resources around a specific DH topic.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the best online lessons I know of are these two on the peer-reviewed &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://programminghistorian.org/lessons&quot;&gt;Programming Historian&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; website: “&lt;a href=&quot;http://programminghistorian.org/lessons/up-and-running-with-omeka&quot;&gt;Up and Running with Omeka.net&lt;/a&gt;” by Miriam Posner, followed by “&lt;a href=&quot;http://programminghistorian.org/lessons/creating-an-omeka-exhibit&quot;&gt;Creating an Omeka Exhibit&lt;/a&gt;” by Miriam Posner and Megan R. Brett. These do a thorough walkthrough of setting up and filling out your Omeka website (and include frequent screenshots!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do you know where you want students to create their websites?&lt;/strong&gt; I’ve found the easiest thing is having each student create an account on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.omeka.net/&quot;&gt;Omeka.net&lt;/a&gt; using the free plan (500MB storage, 15 available plugins that add extra site features, and 5 themes that change the look of your site). An Omeka.net account gives each student a free Omeka website (at something like mycustomtitle.omeka.net) , plus &lt;a href=&quot;http://info.omeka.net/&quot;&gt;lots of documentation&lt;/a&gt; for any questions that come up. Some examples of Omeka.net sites are &lt;a href=&quot;http://info.omeka.net/showcase/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note that Omeka.net is different from Omeka.org&lt;/strong&gt;; Omeka.net lets you build Omeka sites right on the Omeka.net website, while Omeka.org is the Omeka code, which you can download and on your own server to have more control and customization options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a more in-depth project where students would want to be altering Omeka code, installing the code on their own web server, using plugins (things that add features like commenting) or themes (change the look of your website) not available on Omeka.net, or purchasing and using a more customized domain name (MyCustomSite.com instead of MyCustomSite.omeka.net), you’d want to explore the resources on Omeka.org. This is considerably more technically intensive than using Omeka.net and is comparable to running your own WordPress blog instead of using WordPress.net (if you’re familiar with those). But! For both Omeka options (.net and .org), there’s amazing and thorough documentation, user forums, and tutorials focused on teaching with Omeka; you just need to decide how much effort you or your students want to devote to web development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you do choose Omeka.org&lt;/strong&gt;, your university IT may or may not be willing to install the code for you on your free university web space (like Drupal or WordPress, Omeka requires not just web code but a database). If the cost is not prohibitive, I highly recommend considering pointing students to &lt;a href=&quot;https://reclaimhosting.com/&quot;&gt;Reclaim Hosting&lt;/a&gt; instead; this gives them greater control over their website, especially after they graduate or otherwise leave the university. Reclaim has &lt;a href=&quot;a $25/year option&quot;&gt;a $25/year option&lt;/a&gt; that includes excellent custom service knowledgable about academics’ needs, a free custom domain name (e.g. MyCoolOmekaSite.com), and installation of Omeka at the push of a button.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A few additional resources:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Amanda French’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://amandafrench.net/2013/11/12/introduction-to-omeka-lesson-plan/&quot;&gt;Omeka lesson plan&lt;/a&gt; (detailed outline for what to cover in class when introducing Omeka)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Miriam Posner’s “&lt;a href=&quot;http://miriamposner.com/blog/how-did-they-make-that/&quot;&gt;How did they make that?&lt;/a&gt;”, a blog post showing several DH projects (including an Omeka one) and explaining in non-technical language the tools and work involved in creating each project&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://omeka.org/files/docs/OmekaWorkshopTipSheet.pdf&quot;&gt;This Omeka PDF&lt;/a&gt; has links for understanding Omeka terminology like metadata and Dublin Core&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://teachinghistory.org/digital-classroom/tech-for-teachers/25115&quot;&gt;This lesson&lt;/a&gt; at TeachingHistory.org is another option for getting started with Omeka&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jeffrey W. McClurken on “&lt;a href=&quot;http://chronicle.com/blogs/profhacker/teaching-with-omeka/26078&quot;&gt;Teaching with Omeka&lt;/a&gt;”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://omeka.org/codex/Teach_with_Omeka&quot;&gt;Some examples&lt;/a&gt; of Omeka class projects&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sheila Brennan’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://omeka.org/blog/2013/08/20/back-to-school-edition-use-omeka-in-your-class/&quot;&gt;Omeka resource roundup&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Alexandra Bolintineanu’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://omekagym.omeka.net/about&quot;&gt;Omeka Gym&lt;/a&gt;, a website collecting Omeka assignments, resources, examples, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many more excellent Omeka resources out there, so if you’re seeking help with something specific, consider an online search to turn up the many Omeka-focused teacher’s blog posts and presentation, then posting to &lt;a href=&quot;https://forum.omeka.org/&quot;&gt;Omeka’s support forums&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 19 Aug 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/2016/08/19/DH-consultation-notes-teaching-omeka</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2016/08/19/DH-consultation-notes-teaching-omeka</guid>
        
        <category>digital-humanities</category>
        
        <category>advice-tutorial</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A Digital Humanities What, Why, &amp; How (DLF eResearch Network Talk)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I gave the following talk on the what, why, and how of digital humanities to the Digital Library Federation (DLF) Research Network on July 20, 2016 (&lt;a href=&quot;https://clir.adobeconnect.com/_a960001693/p9qmqw2b9w5/?launcher=false&amp;amp;fcsContent=true&amp;amp;pbMode=normal&quot;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/clirdlf/eresearchnetwork/blob/master/syllabus-ern-2016.md#digital-scholarship-digital-humanities-data-visualization&quot;&gt;syllabus&lt;/a&gt;). The audience was librarians interested in digital things, but this talk is broadly applicable; if you’re a grad student or thinking about becoming one, though, you might also be interested in my &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/tag/grad-advice/&quot;&gt;posts on doing DH as a student&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/tag/dissertation/&quot;&gt;on my now-completed DH literature dissertation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I’m going to share my personal answers to some related digital humanities (or “DH”) questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#what&quot;&gt;What is DH?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#why&quot;&gt;Why can DH be good for my work, for my department, and for my university?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#how&quot;&gt;How can I get started in DH?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what&quot;&gt;What&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/DH_DLFtalk/Slide01.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing DH definitely is: overly defined. The website &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.WhatIsDigitalHumanities.com&quot;&gt;WhatIsDigitalHumanities.com&lt;/a&gt; currently offers over 800 definitions of DH submitted by DH practitioners. Definitions of this field maybe aren’t hugely helpful in understanding it, but I’ll start with one anyway:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/DH_DLFtalk/Slide02.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Digital humanities takes the work already done in the humanities (that is, research, teaching, and learning in areas like literature, history, and the arts; everything related to our past and present cultural heritage). But! It does this work in digital ways, such as making and using computer software, websites, and mobile phone apps to teach, or to help researchers and learners…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/DH_DLFtalk/Slide03.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A nuance of this definition is that DH is not just about using digital tools and methods and formats in humanities work; it’s also about applying humanities thinking to the digital. For example, a DHer might think through what a feminist social media platform would look like, or look for the hidden interpretative work that goes into creating a shiny map of political opinions in America. What gets represented, and why? What gets elided and glossed over?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/StewartVarner&quot;&gt;Stewart Varner&lt;/a&gt; (in &lt;a href=&quot;https://stewartvarner.com/2016/01/what-dh-could-be/&quot;&gt;a great blog post&lt;/a&gt;) points out that the &lt;a href=&quot;http://viraltexts.org/&quot;&gt;Viral Texts project&lt;/a&gt; led by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ryancordell&quot;&gt;Ryan Cordell&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/dasmiq&quot;&gt;David Smith&lt;/a&gt; is a good example of this kind of DH. They’re using an algorithm to discover texts that were routinely reprinted in 19th-century historical newspapers—that is, discovering historical memes! After discovering where and how texts were reprinted and passed along among newspapers, they’re applying non-digital literary scholarship to studying why these texts were reprinted, and what their paths of dissemination might mean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/DH_DLFtalk/Slide04.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A third nuance of what DH is, is that it’s as much about a distinct community and its values, as it is about DH methods and output (check out &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/mkirschenbaum&quot;&gt;Matthew Kirschenbaum&lt;/a&gt;’s “&lt;a href=&quot;https://mkirschenbaum.files.wordpress.com/2011/01/kirschenbaum_ade150.pdf&quot;&gt;What Is Digital Humanities and What’s It Doing in English Departments?&lt;/a&gt;”). DH is defined by communities of practice, whether those are of shared methods, research questions, values, or something else. I’ll show you some examples of those values in just a moment, but I do want to say that when I talk about DH community, my view is limited by my own experience, which has included a specific subset of DH using Twitter, and the projects and people at &lt;a href=&quot;http://mith.umd.edu/&quot;&gt;MITH&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://chnm.gmu.edu/&quot;&gt;CHNM&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/&quot;&gt;Scholars’ Lab&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://dhsi.org/&quot;&gt;University of Victoria’s DHSI&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dhinitiative.org/&quot;&gt;DH Initiative at Hamilton&lt;/a&gt;, and other groupings where I’ve either worked, attended an event, or used a tool or project created by that grouping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Examples always help me, so I’ll discuss three particular DH projects in more depth a little later in this talk. When I was getting started in DH, though, the thing that helped me feel like I had an understanding of this weird amorphous interdisciplinary field, was just to hear about a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of different projects, and spend some time being &lt;em&gt;gobsmacked&lt;/em&gt; by the many things doing DH could mean. So I’m going to zip through a handful of the many many things DH can be right now, before going into any level of detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/DH_DLFtalk/Slide17.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DH can look like…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the University of Michigan’s team work on increasing digital access to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lib.umich.edu/islamic/&quot;&gt;Islamic manuscripts&lt;/a&gt;, where scholars have digitized texts’ pages and commenters can add scholarly transcriptions and annotations to help others understand these texts.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;coding &lt;a href=&quot;https://wordpress.org/plugins/braille/&quot;&gt;a WordPress plugin that translates blogs into Braille&lt;/a&gt;. I was on &lt;a href=&quot;http://mith.umd.edu/research/braillesc/&quot;&gt;a team of DHers led by Tina Herzberg, George Williams, and Jen Guiliano&lt;/a&gt;, who realized that so much DH thinking is shared on WordPress blogs, and that creating some code that made blog writing simple to convert into Braille output could help in &lt;a href=&quot;http://journalofdigitalhumanities.org/3-1/making-the-digital-humanities-more-open-modeling-digital-humanities-for-a-wider-audience/&quot;&gt;making the digital humanities more open&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://mith.umd.edu/research/the-documentation-and-preservation-of-dance/&quot;&gt;a project&lt;/a&gt; that explored digital ways choreographers could notate and preserve historical dance performances (team included &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/dougreside&quot;&gt;Doug Reside&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/silkroadstudio&quot;&gt;Elisabeth Kvernen&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;archaeological work excavating old buildings and recreating these lost locations as &lt;a href=&quot;http://nico-digitalarchaeology.blogspot.com/2012/09/catalhoyuk-2012-and-4d-gis.html&quot;&gt;virtual 3D spaces &lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/nicolo_dellunto&quot;&gt;Nicolo’ Dell’Unto&lt;/a&gt;) or &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dhinitiative.org/projects/shgis&quot;&gt;recreating lost urban spaces such as the Soweto township under apartheid regimes&lt;/a&gt; (team led by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/angeldnieves&quot;&gt;Angel David Nieves&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;an event like the &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;THATCamp unconferences&lt;/a&gt;, which started at George Mason University’s DH center (&lt;a href=&quot;http://chnm.gmu.edu/&quot;&gt;RRCHNM&lt;/a&gt;) and now take place around the world. These are events that try to bring DHers together to talk and build in less hierarchical ways than traditional humanities conferences do.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a bot, such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/wcaleb&quot;&gt;Caleb McDaniel&lt;/a&gt;’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/every3minutes&quot;&gt;@Every3Minutes Twitter bot&lt;/a&gt;, which uses social media to hammer in the crushing regularity with which enslaved people were sold in antebellum America.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a tool for doing DH work, like the &lt;a href=&quot;http://chnm.gmu.edu/&quot;&gt;Center for History and New Media&lt;/a&gt;’s work developing the &lt;a href=&quot;http://omeka.org/&quot;&gt;Omeka platform&lt;/a&gt; for online museum and archival collections. Note that making Omeka is &lt;em&gt;itself&lt;/em&gt; DH work: the scholarship that consisted of thinking through, designing, and building Omeka (research assistant professor and Omeka developer Patrick Murray-John discusses this work &lt;a href=&quot;http://journalofdigitalhumanities.org/1-1/theory-digital-humanities-and-noticing-by-patrick-murray-john/&quot;&gt;in this Journal of DH piece&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;using a script or a program to analyze text and discover who most likely authored it, and then publishing about your research (digitally or not). The 1962 Mosteller and Wallace analyses that went into determining the disputed authorship of the Federalist Papers were computer-based. (If this approach interests you, see the free online &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.digitalhumanities.org/companion/view?docId=blackwell/9781405103213/9781405103213.xml&amp;amp;chunk.id=ss1-4-1&amp;amp;toc.depth=1&amp;amp;toc.id=ss1-4-1&amp;amp;brand=default&quot;&gt;Blackwell Companion to DH and its chapter on stylistic analysis&lt;/a&gt; by Hugh Craig.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;DH can look at huge historical events, or it can look at large events alongside the every day, as with projects in &lt;a href=&quot;http://blackpressresearchcollective.org/&quot;&gt;the Black Press Research Collective&lt;/a&gt; (a team project founded and directed by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/blackdigitalhum&quot;&gt;Kim Gallon&lt;/a&gt;). The Collective includes work includes mapping and visualizing the historical availability of black newspapers, so that we don’t only know what was being written, but can also conjecture on who had access to reading that writing. For example, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/mattdelmont&quot;&gt;Matthew Delmont&lt;/a&gt;’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://blackquotidian.com/anvc/black-quotidian/introduction?path=index&quot;&gt;Black Quotidian&lt;/a&gt; captures moments of everyday black life from the past via historical newspapers.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;…meta-work around the digital humanities field, as with &lt;a href=&quot;http://transformdh.org/&quot;&gt;Transform DH&lt;/a&gt;’s work toward a more diverse and inclusive DH. TransformDH is a decentralized network that includes work by &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/moyazb&quot;&gt;Moya Bailey&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/fiona_barnett&quot;&gt;Fiona Barnett&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/anitaconchita&quot;&gt;Anne Cong-Huyen&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/alothian&quot;&gt;Alexis Lothian&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/NazcaTheMad&quot;&gt;Amanda Phillips&lt;/a&gt; among others.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;…the design of a platform like &lt;a href=&quot;http://mukurtu.org/&quot;&gt;Mukurtu&lt;/a&gt;, which is a CMS (website platform) like Drupal or Omeka, but is explicitly built to ethically support indigenous communities in managing their cultural heritage. Mukurtu was started by members of the Warumungu community, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/mukurtu&quot;&gt;Kim Christen Withey&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/craigdietrich&quot;&gt;Craig Dietrich&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Maybe you use traditional non-digital methods to do and print your humanities scholarship (as much as this Microsoft Word-loving field can be non-digital), but you’re plugged into DH Twitter and find out about the latest projects, new blogged thinking, and future collaborators by being part of a digital community (for what it’s worth, that seems to &lt;em&gt;me&lt;/em&gt; to mean that you’re doing some of your scholarship digitally). DH can mean that you actively use digital means to take part in your intellectual community.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DH can look like many kinds of methods and/or publication forms, and those methods should be inclusive of all kinds of critical thinking and contributions to shared knowledge—things that don’t always get credited as scholarship but should be, like coding, teaching, cleaning your data, building bibliographies, and documentation of how to use a humanities tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(Edit: Thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ProfessMoravec/&quot;&gt;Michelle Moravec&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/digiwonk&quot;&gt;Aimée Morrison&lt;/a&gt; for their #inclusivesyllabi tweets and work, which encouraged me to try to define DH with a diverse list of examples. Ways I can improve the list before my next talk: check if authorship %s are good, and include teaching, community &amp;amp; outside-university work, student work, &amp;amp; LGBTQ examples. I’m keeping of things I need to add &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/amandavisconti/digitalhumanities/issues/7&quot;&gt;here in a GitHub issue&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/amandavisconti/digitalhumanities/blob/master/DiverseDHExampleList.md&quot;&gt;updating the list as on GitHub&lt;/a&gt; so I can easily compare it to past versions as it changes over time). Suggestions for authors and representations of DH my list is missing warmly welcomed! [Note that I’m not looking for more &lt;u&gt;general&lt;/u&gt; intro to DH resources, just examples of diverse DH work that I’ve failed to represent with my list.]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Current suggestions from DHers: &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/elotroalex/status/756865619757260800&quot;&gt;examples of minimal computing aka #mincomp&lt;/a&gt;, plus &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/dh-notes/dhnotes&quot;&gt;a larger list of DH places to read/write/go/etc.&lt;/a&gt; both via &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/elotroalex&quot;&gt;Alex Gil&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-isnt-dh&quot;&gt;What isn’t DH?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If all this can be DH, maybe we want to say, &lt;em&gt;fine, what isn’t DH&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find that question difficult to answer concisely or usefully? But I’ll try to give an example of a thing that can both very much “be” DH, or can be a non-DH thing—with explicit emphasis that &lt;strong&gt;it’s up to the practitioner(s) in question to identify whether they, their project, and their methods “are DH”.&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;em&gt;I added some stuff here subsequent to my talk, as I wasn’t quite sure I’d gotten across what I wanted to say and needed to think through it more via writing; you can &lt;a href=&quot;#dh-values&quot;&gt;skip down to the “DH values” section&lt;/a&gt; if you’d prefer.&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite arguments that the term DH isn’t useful if we don’t define it more rigidly than I have above—and maybe what I’ve said above, or any of the other 800+ definitions, should really be enough as a definition?–I just don’t have much use for someone declaring whether &lt;em&gt;someone else’s&lt;/em&gt; work “is DH” or not, and have trouble imagining I wouldn’t find such a declaration both wrong and disrespectful. But there are reasons to apply the term DH other than boundary-defining: sometimes we want to talk about some group of work in general, or about work for which we don’t know whether the creator would term it DH, or want to say “I’d consider this project DH [implicitly expecting that anyone involved contradicted this, they have the last word]”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I define DH in part by a willingness to partner with and borrow from all other fields. If someone expresses interest in what a community is doing and its values, they don’t need to perfectly perform all those values to have some magical judge grant them entrance to an academic field. If we all had to tirelessly adhere to rules all the time or be cast out of DH, we wouldn’t have anyone in the field, and the field would never grow. (This is, of course, a separate issue from banning people from a community who are harassers or engage in other unethical behavior.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll give an example of a DH activity that is at some times somewhat related or overlapping with DH, and at some times not DH: digitization. (I really could have picked any of a number of activities: for example, it’s pretty clear to everyone that coding can “be” DH, or it can be not DH, e.g. coding for business, science, etc.). I’m picking digitization because the general public tends to be more aware of projects like &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.com/&quot;&gt;Google Books&lt;/a&gt;, of scanning and putting stuff online, and less aware of research based on it (Google Books might not be the best example because of DHers’ mixed response to  &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.com/ngrams&quot;&gt;stuff subsequently built from the Google Books digitization&lt;/a&gt;). The public tends to know less about other DHy things, and when I mention my field I sometimes encounter people thinking that “all” DH means is scanning and uploading humanities stuff. (One problem with this: you can “just” scan and upload in exactly the same way you can “just” write a shopping list or code a science tool, or you can engage critically with the decisions this involves, etc.). Digitization is a DH method, and is often crucial, scholarly work; it’s just that digitization (or coding, or whatever other method you want to think through) is in no way &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; of what DH does. Just pointing to any method (scanning, 3D modeling, coding, writing…) without the thinking and sharing that together with that method equals scholarship, is something I do run into, and I want people to be aware of the thinking and learning part of using a scholarly method, too. (More on what “scholarly method” means to me later, too.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Digital humanities isn’t so much focused “just” on digitizing things. DH projects often don’t stop at scanning and putting humanities content like historical newspapers or photos online (although they could stop there and share their learning). Rather, DH projects often do so as a way to study or improve the process of digitization, or as a prelude to additional research. DH is often focused on designing inspiring and useful ways for interacting with those online materials, once they’ve been made digital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(&lt;em&gt;On reflection, I shouldn’t have picked digitization as my main example, because digitization work tends to be wrongly less treated as scholarly or more poorly paid, than other can-be-DH methods like coding. I think that incorrect dynamic made this explanation less concise than it could have been&lt;/em&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/DH_DLFtalk/Slide19.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Digitization can be DH, just as much as coding, teaching, writing, performing, or many other possible methods of scholarship. Rather than bulk uploading of scanned documents, a DH digitization project might, for example, be concerned with figuring out the exact lighting and scanner settings to represent a scanned manuscript online, and the people doing this might speculate about what it would mean for a scan to be a more authoritative representation of the scanned manuscript, than if that manuscript were scanned with different lighting and settings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These scholars are asking, how do we best represent this physical thing digitally? What would “best representation” mean, and is there even such a thing, or is any process that involves choices subjective? People aren’t just robotically scanning and uploading stuff; even if they’re overworked and underpaid they’re developing expertise around this technical work. People care about the work they do and can’t help but think critically about the best ways to do it, and it’s weird and not useful to assume people working in the humanities in any role aren’t expert critical thinkers around the work they do. One thing I like about DH is that the community tends to be a little better at recognizing all humanities labor as the scholarship it is (versus “traditional” humanities), rather than glossing over the important, critical thinking and scholarship of people in many different professional roles (&lt;em&gt;though it’s far from perfect at this recognition, as I’ll discuss below&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dh-values&quot;&gt;DH values&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, asking if something is or isn’t DH might not be the most generative question (&lt;em&gt;I guess it generated a bunch of words from my keyboard, though…)&lt;/em&gt;. Instead, we may want to ask, what do DHers care about? And how can we encourage others to care about the same thing, when that’s appropriate?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll talk a bit more in-depth about three DH projects now, to give you a sense of what some DH values look like in practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/DH_DLFtalk/Slide20.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the trends I’m seeing in DH is a move from making things public, to making things participatory. 10-20 years ago, there was a big emphasis on just getting transcripts and scans of texts and images online, so people who couldn’t afford to travel to see the originals could nevertheless create scholarship around these things. These projects are great gifts to the world, and the critical thinking and decisions and experiments that went into them (and continues today with digitization staff) is DH scholarship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a basic level of creating “access” to information, where someone’s scanned something and put it online where anyone can hypothetically access it. This is the case with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.loc.gov/pictures/collection/fsa/&quot;&gt;the Library of Congress’ digitization and hosting&lt;/a&gt; of the thousands of photographs taken as part of government-sponsored programs during the Great Depression and WWII. These photos have been freely available online thanks to the LOC for years, and they give a wonderful view of what daily life was like all over the U.S. during this time period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, the website is hard to use if you’re not used to working with research data collections every day—that is, if you’re not a researcher. And it doesn’t have tools or other design aimed explicitly at helping students and the public see why these photos are interesting and relevant to them. What the LOC staff have done (especially despite their past &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/entertainment/museums/americas-national-library-is-behind-the-digital-curve-a-new-report-finds/2015/03/31/fad54c3a-d3fd-11e4-a62f-ee745911a4ff_story.html&quot;&gt;problematic management&lt;/a&gt; and with limited resources) is truly amazing scholarship, so I want to emphasize that this is awesome work, and I believe we need projects aimed just at researchers just like this project is—it’s just that I want researchers to be making more things that are aimed at people besides ourselves, also.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(&lt;em&gt;Below is a 50-second clip I made checking out the &lt;a href=&quot;http://photogrammar.yale.edu/&quot;&gt;Photogrammar project&lt;/a&gt;… although since this is a blog post rather than a live presentation, I highly encourage &lt;a href=&quot;http://photogrammar.yale.edu/&quot;&gt;just playing around with Photogrammar yourself&lt;/a&gt;! It’s extremely intuitive and impressive.&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://player.vimeo.com/video/175695252?title=0&amp;amp;byline=0&amp;amp;portrait=0&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;434&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://photogrammar.yale.edu/&quot;&gt;The Photogrammar project&lt;/a&gt; at Yale, with a &lt;a href=&quot;http://photogrammar.yale.edu/about/team/&quot;&gt;team&lt;/a&gt; directed by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/laura_wexler&quot;&gt;Laura Wexler&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/nolauren&quot;&gt;Lauren Tilton&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/statsmaths&quot;&gt;Taylor Arnold&lt;/a&gt;, is a great example of what digital humanities projects can add to the basic access allowed by digitized materials. Photogrammar is built on those thousands of Great Depression and WWII photos hosted by the Library of Congress (&lt;a href=&quot;http://photogrammar.yale.edu/about/fsa_owi/&quot;&gt;the FSA-OWI collection, 1935-1944 photos sponsored by the Farm Security Administration&lt;/a&gt;). What Photogrammar does, is to add an appealing interface that makes you interested in looking at these photos, then supports you as you start to have questions you’d like to answer about the photos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/DH_DLFtalk/Slide22.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additional tools on the site help you locate the photos that would be most interesting to you, and relate to what you’re teaching or learning. For example, above is a tool that uses facial recognition to identify people in these photos, and to let you explore and question where and when these photos were taken by the subjects’ ethnicities. Another tool lets you find commonalities and differences among subsets of the photos: like what kind of photos were most often taken in California between 1935 and 1945?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see the LOC ‘s project as representative of an earlier but still extremely important set of DH values: of getting stuff online in clean and accessible fashion; once more information is online, we can start to make it easier for people to do stuff with it, like Photogrammar does. Photogrammar is representative of a more recent value of DH: making the humanities not just more public, but more publicly inviting and participatory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/DH_DLFtalk/Slide23.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.docnow.io/&quot;&gt;Documenting the Now&lt;/a&gt; is a DH project building ethical tools for preserving and including social media activism in the archive, with a focus on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/blacklivesmatter&quot;&gt;#BlackLivesMatter&lt;/a&gt; and related hashtags. More than just a tool, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.docnow.io/&quot;&gt;DocNow&lt;/a&gt; is building a community around the difficult questions of ethically and respectfully creating a historical record of protests, including through a &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/1Wk0JdF2Cty2VHMqpf_QlJXVKQdUtfeeFhaYRben3qaM/viewform&quot;&gt;Slack&lt;/a&gt; (a chat platform) where everyone is invited to participate in conversations around archival ethics and design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DocNow’s community lead, archivist &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/BergisJules&quot;&gt;Bergis Jules&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/BergisJules/status/755484124614303744&quot;&gt;describes the project&lt;/a&gt; as trying to make the social media and web archiving conversation and work more inclusive, and says &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; might be the most important contribution of their project, even more than the tool they create.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DocNow’s lead developer &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/edsu&quot;&gt;Ed Summers&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.docnow.io/docnow-as-community-2aa13fca860f#.gtbx9a4jh&quot;&gt;describes their work&lt;/a&gt; by saying: “I think what we are hoping to do is build a tool that doesn’t just do things because it’s possible, but has some values built into it”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an example of a couple things I like about DH, and optimistically think of as representative of DH’s values: they’re documenting their thinking and decisions, via &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.docnow.io/&quot;&gt;blog posts&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/1Wk0JdF2Cty2VHMqpf_QlJXVKQdUtfeeFhaYRben3qaM/viewform&quot;&gt;Slack&lt;/a&gt;, as they go along. They’re thinking about the shortcomings of technology: what happens to discussions happening on for-profit platforms like Twitter, where video links can break, tweets can be taken out of context, and people converse without consenting to becoming part of some institution’s record? They’re thinking carefully about the ethics of what they build and what others may do with what they build, trying to be not just legal, but moral. They’ve created &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/1Wk0JdF2Cty2VHMqpf_QlJXVKQdUtfeeFhaYRben3qaM/viewform&quot;&gt;a community space&lt;/a&gt; where anyone interested in these questions can participate in the conversation shaping the tool. And they’re working toward making the archive a better, more diverse, actively anti-racist record.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/DH_DLFtalk/Slide24.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a final example, one of my DH projects is a website that supports collaboratively reading and interpreting a really difficult novel, James Joyce’s &lt;em&gt;Ulysses.&lt;/em&gt; Above is a screenshot of the front page of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.infiniteulysses.com&quot;&gt;Infinite Ulysses digital edition&lt;/a&gt;. The images give a high level tour of the edition’s features: you can highlight parts of the book and annotate those highlights; read others’ annotations; and start to personalize what annotations you see to your background, interests, and needs on a very basic level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal of the project was to take a popular DH platform—the scholarly digital edition—and look at ways we can use visual and community design to invite, welcome, support, and value the contributions of non-academics in the conversations around challenging and complex literary texts. It was an experiment—I wasn’t sure what was going to happen and whether anyone would use the site. I also valued publicly documenting the design and technical choices I made throughout the project, and to not only discuss successes but also failures, like &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2014/05/12/spring-2014-tech-update&quot;&gt;the time I spent 6 months working with a platform I ended up not using in the final website&lt;/a&gt;. I wrote &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/tag/dissertation/&quot;&gt;a blog post twice a month&lt;/a&gt; to capture this information where others could read it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/DH_DLFtalk/Slide25.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Increasing access can mean reaching out farther to collaborate with audiences that aren’t as welcomed by the humanities. We want to think about the time and money required to engage with DH projects; about the bandwidth and hardware needed; about who gets to see themselves represented and spoken to. One of the failures I often hear ascribed to MOOCs, is that they don’t actually open up learning to people who didn’t already have some other option in terms of accessing higher ed resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As happy as I am with how &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.infiniteulysses.com&quot;&gt;Infinite Ulysses&lt;/a&gt; has reached a variety of readers outside academia, of all ages and from around the world, there are two big things I’d like the project to do better. The first is to design to invite and support readers who don’t already have other alternatives for making their way through Joyce. And the second goal is to make this bigger than &lt;em&gt;Ulysses&lt;/em&gt;: I was able to draw over 20 thousand site unique visitors because people have heard something about James Joyce and &lt;em&gt;Ulysses&lt;/em&gt;, but it’s a big problem if what we create and encourage people to visit online just recreates the canon of print books (and a related problem that huge numbers of site visitors doesn’t mean people who stay and enjoy the project). As much as I like &lt;em&gt;Ulysses&lt;/em&gt;, I want to figure out what readers on my site like about the novel, and then point them to less-canon texts that do similar things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;why&quot;&gt;Why&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/DH_DLFtalk/Slide26.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I talk about why you might want to be involved in the digital humanities, I tend to speak toward the good and ideal of DH, and the DH I want to see. But DH isn’t some magical anomaly. It’s a community of people from a lot of fields, with a lot of subfields of its own, and it shares many of the same problems as humanities fields, something the &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/search?q=%23transformdh&quot;&gt;#TransformDH hashtag&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://transformdh.tumblr.com/&quot;&gt;Tumblr&lt;/a&gt; are working on. I encourage you to check out the Twitter hashtags on the screen for some useful conversations around problems in DH, including issues at the yearly big DH conference that took place last week—the &lt;a href=&quot;http://hawksey.info/tagsexplorer/arc.html?key=1zlUFubccXY7Pekfs0bXgxzIbNalJPGvU_SJIlmLTI50&amp;amp;gid=400689247&quot;&gt;#DHdiversity hashtag&lt;/a&gt; (archive captured by &lt;a href=&quot;https://epriego.wordpress.com/2016/07/13/dhdiversity-a-searchable-archive-and-a-quick-comment-from-afar/&quot;&gt;Ernesto Priego&lt;/a&gt;) documents a series of panels and talks identifying ongoing issues of sexism, racism, ableism, and other marginalizations in DH and at our conference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People who are marginalized and in precarious professional roles are still overly called to testify and labor for improvements within DH. And DH is getting big: the yearly DH conference last week drew 902 participants from 45 countries, but diverse representation is lagging behind the realities of who does DH. Projects actively working to make DH better in this regard include &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/roopikarisam&quot;&gt;Roopika Risam&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/michacardenas&quot;&gt;micha cárdenas&lt;/a&gt;’ &lt;a href=&quot;http://criticaldh.roopikarisam.com/&quot;&gt;Social Justice and DH project&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/elotroalex&quot;&gt;Alex Gil&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ryancordell&quot;&gt;Ryan Cordell&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.arounddh.org/credits/&quot;&gt;others&lt;/a&gt;’ &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.arounddh.org/&quot;&gt;Around DH in 80 Days&lt;/a&gt; (which highlights DH centers and projects from around the world); and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://mith.umd.edu/offthetracks/recommendations/&quot;&gt;Off the Tracks Collaborators’ Bill of Rights&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cdh.ucla.edu/news-events/a-student-collaborators-bill-of-rights/&quot;&gt;UCLA A Student Collaborators’ Bill of Rights&lt;/a&gt; (which both lay out how to ethically credit and celebrate the labor of everyone involved in a DH project).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/DH_DLFtalk/Slide27.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As much as I like to work toward what I want my DH to be, I don’t want to give anyone the impression that DH is some utopia. It’s not better than other fields, but it has in its favor some more ways for people to regularly, actively move the field to be a little bit better at a time. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/mydhis&quot;&gt;#MyDHis hashtag&lt;/a&gt; captures people speaking about their visions for what DH should value; the &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/whatifdh2017&quot;&gt;#WhatIfDH2017&lt;/a&gt; and previous years’ hashtags capture suggestions and provocations challenging the next year’s big DH conference to be better than this year’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do want to express some of the things that &lt;em&gt;my&lt;/em&gt; DH is. I tend to see DH as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Valuing interdisciplinarity (including of methods)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A celebration and valuing of a variety of skills and professional roles&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As real-time: I love being part of a community where I can ask a question on Twitter or the &lt;a href=&quot;http://tinyurl.com/DHslack&quot;&gt;DH Slack&lt;/a&gt; and hear a bunch of ideas in the next few hours.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As valuing sharing what you learn, without needing to be an expert: I was able to get started doing some very basic information visualization work and &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/tag/gephi/&quot;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt; about what I did. Even without being anything ever near an expert in information visualization, I’ve heard from people who were also able to get started in infoviz by reading my blog posts. (If you’re interested in information visualization and analysis, one place to start is Miriam Posner’s blog (&lt;a href=&quot;http://miriamposner.com/blog/how-did-they-make-that/#network&quot;&gt;getting started&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://miriamposner.com/blog/the-case-of-the-missing-faces/&quot;&gt;infoviz and ethics for historical research&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://miriamposner.com/blog/a-fun-way-to-introduce-dh-students-to-dataviz/&quot;&gt;infoviz lesson plan&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://miriamposner.com/blog/getting-started-with-palladio/&quot;&gt;Palladio tool&lt;/a&gt;) and &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/scott_bot&quot;&gt;Scott Weingart&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.scottbot.net/HIAL/index.html@p=39600.html&quot;&gt;when networks are inappropriate&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;(&lt;em&gt;On review: wow, there’s a lot of other things #myDHis not in this list, but I think they’re represented by the projects I chose to cite in this talk: public and participatory, diverse and inclusive and anti-racist, ethical and respectful… hoping to update my old “DH values” post soon to better hold myself to perform these values in my work.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/DH_DLFtalk/Slide28.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did &lt;a href=&quot;http://dr.amandavisconti.com&quot;&gt;a very DHy dissertation&lt;/a&gt; that didn’t have any chapter writing; instead, I was able to spend some time thinking through the best methods and publication formats for pursuing my research question and sharing what I learned. It turned out that designing, coding, blogging, and user-testing what I’d built were the best ways for my research to go. Being linked into the DH community was a big part of successfully being able to do that as my dissertation, instead of doing one traditional dissertation, and a whole extra DH project that wasn’t officially counted. The DH I’ve encountered is open to rethinking how what we value as scholars can look, given today’s knowledge and opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tend to see people not feeling enfranchised to call themselves digital humanists, not feeling enfranchised to call themselves scholars, not feeling enfranchised to call all their critical efforts research. So I tend to emphasize these labels to counteract imposter syndrome, people being undercredited, people not getting opportunities to situate their work as intellectual labor.
I also want to recognize that there are negative results of this habit: not everyone is or wants to be called a digital humanist or a scholar or a researcher, so I absolutely do not want to say someone is any of these things, if that’s not how someone identifies themself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/DH_DLFtalk/Slide29.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;twitter.com/moyazb&quot;&gt;Moya Bailey&lt;/a&gt; at Northeastern recently gave &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.culturalfront.org/2016/07/reflections-on-space-place-in.html&quot;&gt;a great talk here&lt;/a&gt; discussing the pros and cons of strategically leveraging the phrase “digital humanities”, and I’d encourage you all to &lt;a href=&quot;http://moyabailey.com/projects/dh/&quot;&gt;check out her work&lt;/a&gt;. She emphasized that choosing to label yourself or your work via DH can open opportunities for funding and publicity and community, but identifying with DH can also close doors or make others expect certain things about your work, or turn away scholars who are not interested in or are resistant to digital scholarship. So maybe what you do, or want to do, or the community you want to join or create, isn’t DH: you can still make use of DH-labeled resources, but choose to identify yourself and your work in a variety of ways, and attend a plethora of DHy conferences beyond the main huge DH event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/DH_DLFtalk/Slide30.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I encourage people starting with DH—especially students looking to take on a DH project but also complete their coursework or dissertation—to remember that prototyping is an option. That is, you can have a research question and imagine an ideal digital method or tool or presentation format to pursue that research. To then document the critical thinking that went into your brainstorming design, to list problems you foresee or storyboard how someone might engage with your idea, to get out your colored pencils and sketch your tool, or use some other way of wireframing or prototyping what you’re imagining—and then share all that with your community, is scholarship. It absolutely contributes to communal knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It isn’t some magical requirement that you go on and code the idea yourself, though you certainly can embark on learning how to do that—having a specific project in mind does wonders for making tutorials stick in your brain. And learning about cod,e or other pieces of realizing a DH project, helps you understand issues, limitations, opportunities you might not have seen otherwise. Or, understand why DH has treated some opportunities as low-hanging fruit and others as blue-sky wishes. But you can also leave that scholarship to a collaborator—coding and building are useful methods, but they are just some of many methods out there, and nobody needs to take all of them on. Many DH projects are necessarily collaborative, because they require many skills and no one person is likely to offer expertise for each. You can work in DH without needing to do everything yourself, and without being an expert in coding or a digital method; maybe your contribution is historical knowledge, or being great at locating information online, or designing, documenting, user testing, or publicizing, among many other options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/DH_DLFtalk/Slide31.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/samplereality&quot;&gt;Mark Sample&lt;/a&gt; has &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.samplereality.com/2013/02/08/when-does-service-become-scholarship/&quot;&gt;a fantastic blog essay on the question: “When does service become scholarship?”&lt;/a&gt;, in which he says his answer to that question “is simply this: a creative or intellectual act becomes scholarship when it is public and circulates in a community of peers that evaluates and builds upon it.” One of the things I like most about DH, is that practitioners tend to recognize and reward scholarship in its many methods and forms. Scholarship isn’t bounded by what your professional title is or whether you create something that looks like a book or journal article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see DH as not just about openness to many methods as ways to think critically and share those thoughts, but also as a movement to recognize meta-activities such as project management and documentation as scholarship. So my biggest reason why DH can be good for you, for your department or unit or university, is that it usually comes with a culture of valuing all kinds of effort. I do want to recognize that some people don’t want to identify as scholars or their work as scholarly; when I speak of scholars here, I mean everyone who’s interested in doing their best thinking and sharing the results of that thinking with others, whether you’re teaching, developing a library unit workflow, coding, writing, or another method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a personal level, it can make a useful difference in how you feel about your job and your work, if you start to value all of your effort as part of being a scholar, or feel enfranchised to identify as a scholar or researcher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Identifying with DH opens up an interdisciplinary community that, while in &lt;em&gt;no way&lt;/em&gt; perfect, is at least sometimes better than traditional academic departments at a couple useful things—and when it fails, we at least more often have public discussions about that failure, and these at least more often can slowly improve our community (e.g. when the big DH conference had all-female keynote speakers this year, and the #DHdiversity hashtag was used extensively to identify ongoing problems and suggest improvements). DH tends to welcome newcomers a little more, in part because it’s the norm for someone with years of experience in some academic field to be new to a digital method, or vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DH tends to value all kinds of professional roles and to think about how to make collaboration and attribution and credit work well, because the skills we need to make solid projects incorporate all kinds of design, theoretical, practical, technical, archival thinking (and when I say theoretical, I guess I should point out that a big thing in DH is recognizing that it isn’t just article and book writing that gets to be called “theory”; that all methods of research, for example coding and digital platform design, engage in existing theory and develop their own theories as well). Being part of this community means you can use platforms like Twitter and Slack to get real-time feedback on your thinking and projects, and sometimes you’re able to focus on and reach much wider audiences than traditional scholarship allows. (Twitter isn’t any safer for being a DHer, but on the DH Slack I’m trying to hold discussions to a code of conduct as far as a couple casual moderators can for 700 people.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DHers use the term “alt-ac” (&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/search?q=%23altac&quot;&gt;#altac&lt;/a&gt;) to refer to “alternative academic” positions, which are career paths that satisfy your desire to work as a scholar while recognizing that tenure-track teaching positions are extremely limited in number, and that many excellent researchers who would like to have such a position just can’t, in terms of position availability. There’s some really good blogging about DHer alt-ac experiences, including &lt;a href=&quot;http://mediacommons.futureofthebook.org/alt-ac/&quot;&gt;the #alt-academy mediacommons project&lt;/a&gt;. It might not seem like a big deal to be aware of related types of job if you’re coming from interdisciplinary library science, but often humanities PhDs come out of their dissertations without being aware of career options other than tenure-track teaching. Besides the obvious digital skills involvement in DH can help you develop, related abilities like being able to work well with a team of people with different interests and backgrounds, and having experience in project design, management, and grant-writing, are all skills DH projects can model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the university level, DH’s emphasis on interdisciplinary collaboration, methodologies over content, and recognition that all academic fields deal with history of the field, ethics, subjective interpretation, design, and texts will help us connect libraries and liberal arts units to other campus communities including STEM departments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;how&quot;&gt;How&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/DH_DLFtalk/Slide34.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll finish up with some resources for getting started in DH. I’ll talk briefly about where to ask questions and find foundational resources online, where to publish and read current DH work, doing DH as a job, and arguing about DH.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/DH_DLFtalk/Slide35.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are a combination of things you can do to get involved in DH, either where you are (depending on local resources) or online. Does your library have a DH, digital scholarship, or other “digital something” librarian or unit—someone who doesn’t also happen to be you? If not, I’d still recommend asking around if your colleagues have consulted or collaborated with anyone on campus doing DH. Student and staff working groups and book clubs are another option—if there aren’t any where you are, you might use a campus listserv and put out a call for anyone interested in meeting to chat and work through reading a solid DH resource such as the &lt;a href=&quot;http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/&quot;&gt;Debates in the Digital Humanities series&lt;/a&gt; (which is free online, and offers timely argumentative pieces about the shape and future of DH).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve seen some people come at DH by taking a term they keep hearing—say, Drupal websites—and deciding to learn that thing. Having that focus can work well, but I find you’re more likely to be successful if you get a little help at the start in choosing a tool or method that’s actually the best fit for your interests (Drupal, for example, can do cool things but is a headache to maintain, so you only want to use it when you need features other options don’t offer).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you can find someone in-person or online who’s involved in DH, ask if they’d be willing to point you in the right direction given your interests, whether that’s a specific research question or imagined project, or just the desire to learn how digital methods could support your love of Victorian dime novels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can be hard to ask strangers online for help, and I know people involved in scholarly organizations who are thinking through making virtual mentoring a good option. In the meantime, safer places to ask for direction or advice include the &lt;a href=&quot;http://digitalhumanities.org/answers/&quot;&gt;DH Q&amp;amp;A forum&lt;/a&gt;, and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://tinyurl.com/DHSlack&quot;&gt;DH Slack&lt;/a&gt; (which is like a set of DH themed chatrooms, with currently over 700 members and a &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/amandavisconti/DHslack/blob/master/CodeOfConduct.md&quot;&gt;code of conduct&lt;/a&gt;). The &lt;a href=&quot;http://tinyurl.com/DHslack&quot;&gt;DH Slack&lt;/a&gt; has a number of channels (or themed chatrooms) for asking any level of DH question, for students wanting to discuss fitting DH into their studies, for self-identified beginners, and for people interested in seeing the kinds of jobs and conferences currently available in DH. I run the Slack, so if you’re curious about joining or participating, but have questions or would like suggestions for getting involved, please feel free to tweet at me (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.twitter.com/literature_geek&quot;&gt;@Literature_Geek&lt;/a&gt;) or send me an email (viscount@purdue.edu).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/DH_DLFtalk/Slide36.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have a project idea that needs funding, DH funders including &lt;a href=&quot;https://mellon.org/grants/&quot;&gt;Mellon&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.neh.gov/&quot;&gt;NEH&lt;/a&gt; (National Endowment for the Humanities and especially &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.neh.gov/divisions/odh&quot;&gt;the NEH Office of Digital Humanities&lt;/a&gt;), and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imls.gov/&quot;&gt;IMLS&lt;/a&gt; (Institute of Museum and Library Services) often post example grant proposals or successful past proposals, which can be useful in shaping your research or discovering precedents in a subfield, even if you’re not applying for a grant yourself. If you are interested in grant funding, though, you should know that some regular DH funders—&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.neh.gov/divisions/odh&quot;&gt;the NEH Office of Digital Humanities&lt;/a&gt; definitely, and I believe also the IMLS?—have amazing program officers willing to read through and comment on your grant proposal, if you ask for feedback before the actual grant submission deadline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/DH_DLFtalk/Slide37.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some of the good places to read about and publish in DH &lt;em&gt;(note: resources linked in this section are very much non-exhaustive as there are lots more places to read/share/do DH, but this blog represents a time-limited talk rather than an exhaustive resource—see &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/mswEpAIS9K&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; for more stuff!):&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://digitalhumanitiesnow.org/&quot;&gt;DH Now&lt;/a&gt; is an aggregator of DH online content; I use it to hear about new blog posts on DH topics, but it also aggregates DH events, CFPs, and job openings. You can follow via &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/dhnow&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; or RSS feed. But DH now isn’t just a good way to hear about DH, it’s a good place to get started in DH social media. You can &lt;a href=&quot;http://digitalhumanitiesnow.org/editors-corner/volunteer/&quot;&gt;volunteer as an editor of DH Now&lt;/a&gt;, which means that during a specific week you’ll curate a feed of incoming content from &lt;a href=&quot;http://digitalhumanitiesnow.org/subscribed-feeds/&quot;&gt;a huge set of DH blogs and websites&lt;/a&gt;, and recommend the best stuff for sharing. This is a great way to get an overview of who you might want to follow on Twitter or who’s doing work related to your interests.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Another option is &lt;a href=&quot;http://programminghistorian.org/lessons/&quot;&gt;The Programming Historian&lt;/a&gt; website (&lt;em&gt;I should note that I’ve just joined the site’s editorial team last week because I like the project so much—so I’m biased, but for a good reason&lt;/em&gt;). &lt;em&gt;The Programming Historian&lt;/em&gt; offers peer-reviewed, novice-friendly lessons on DH tools and methods; it’s not only pitched at the right place for someone who wants to learn a skill but doesn’t already know other digital methods; each lesson tries to explain why a humanities researcher might want to use the tool, and how. In addition to being a good place for learning, it’s also &lt;a href=&quot;http://programminghistorian.org/contribute&quot;&gt;a place to do peer-reviewed publication of DH lessons and tutorials&lt;/a&gt;. If you need peer-reviewed pieces for promotion or tenure in your job, this can be a way to get credit for skills you already know, while at the same time mentoring others you want to learn those skills.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dhcommons.org/&quot;&gt;DH Commons&lt;/a&gt; is both a platform for sharing DH projects and &lt;a href=&quot;http://dhcommons.org/collaborators&quot;&gt;volunteering as a collaborator&lt;/a&gt; for things like beta-testing new DH work, and also &lt;a href=&quot;http://dhcommons.org/journal&quot;&gt;an online, peer-reviewed journal&lt;/a&gt;. This journal &lt;a href=&quot;http://dhcommons.org/journal/submission-guidelines&quot;&gt;supports submitting peer-reviewed publications&lt;/a&gt; of two DHy types: you can submit DH project statements (explanations of the work that went into your DH research) and you can submit  “How did they make that?” pieces (explaining the tech/design/methods that went into making what you made, based on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/miriamkp&quot;&gt;Miriam Posner&lt;/a&gt;’s highly recommended &lt;a href=&quot;http://miriamposner.com/blog/how-did-they-make-that/&quot;&gt;blog post of the same title&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other journals friendly to DH publication (and free to read online!) include:
* &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/&quot;&gt;Digital Humanities Quarterly&lt;/a&gt; 
* &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.digitalstudies.org/ojs/index.php/digital_studies&quot;&gt;Digital Studies&lt;/a&gt; 
* &lt;a href=&quot;http://journalofdigitalhumanities.org/&quot;&gt;The Journal of Digital Humanities&lt;/a&gt; (on hiatus, but past articles are interesting to read)
* &lt;a href=&quot;http://vectorsjournal.org/&quot;&gt;Vectors&lt;/a&gt;, a journal for publishing multimedia work in DH and related areas. I believe they take all kinds of DH pieces (websites, visualizations, etc.) but may have a preference for things authored using the &lt;a href=&quot;http://scalar.usc.edu/scalar/&quot;&gt;Scalar&lt;/a&gt; tool?
* &lt;a href=&quot;http://digitalhumanities.berkeley.edu/resources/digital-humanities-journals&quot;&gt;Digital Humanities at Berkeley’s great overview of these and other DH publications&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/DH_DLFtalk/Slide38.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if you’re not interested in a DH job yourself, keeping abreast of recent DH job ads can give you a better sense of how different DH subfields and tools cluster—you’ll see what kinds of tools DH archivists are using, what history professors are using, and be better able to point others in the right direction for getting involved in DH. And if you are thinking about a DH career, being aware of the language in DH job ads can help you tailor your learning toward a specific role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Miriam Posner &lt;a href=&quot;http://tinyurl.com/MiriamPosnerJobs&quot;&gt;posts DHy jobs to her Pinboard&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://digitalhumanitiesnow.org/category/news/job/&quot;&gt;Digital Humanities Now’s job feed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Using general job search engines like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.usajobs.gov&quot;&gt;USA Jobs&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.indeed.com/jobs?q=Digital-humanities&quot;&gt;Indeed.com with “digital humanities” as the search term&lt;/a&gt; is more hit and miss, but you can set things up so they email you whenever a job matching DH appears on their sites.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you’re interested in government DHy jobs (e.g. NEH ODH, IMLS, Smithsonian…), besides searching by institution on the USA Jobs site, you can follow NEH ODH Senior Program Officer &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jenserventi&quot;&gt;Jennifer Serventi&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter, where she periodically shares these humanities-focused jobs (&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/JenServenti/status/755926991388315648&quot;&gt;for example&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other places to scope DH and related digital library jobs include:
* &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.h-net.org/jobs/job_search.php?category_id=29&quot;&gt;H-Net DH jobs&lt;/a&gt;
* &lt;a href=&quot;http://jobs.code4lib.org/jobs/digital-humanities/&quot;&gt;Code 4 Lib DH jobs&lt;/a&gt;
* &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hastac.org/events-opportunities/jobs-and-fellowships&quot;&gt;HASTAC jobs and fellowships&lt;/a&gt;
* &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.diglib.org/contact/jobs/&quot;&gt;Digital Library Federation job postings&lt;/a&gt;
* &lt;a href=&quot;http://acrl.ala.org/dh/&quot;&gt;DH+Lib website&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.twitter.com/dh+lib&quot;&gt;@DH+lib Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you start to see a lot of projects that fit your interest coming from one DH center or department, it can’t hurt to follow their website’s RSS feed to hear about new job openings. And when you apply, remember that DH gives you particular skills beyond technical ones, and you should demonstrate these skills to potential employers: the ability to handle project management (even more, often for projects with less precedents than usual precedents in academia!), experience with collaboration and interdisciplinarity, and learning to communicate in voices suited to multiple audiences and with relevancy for who you’re talking to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/DH_DLFtalk/Slide39.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, I wanted to say a bit about arguing to do DH. If you run into trouble with someone preventing you from doing DH work (e.g. saying you can’t use your professional development funding to learn a DH tool, or that you can’t satisfy coursework with digital scholarship), you can help you argument in a couple ways. You might develop a concise statement or elevator pitch, using no specialist/technical language: maybe one paragraph on what your final deliverables will look like (to help people picture what you’ll do), and one paragraph explaining why your digital methods or format are the best way for exploring and communicating your research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can also help to assemble a list of precedents for your work. When I was arguing that I should be able to design and code a digital edition for my dissertation, &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2013/08/19/scholarlyexperimentation&quot;&gt;for example&lt;/a&gt;, I &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2013/06/26/experimental-editions&quot;&gt;pointed to&lt;/a&gt; work by established scholars like Alan Galey, whose &lt;a href=&quot;http://individual.utoronto.ca/alangaley/visualizingvariation/index.html&quot;&gt;Visualizing Variation&lt;/a&gt; project uses code to make arguments about early modern textual scholarship. I also looked for examples both of similar methods and formats; in my case, my committee pointed out that literature departments have a history of allowing a print scholarly edition as a dissertation. I also looked to pre-digital precedents in my subfield: textual scholarship—the people who create scholarly editions of texts—has a long history of using design and building to perform arguments (e.g. the Victorian editor Teena Rochfort Smith created &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2013/06/26/experimental-editions&quot;&gt;an experimental prototype of &lt;em&gt;Hamlet&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; with typography so innovative it would have been impossible to print at scale at that time). A lot of the rejection of digital scholarship hinges on it being “different” from non-digital scholarship, so showing the ways digital scholarship is a natural successor to research widely recognized as scholarship is a useful tactic (not “digital vs. traditional”, but “digital vs. non-digital”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I hope I communicated earlier, DH is not perfect. DH has a lot of areas where we can greatly improve as a community. That said, I don’t want to overemphasize the issue of needing to argue for DH as scholarship. Instead of predicting that my DH work will meet with resistance, I try to design my work to invite understanding, by doing things like showing its continuity with past non-digital work, and making sure I’m careful about defining technical terms. From just my particular point of view, I can say that presenting DH pedagogically rather than defensively has been great at helping me communicate with people not involved in DH.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thank you to organizers Jason Clark, Oliver Bendorf, and Sara Mannheimer, as well as to the DLF eResearch Network members for being a great audience! Also, a big thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/elikaortega&quot;&gt;Élika Ortega&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/StewartVarner&quot;&gt;Stewart Varner&lt;/a&gt; (“&lt;a href=&quot;https://stewartvarner.com/2016/01/what-dh-could-be/&quot;&gt;What DH Could Be&lt;/a&gt;”) for changing how I present on and define DH. The &lt;a href=&quot;http://hawksey.info/tagsexplorer/arc.html?key=1zlUFubccXY7Pekfs0bXgxzIbNalJPGvU_SJIlmLTI50&amp;amp;gid=400689247&quot;&gt;#DHdiversity&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/mydhis&quot;&gt;#MyDHis&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/whatifdh2017&quot;&gt;#WhatIfDH&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://transformdh.org/&quot;&gt;#TransformDH&lt;/a&gt; DHers are also awesome and have helped me be a better DHer and person.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;P.S. I can’t find the original creator of the GIF on my first slide (museum gallery with framed loading icons). Let me know if you know—I’d like to credit them!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jul 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/2016/07/21/dlf-digital-humanities-what-why-how</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2016/07/21/dlf-digital-humanities-what-why-how</guid>
        
        <category>digital-humanities</category>
        
        <category>advice-tutorial</category>
        
        <category>best</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Infinite Ulysses in the New York Times and other recent DH activity</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Lots of DH stuff cooking lately:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.infiniteulysses.com&quot;&gt;Infinite Ulysses&lt;/a&gt; project was mentioned and linked in the &lt;em&gt;The New York Times&lt;/em&gt;! The piece, by J.D. Biersdorfer, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/2016/07/17/books/review/cant-get-through-ulysses-digital-help-is-on-the-way.html&quot;&gt;appeared online July 13, 2016 as “Can’t Get Through ‘Ulysses’? Digital Help Is on the Way”&lt;/a&gt; and in print on Sunday, July 17, 2016 in the “Sunday Book Review” section of the paper under the headline “Virtual Odyssey”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I joined &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://programminghistorian.org/&quot;&gt;The Programming Historian&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; editorial team as an editor and also ombudsperson. &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://programminghistorian.org/&quot;&gt;The Programming Historian&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; is an online, peer-reviewed, novice-friendly platform for humanities scholars wishing to learn digital methods and tools. (You might remember I published a lesson, “&lt;a href=&quot;http://programminghistorian.org/lessons/building-static-sites-with-jekyll-github-pages&quot;&gt;Building a static website with Jekyll and GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt;”, with &lt;em&gt;PH&lt;/em&gt; earlier this year.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll be presenting to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.diglib.org/&quot;&gt;Digital Library Federation&lt;/a&gt; (DLF) &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.diglib.org/groups/e-research-network/&quot;&gt;eResearch Network&lt;/a&gt; as their DH speaker in a six-talk series on digital library research and data management practice, on July 20th. I’ll cover what digital humanities is, why it can be good for you and your institution, and how to get started in DH. The slides and talk video should go online shortly after.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The DH 2016 conference just finished up (check out &lt;a href=&quot;http://hawksey.info/tagsexplorer/arc.html?key=1zlUFubccXY7Pekfs0bXgxzIbNalJPGvU_SJIlmLTI50&amp;amp;gid=400689247&quot;&gt;the #DHdiversity tweets&lt;/a&gt; especially), so incoming new ACH executive officers Scott Weingart, Micki Kaufman, and I have begun our 2016-2020 terms, along with Jen Guiliano as the new ACH president 2016-2018 and Matt Gold as the new vice-president 2016-2018 and 2018-2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/NYTimesUlysses.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of digital Ulysses article on New York Times online front page&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/NYTimesUlysses2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of digital Ulysses article in New York Times mentioning and linking to Infinite Ulysses&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jul 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/2016/07/15/digital-humanities-update-infinite-ulysses-new-york-times</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2016/07/15/digital-humanities-update-infinite-ulysses-new-york-times</guid>
        
        <category>digital-humanities</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How the Digital Humanities uses Slack to support and build a geographically dispersed intellectual community</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I was invited to write a piece on the Digital Humanities Slack for the London School of Economics blog (&lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.lse.ac.uk/impactofsocialsciences/2016/07/13/using-slack-to-support-a-geographically-dispersed-community/&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;), and I’m crossposting it here.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m a member of the digital humanities (DH) community—we’re builders, tech users, teachers, and thinkers around digital tools exploring literature, history, and other cultural heritage fields (stuff like &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/uncategorized/preserving-reconstructing-teaching-in-3d/&quot;&gt;3D printing for archaeology&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://viraltexts.org/&quot;&gt;text analysis of historical memes in newspapers&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.InfiniteUlysses.com&quot;&gt;interfaces that let readers interpret and discuss challenging novels&lt;/a&gt;). One of the more recent ways we communicate is via a Digital Humanities Slack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slack is a digital platform (web or desktop/mobile app) much like a set of chatrooms for a team of people: you can chat in real-time, and create ongoing “channels” (chatrooms) around specific themes or topics (&lt;a href=&quot;https://get.slack.help/hc/en-us/articles/218080037-Getting-started-for-new-users&quot;&gt;here’s a good overview of what Slack is/how to use it&lt;/a&gt;). Slack is a bit different from chatting you might have done in the past, in that it’s set up to integrate with a variety of web services that help in project management, website monitoring, social media, and other needs of business teams. Because Slack is built with limited teams from inside one business in mind, we needed to use &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/dherbst/slack-invite-script&quot;&gt;Darrel Herbst’s Slack invite script&lt;/a&gt; to instead allow anyone to sign up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Digital Humanities Slack is open to anyone with a curiosity about DH and/or related interests (e.g. digital libraries, museums, and archives)—those interested just visit &lt;a href=&quot;http://tinyurl.com/DHslack&quot;&gt;tinyurl.com/DHslack&lt;/a&gt; to join. Absolutely no DH expertise is required, and we have several specific channels devoted to DH beginners, students, job seekers, and asking all kinds of DHy questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The DH Slack was created in October 2015 after a suggestion from Ed Summers, and was built by the channel creation and chatting of its members. Nine months later (as of July 6, 2016), we have:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;700 members (84% of which have used the Slack over the past two weeks)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;67 “channels” (chat rooms devoted to specific topics)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;21.3k messages sent&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;About 60% of messages are on public channels, with the other 40% being DMs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;180 files (shared code, documents, screenshots…) have been shared and stored on the Slack&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Loading screen messages that quote definitions of DH from a variety of practitioners (thanks to Matthew Lincoln), and when someone types “what is the digital humanities”, a bot responds by pointing you to the 800+ definitions for DH over at &lt;a href=&quot;http://whatisdigitalhumanities.com&quot;&gt;whatisdigitalhumanities.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Channels (chat rooms) are user-created, and the names of channels are represented with a pound sign and no spaces (#DHteaching). The current channels cover&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;socializing and academic community information (e.g. #hottopic for chatting about current DH issues like the latest LARB interview, and channels to share upcoming conferences and job opportunities)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;regions and languages (e.g. a Spanish-language channel, channels for DHers in Baltimore, the Bay Area, and Tennessee)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;academic fields (e.g. people working in libraries, museums, publishing, and environmental humanities)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;getting started in the digital humanities (e.g. a place to ask for tutorials to learn specific skills, a channel for talking about what being a DH student is like)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;specific DH methods and practices (e.g. visualization, linked open data, coding, crowdsourcing, machine learning, teaching DH)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;plus a #meta channel to discuss the DH Slack community itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slack is a comparatively new platform for DHers, who have been blogging and using Facebook and Twitter as part of their intellectual life almost since those platforms began. For example, I use Twitter to share blog posts on my in-progress work and teaching; hear about others’ blog posts, projects, and publications; discover potential project collaborators and mentors (including people who don’t work in academia); and as a backchannel to share and discuss conference presentations in real-time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re still figuring out how Slack can be useful: Can it allow different kinds of conversations than Twitter? Can we use it to teach and support people interested in DH who don’t have mentors geographically near them, or who aren’t inside academia? Like Twitter, Slack allows coexisting formal use (posting job opportunities, discussing theories) with informal socializing (which is really part of professional work, since it lays good foundations for future collaboration and problem-solving). Interesting uses of the DH Slack I’ve seen so far include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A user creating a channel around their specific research interests, and chatting in that channel as a sort of live-blog of the different approaches they’re trying and how they address issues as they arise (other Slack members can read or ask questions in the channel, too)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If an interesting discussion on Twitter starts to feel stifled or miscommunicated because of Twitter’s size constraints, moving the conversation to the DH Slack allows more freedom while also keeping the conversation semi-public (it’s more public than moving to an email conversation, but anyone wanting to follow the conversation does need to join the DH Slack first)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mentoring and socializing: I’ve seen Slack members walk each other through fixing a coding bug or suggest lesson plans, and we use the #weeklies channel for weekly sharing around a fun theme (e.g. what’s a book that changed your way of thinking?)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A user sharing a digital humanities method tutorial, then offering to be available on the DH Slack for a certain evening to answer any questions about the tutorial (with the idea that people are encouraged to try working through the tutorial, knowing they will have help if they get stuck or have a question)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve collectively discussed the design of our community, deciding by lazy consensus issues like whether we should keep a permanent archive of all messages sent on the Slack, or keep things ephemeral (check out &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2016/07/06/digital-humanities-slack-community-design&quot;&gt;this blog post&lt;/a&gt; for a discussion and more examples of that collective community design). &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/amandavisconti/DHslack/blob/master/CodeOfConduct.md&quot;&gt;Our evolving code of conduct lives here&lt;/a&gt;, and Slack members are encouraged to suggest additions or changes via #meta. We’re dedicated to a harassment-free experience for everyone, with a particular reminder that dismissing or belittling lack of DH, tech, or other experience (e.g. answering questions with links to Let Me Google That For You) is not allowed. This code helps us set expectations for behavior and promote the Slack as a safe and welcoming space for everyone. With the code and open community design discussion in place, we’re finding that Slack works pretty well at supporting a broad, geographically dispersed intellectual community!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 13 Jul 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/2016/07/13/digital-humanities-slack-london-school-economics</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2016/07/13/digital-humanities-slack-london-school-economics</guid>
        
        <category>digital-humanities</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Digital Humanities Slack &amp; Community Design</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Update 7/7/2016: The “message archive” section has been updated to reflect a Slack feature pointed out by Jeff Godin—thanks, Jeff!.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Come join the Digital Humanities Slack, a set of DHy chatrooms! (Visit &lt;a href=&quot;http://tinyurl.com/DHslack&quot;&gt;tinyurl.com/DHslack&lt;/a&gt; to join.) &lt;strong&gt;We are open to anyone&lt;/strong&gt; with a curiosity about DH and/or related interests (e.g. digital libraries, museums, and archives). Absolutely no expertise needed, and we have several specific chat rooms (called “channels” on Slack) devoted to DH beginners, students, job seekers, and asking all kinds of DHy and digital methods questions. (&lt;a href=&quot;https://get.slack.help/hc/en-us/articles/218080037-Getting-started-for-new-users&quot;&gt;Here’s a good overview of what Slack is/how to use it&lt;/a&gt;. I’m happy to answer questions about how to use Slack or what it is via &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.twitter.com/literature_geek&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;&amp;#109;&amp;#097;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;:&amp;#097;&amp;#118;&amp;#105;&amp;#115;&amp;#099;&amp;#111;&amp;#110;&amp;#116;&amp;#064;&amp;#112;&amp;#117;&amp;#114;&amp;#100;&amp;#117;&amp;#101;&amp;#046;&amp;#101;&amp;#100;&amp;#117;&quot;&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;, too.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dh-slack-stats&quot;&gt;DH Slack stats&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The DH Slack was created in October 2015 after a suggestion from Ed Summers, and was built by the channel creation and chatting of its members. Nine months later (as of July 6, 2016), we have:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;700 members (84% of which have used the Slack over the past two weeks)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;67 “channels” (chat rooms devoted to specific topics)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;21.3k messages sent&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;About 60% of messages are on public channels, with the other 40% being DMs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;180 files (shared code, documents, screenshots…) have been shared and stored on the Slack&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Matthew Lincoln set up Slack loading screen messages to quote definitions of DH from a variety of practitioners! And when someone types “what is the digital humanities”, a bot should respond by pointing you to the 800+ definitions over at &lt;a href=&quot;http://whatisdigitalhumanities.com&quot;&gt;whatisdigitalhumanities.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Channels (chat rooms) are Slack user-created, and the names of channels are represented with a pound sign and no space (#wordlefans). The current channels include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Socializing and community info:&lt;/strong&gt; #introductions (share a little about your DH interests and what you do, or let people know about a new channel you created), #conferences, #off-topic (water cooler space for non-DHy chat and GIFs), #jobs, #announcements (events, CFPs, new projects), #hottopic (chat about current general DH issues, like that LARB piece…), #reading (share recent DH and entertainment reading and discuss books), #weeklies (weekly fun themes/survey questions)&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Regional and language channels:&lt;/strong&gt; #dh-california, #dh_humanidadesdigital, #dh-tennessee, #dh-bay-area, #dh-baltimore&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fields:&lt;/strong&gt; #libraries, #dh-archives, #museums, #publichistory, #arthistory, #envirohumanities, #mediastudies, #elit, #publishing, #openaccess, #copyright&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Getting started:&lt;/strong&gt; #DHanswers (both pulls from the DH Q&amp;amp;A site, and a space for asking new questions), #students (talk about the experience of being a student, doing DH as a student…), #beginners (welcoming space for those just getting started in DH), #tutorialplease (ask for pointers to good tutorials on something you want to learn) and #tutorials (share useful tutorials as you run across them)&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Specific DH methods and practices:&lt;/strong&gt; #methodology, #visualization, #data-sharing, #annotation (plus a channel specifically about #hypothes-is annotation), #geospatial, #networks, #coding, #design, #linkeddata, #bots, #crowdsourcing, #gaming, #linux, #machinelearning, #databases, #physcomp, #topicmodel, #bibliography, #textencoding, #texthacking, #textanalysis, #datacuration, #philosophy, #simulation, #music, #sound, #3dscholarship, #codesnippets&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Teaching/learning:&lt;/strong&gt; #teachingDH, #digitalpedagogy, #programminghistorian (for discussions around the DH tutorial website)&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And #meta&lt;/strong&gt; (to discuss the DH Slack itself)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;community-design-decisions&quot;&gt;Community design decisions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slack is a comparatively new platform (vs. Twitter), so DHers are still figuring out how it can be useful and how to best run the DH Slack. Anyone can join the DH Slack (&lt;a href=&quot;http://tinyurl.com/DHslack&quot;&gt;tinyurl.com/DHslack&lt;/a&gt;) and then visit the #meta channel to participate in decisions about our community design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you to everyone who shared thoughts on improving the DH Slack on the Slack, via email, or on Twitter, including DH Slack members Sam Abrams, Kristen Mapes, Matthew Lincoln, Ed Summers, Alan G. Pike, Liz Lorang, Hyperverses, timfinnegan, Jeremy Throne, Brandon Locke, Lincoln Mullen, Brian Croxall, Jeff Godin, and Micah Vandegrift, and others via Twitter and email.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;tl;dr&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;After community discussion, we’re keeping the DH Slack as ephemeral (no longterm archive of all messages) and not allowing people who aren’t signed into the Slack to read it. I’d be happy to chat with and amplify the platform of anyone who wants to make a DH Slack alternative that does either/both of these things, and I agree that it would be nice to have a place where Twitter conversations could be comfortably and publicly expanded (e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;http://Hypothes.is&quot;&gt;Hypothes.is&lt;/a&gt; annotation?)—it’s just that the place to do that right now isn’t the DH Slack.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below are some of the issues we’ve been thinking through. I’ve heard reasonable arguments for public readability and/or archiving from people who haven’t been using the Slack. Hearing from non-Slacker users is good, since we want to be careful about decisions that deter others from joining; on the other hand, submitting feedback after using this Slack shows both an understanding of how people have been using it, and buy-in to the outcome of these decisions. (That’s what my thinking has been in weighing input from inside and outside the Slack.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Code of conduct&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/amandavisconti/DHslack/blob/master/CodeOfConduct.md&quot;&gt;Our evolving code of conduct lives here&lt;/a&gt;, and Slack members are encouraged to suggest additions or changes via #meta. To summarize, we’re dedicated to a harassment-free experience for everyone, with a particular reminder that dismissing or belittling lack of DH, tech, or other experience (e.g. answering questions with links to Let Me Google That For You) is not allowed. We provide a list with specific examples of what constitutes harassment and a statement on handling of “reverse-isms”. &lt;em&gt;Update:&lt;/em&gt; we’re also looking at a statement on how to approach using screenshots or exports of the Slack for research use or for discussion outside the Slack (see “Message archive” update below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Public reading.&lt;/strong&gt; Thanks to Sava Saheli for pointing out that the problem with moving unwieldy Twitter conversations to the DH Slack is that this adds a barrier to public reading not present on Twitter (anyone can sign up for the DH Slack and start using it right away, but you do need to sign up and know how to navigate Slack).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both Slack and the self-hosted OS Slack alternative Mattermost (that I’ll discuss below) don’t allow non-signed-in (public) reading. Our workaround would be &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mdlincoln/jekyll-slack&quot;&gt;Matthew Lincoln’s nice solution for exporting Slack messages to a GitHub Pages-hosted Jekyll website&lt;/a&gt;. This would require someone to remember to periodically manually export the Slack’s messages and upload them to GitHub, and I’m not sure if our 10k message limit would cause a problem (each export would be missing earlier messages, so new exports to GitHub might overwrite old ones, meaning older messages would disappear from the public site–insofar as anything disappears from the web given Internet Archive, screenshots, etc.). One option would be to only export certain channels that are visibly marked as public-readable, rather than exporting the entire DH Slack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We discussed whether allowing public reading this way would make people more or less comfortable using the DH Slack, reaching out both on the DH Slack to active users, and on Twitter to inactive users and people who haven’t joined the DH Slack. I heard more people as neutral or against making any of the DH Slack publicly readable this way, making me think we shouldn’t pursue it for now. A twice-cited reason was that a code of conduct is useful when applied not just to people writing on the Slack, but to people reading it as well; if only signed-in people can read the DH Slack, then we can block anyone who harasses from continuing to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Message archive.&lt;/strong&gt; We’re at 21.3k Slack messages, and Slack limits its free plan users to seeing the most recent 10k messages. We discussed whether we should pursue a plan that gives us access to the full archive of messages (or come up with a hack to preserve these on our own, like Matthew Lincoln’s solution discussed above). I heard more people who were neutral or against doing this, so we won’t do it. One cited reason was that ephemerality was freeing: people tend to use the Slack as a place for informal chat, memes, and gifs as well as scholarship, and knowing you’re on the record for whatever you say has a chilling effect on that use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Update 7/7/2016:&lt;/em&gt; Jeff Godin pointed out that on our free Slack plan, although no one can access messages older than the most recent 10k via the Slack or admin dashboard, people with admin privileges &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; export the Slack as a JSON file and that file will include all messages since the beginning of the Slack (does not include private group history or files, direct message history or files, edit and deletion logs). The JSON isn’t super-friendly to read, but I’ll bet a good number of DHers are familiar with transforming it into something easily human-readable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We already knew that we can’t have a truly ephemeral space because of screenshots, etc., but anyone who has changed feelings because of this discovery is invited to share them. Also, I started a conversation on #meta about how this knowledge might be reflected in our code of conduct. I’m leaning toward: if you’re going to share a snapshot of a conversation on the Slack, you must ask anyone whose username is shown first and receive permission from them (including honoring if they only give permission if you black out their username). For research/public discussion use of the Slack message export, you should ask in the #meta channel and wait to get an explicit okay from an admin who has had time to synthesize responses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Slack alternative?&lt;/strong&gt; Micki Kaufman suggested &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mattermost&quot;&gt;Mattermost&lt;/a&gt; as a Slack alternative: Mattermost is open-source, not run by a for-profit company, self-hosted, and has a tool to import users from Slack. I think this is a really promising platform, and if we were back in October I’d probably have tried it first before Slack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a couple reasons, we’re not moving the DH Slack to Mattermost—but anyone is welcomed to set up their own Mattermost install on their servers and create a DH community. I’d happily advertise such as platform on the DH Slack! One reason we’re not moving right now is buy-in: people already use Slack for other teams (work, participating in project discussions like &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/1Wk0JdF2Cty2VHMqpf_QlJXVKQdUtfeeFhaYRben3qaM/viewform&quot;&gt;Documenting the Now’s awesome chatroom around social media archiving ethics&lt;/a&gt;) and can move between those and the DH Slack in the same app, instead of having an additional platform open. We’re at 700 members, so although the Mattermost user import tool sounds very useful, we’d need to secure permission and interest from our users to move to that platform, and when this possibility was raised, no one was interested in moving. Someone would also need to provide the web hosting and be willing to maintain and upgrade the installation longterm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DH scholarly organization oversight?&lt;/strong&gt; We originally approached a DH scholarly organization about sponsoring the DH Slack because doing so would let us use Slack’s free non-profit plan, which gives you access to a permanent archive of all your Slack’s messages (the free Slack plan we’re using now only gives you access to the last 10k messages, although it doesn’t delete the hidden messages—you can get access back by upgrading your plan). Just paying for a Slack plan (even with the education discount) is cost-prohibitive as cost is calculated by number of users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve decided to no longer seek sponsorship for the Slack non-profit plan, but we’re still discussing other ways the DH scholarly organization might sponsor or collaborate with the DH Slack. The way Slack forces one person with super admin privileges to “own” a Slack team is weird and undemocratic in our case, when this Slack exists and thrives because of all its members. I think it would still be worth considering a DH scholarly organization being involved just to help with moderation, and to prevent my using my admin privileges to replace all messages with Hamilton memes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/hamiltonisawesome.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Facebook post: &amp;quot;Washington: we are outgunned! outmanned! Hamilton: I have 3 friends if that helps&amp;quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seriously, though, it isn’t good for one person to control something with so many members (even assuming my good intentions and trying to mitigate personal biases, I could e.g. be hit by a bus). DH scholarly organization involvement could just mean the organization would let members know about the Slack, but another option could be having a couple people from the organization (possibly from its communications committee) who would explicitly commit to helping with moderation/code of conduct issues if they arise. We might even switch the Slack “owner” to an account that several explicit moderators could use, instead of it just being my personal account, so the community can continue without resting on a single person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contribute:&lt;/strong&gt; I’ve been trying to synthesize the discussions around these issues, and it’s very possible we’re missing some issues or that my biases are making me interpret people’s responses wrong. Please feel free to tell me so via &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.twitter.com/literature_geek&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;&amp;#109;&amp;#097;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;:&amp;#097;&amp;#118;&amp;#105;&amp;#115;&amp;#099;&amp;#111;&amp;#110;&amp;#116;&amp;#064;&amp;#112;&amp;#117;&amp;#114;&amp;#100;&amp;#117;&amp;#101;&amp;#046;&amp;#101;&amp;#100;&amp;#117;&quot;&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;—your name won’t be shared with anyone unless you want it to be. Or if you disagree or think of more reasons why we should reconsider these choices, please let me know! Finally, this isn’t a binding decision—we can definitely revisit these questions at any time in the future as issues arise or the Slack evolves.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jul 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/2016/07/06/digital-humanities-slack-community-design</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2016/07/06/digital-humanities-slack-community-design</guid>
        
        <category>digital-humanities</category>
        
        <category>best</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Digital Humanities Dissertation Defense Talk</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;http://digitalhumanitiesnow.org/2016/06/digital-humanities-dissertation-defense-talk/&quot;&gt;DH Now Editors’ Choice post&lt;/a&gt;! (See &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/tag/dh-now/&quot;&gt;this page&lt;/a&gt; for more Literature Geek posts highlighted by DH Now.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2016/06/14/digital-humanities-dissertation-defense-advice&quot;&gt;made a few comments about the dissertation defense process in a previous blog post&lt;/a&gt;, and here I’ll blog the actual defense talk. I’m even resisting the urge to edit and improve (although I’ve learned a lot about slide design and public speaking in the past year…). So, this post is a good representation of the actual defense talk I gave on April 14, 2015. If you’ve seen me present on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.infiniteulysses.com&quot;&gt;Infinite Ulysses&lt;/a&gt; in the past year, some pieces of this may be familiar…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that I didn’t go back into the talk text and insert full citations, but anything I mention can be found in the bibliography of my dissertation whitepaper at &lt;a href=&quot;http://dr.amandavisconti.com&quot;&gt;dr.amandavisconti.com&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;http://dr.amandavisconti.com&quot;&gt;Dr.AmandaVisconti.com&lt;/a&gt; is also the &lt;strong&gt;actual dissertation&lt;/strong&gt;, if you’d like to learn more about the full project (it is not the website for the dissertation—it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; the dissertation!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(If you didn’t see &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2016/06/14/digital-humanities-dissertation-defense-advice&quot;&gt;the previous post&lt;/a&gt;: I recently realized that although &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/tag/dissertation/&quot;&gt;I thoroughly blogged my dissertation (almost 40 blog posts)&lt;/a&gt; and wrote &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2015/05/09/dissertationdefended&quot;&gt;a post after successfully defending the dissertation in April 2015&lt;/a&gt;, I never blogged my actual defense talk. In keeping with &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2016/02/28/DHjobtalk&quot;&gt;blogging the job talk&lt;/a&gt; that took me into my current job, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/tag/grad-advice/&quot;&gt;other DH/grad student advice&lt;/a&gt;, I am now rectifying this oversight!)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-dh-defense-talk&quot;&gt;The DH defense talk&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started my slides early so that this slide was on the screen before the defense began; when I give invited talks or conference presentations, I make a credits list my last slide instead, so it can stay up during Q&amp;amp;A (I also thank a few key supporters by name: my site users and testers, my dissertation advisor and committee, Michael Widner, and MITH/UMD). Note that any stats about Infinite Ulysses site use were from before the site had surprising publicity via Hacker News (the morning after my defense, so I include those stats in the first month of open beta stats).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/defense-slides/defense-slides.001.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of presentation slide from the dissertation defense&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here’s the title slide! (That’s the full title of my dissertation.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/defense-slides/defense-slides.002.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of presentation slide from the dissertation defense&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In one of my &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zotero.org/amandavisconti/items/itemKey/4F5DJ2GB/q/taylor&quot;&gt;very favorite works on textual scholarship&lt;/a&gt;, scholarly editor Gary Taylor asks, “How can you love a work, if you don’t know it? How can you know it, if you can’t get near it? How can you get near it, without editors?” Scholarly editors are integral to the continuum that keeps the stories of the past available to and understood by the present—but in Taylor’s formulation, the “you” is just as important: that public of readers beyond the academy, whose interest keeps the humanities alive and relevant. What if we build a digital edition and invite everyone to participate in its use? My dissertation considered this question by creating and testing the Infinite Ulysses digital edition with both readers from inside and outside the academy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/defense-slides/defense-slides.003.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of presentation slide from the dissertation defense&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In studying what follows from a participatory digital edition, I’ve grouped my research into three groups of inquiry:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;First, questions about making the humanities more public and more participatory (that is, welcoming public participation, in addition to making resources theoretically publicly available). How can we design digital editions that are not just public, but invite and assist participation in the scholarly love of a text?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My second set of questions focused on the design of digital editions, using Bethany Nowviskie’s idea of edition “interfacing” to do critical textual scholarship work through design, that is different from textual editing tasks. If we design editions for the public, how do we design to handle an influx of readers and annotations on texts (questions of moderation, curation, and personalization)? And what might we learn about digital editions and their texts from the accompanying influx of site use data?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My third set of questions stem from looking at Infinite Ulysses and asking, “is this an edition?” I considered whether we could separate the values of textual scholarship, from the common embodiments of these values. How might this clarification help us imagine new types of digital edition?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My presentation today will start by describing my project’s methods and format, offer some textual scholarship and digital humanities precedents for critical design and code work, and provide a brief tour of the Infinite Ulysses digital edition. I’ll also provide an overview of this project’s interventions and next steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/defense-slides/defense-slides.004.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of presentation slide from the dissertation defense&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Textual scholar Morris Eaves conceives of editions not just as vessels for textual content, but also as “problem-solving mechanisms”. The problem of designing participatory digital editions was best addressed by designing, building, and testing real use of a digital edition. Analytical discussion took the form of research blogging throughout the course of the project, averaging out to about one post a month for the last three years. Analytical discussion of the project was also performed through a whitepaper authored near the end of the project; where the prospectus was a briefing for the project, with a lit review and justification of the project’s exigence, the whitepaper served as a debriefing, a place to consider what was learned and what my next research steps should be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/defense-slides/defense-slides.005.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of presentation slide from the dissertation defense&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In textual scholarship, there’s a history of embodying arguments both about specific texts, and about how edition interfaces function. Editing has always intertwined theory and embodied practice. Arguments about which document (or patchwork of documents) best represents the ideal of a text, for example, were practically realized through editions of specific texts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see an example of textual arguments being made through textual interfaces up on the screen. On the left is a page from the print variorum edition of Darwin’s On the Origin of Species. Between the first and sixth editions, the word count went up by 40,000 words. This is an edition that values giving the reader access, to the full picture of the text in all its variations. It is unpleasant to read, but it’s not really intended to be read, but for researchers to focus on changes to a specific section of the text (searching rather than browsing).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the right, is a static screenshot of Ben Fry’s animated visualization of these changes in the text over time. If you visit his site, you can see the visualization shift, as new words are added or taken away from different sections over time, and you can also zoom in and read the text at any stage of its development. This is a textual interface that values awareness of the changing shape of the whole text over time (browsing rather than searching).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/defense-slides/defense-slides.006.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of presentation slide from the dissertation defense&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Design experiments aren’t a new tactic in textual scholarship. The typographic and spatial innovations of scholarly editor Teena Rochfort Smith’s 1883 &lt;em&gt;Four-Text ‘Hamlet’ in Parallel Columns&lt;/em&gt; offer one example of experimentation, that focused on editions as a form. Smith intended this prototype to provide several transcriptions of Hamlet’s quartos, as well as her own edition of the play, side-by-side. The edition employed six varieties of typeface, four inks, three kinds of underlining, and daggers, asterisks, and other symbols to call out the presence and extent of variance. Like the Darwin print variorum, this edition values giving the reader access to a fuller picture of the text in all its variations, but this edition also values its user being able to access each work fully—something made possible by the parallel columns and notation, instead of a single column of inline variants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This prototype would have been nearly impossible to typeset and print in 1883. Smith worked toward a simpler final version of the edition after circulating this prototype. This suggests Smith’s initial focus was on an experiment with the form of a prototyped edition, rather than a fully realized edition with a focus on its text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/defense-slides/defense-slides.007.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of presentation slide from the dissertation defense&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A recent example of text-specific critical design is seen in Jeffrey Masten’s edition &lt;em&gt;A/The Old Law&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the left we have a page from the EEBO scan of the early modern Middleton Rowley play, and on the right we have one of the pages as edited by Masten. He argues that for texts like this one, multiple readings of single words were the historical reality, due to puns, bad printing, and non-standardized spelling. Masten views this play as very much about multiple possible interpretations of laws legal, moral, and Biblical. He reflects this emphasis in print design by arbitrarily flipping between the use of side and footnotes, throughout the pages of his edition. Because he also includes his textual commentary in these notes, this randomizing makes it difficult for the reader to &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; read the “real” text of the play, or to ignore reading about these possible variants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/defense-slides/defense-slides.008.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of presentation slide from the dissertation defense&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m most interested in experiments that are somewhat text-agnostic—that have a focus on what &lt;em&gt;editions&lt;/em&gt; can do, not what &lt;em&gt;an edition&lt;/em&gt; can do for &lt;em&gt;a specific text&lt;/em&gt;. Alan Galey’s Visualizing Variation coding project is another recent example of textual experimentation, that focuses on edition form over any one text. His code set is a scholarly response, to the early modern experience of reading, when spellings varied wildly, and a reader was accustomed to holding multiple possible meanings for badly printed or ambiguously spelled words in their mind at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, his “Animated Variants” code cycles which word to display in the reading text, for contended words such as Hamlet’s sallied/solid/sullied, so that the reader isn’t biased by a word’s placement in the main text, rather than in the footnotes. By experimenting with digital means of approximating this historical experience, Galey moves theorists past discussing that this different experience of texts occurred. Instead, scholars can now respond to an actual participation in that historical experience. Galey’s coded textual experiments are themselves critical arguments about edition design. His example of a project where the principal investigator is also the lead programmer was a helpful model for my coding work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/defense-slides/defense-slides.009.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of presentation slide from the dissertation defense&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve seen how textual scholarship uses edition design experiments, to develop interpretive interfaces. I’d like to switch now to discussing how those edition interfaces are used, when exposed to public readers and researchers.
Lindsey Thomas notes that making something freely available online does not necessarily guarantee that thing is public, or that it will be used as a public resource. It isn’t enough to make something theoretically publicly accessible to advance a public humanities. We need to prioritize accessibility, inclusion, and education, if we want to create a real conversation among academics and the public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/defense-slides/defense-slides.010.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of presentation slide from the dissertation defense&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My project both designed for participation by public readers, and used participatory design by incorporating users’ feedback during the design process. In the world of textual scholarship, my edition has precedents in digital editions that allowed site visitors to transcribe, mark up, and annotate texts. The Shelley-Godwin Archive has worked toward public participation, envisioning an eventual “work-site for scholars, students, and the general public” with “contributions in the form of transcriptions, corrections, and annotations”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see the valuing of participation from all levels of expertise even in the beta site, where a stoplight icon visually signals the reliability of a text’s transcription, allowing non-expert markup and transcription to be made public more quickly. The New York Public Library’s &lt;em&gt;Candide 2.0&lt;/em&gt; offered public annotation alongside the novel: stating “the margin is a public space where readers can congregate, discuss and debate the book together, in intimate proximity to the text”. Participation privileges developed in stages: commissioned annotators seeded the edition with expert commentary, after which the edition was opened to public annotation for a trial period. The London Lives project similarly used a graded approach to participation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/defense-slides/defense-slides.011.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of presentation slide from the dissertation defense&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve distilled my review of pertinent literature into several calls for further work:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We need models for conducting and analyzing user studies in the digital humanities and textual studies.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We need digital editions that are both public and participatory. Designing and coding participatory digital editions lets textual scholars serve more than one of the field’s intellectual values: &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt; our mandate as humanists to preserve and renew the relevance of past culture, &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; the focus on more intimate knowledge of texts via edition-building and the interpretive work that entails.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What a digital Ulysses would do has been theorized; recent changes to the text’s digital availability mean we now need to build and test those theories.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll next give you a brief tour of the edition I created in response to these calls to action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/defense-slides/defense-slides.012.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of presentation slide from the dissertation defense&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the current front page of the edition. The images give a high level tour of the edition’s features: you can highlight parts of the book and annotate those highlights; read others’ annotations; and personalize what annotations you see to your background, interests, and needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/defense-slides/defense-slides.013.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of presentation slide from the dissertation defense&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For an allusion to Hamlet, an annotator might explain the reference and also tag the annotation with tags like “meaning” (a tag we’ve been using to call out answers to “what does this mean?”) as well as tags like “Shakespeare”, “Hamlet”, and “intertextuality”. Other popular tags mark if an annotation translates a specific language, refers to a specific author or book or to Joyce’s biography, or relates to a topic such as Modernist style, colonialism, or religion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/defense-slides/defense-slides.014.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of presentation slide from the dissertation defense&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Readers click on highlighted text to see any annotations tied to that highlight; these annotations appear in the sidebar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/defense-slides/defense-slides.015.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of presentation slide from the dissertation defense&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each annotation on the text can receive either one upvote or one downvote from each reader. Annotation votes accrue to the user who authored those annotations, so that helpfulness and credibility of annotators can also be very roughly assessed. These votes allow readers to prioritize what annotations they are shown, when a word or phrase has multiple annotations. For example, a reader can choose to see the top-rated annotations first, or the newest annotations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Readers can also favorite annotations to save them into a personal list; I hope to eventually tie this feature into the filtering system so that users can share links to “custom” editions only showing their curated annotations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/defense-slides/defense-slides.016.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of presentation slide from the dissertation defense&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Readers can filter annotations to only display annotations dealing with areas of interest (e.g. if you’re interested in references to Shakespeare’s plays). Readers can also filter to only display annotations authored by certain users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/defense-slides/defense-slides.017.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of presentation slide from the dissertation defense&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The edition, after being open in beta or testing mode about one month, has a couple hundred user accounts (367 on Sunday) and a couple hundred annotations (416 on Sunday) (&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Post-defense note: when I quote the first month of open beta stats in my talks, the numbers are much, much higher: that’s because Infinite Ulysses made the Daily Top 20 on Hacker News the morning after my defense, bringing in thousands of site visitors&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The number of those user accounts who are actually actively annotating while reading is very low so far. There were two fairly active users on the site besides myself (they added 60 and 19 annotations), with 10 users authoring 5 or more annotations, 20 users authoring 2 or more annotations, and 32 site users authoring at least 1 annotation. All but 4 of those 29 annotators are people I’d never met before. I expect site activity to pick up as more of the book is annotated, and several teachers are already planning to use the site with classes this summer and fall. It’s also worth noting that the first two chapters of the book are fairly thickly annotated by me already (around 240 annotations), so new readers might not have felt they had as much to add.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/defense-slides/defense-slides.018.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of presentation slide from the dissertation defense&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of code, my biggest intervention was to create a module that ties the highlighting of text from the Annotator tool, into how Drupal lets you add metadata to, filter, and sort units of content such as annotations. These social features, filtering, and sorting addressed a need already present even at the level of a few hundreds readers on the site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most-annotated page on the site after four weeks of the open beta had 45 annotations, with the next ten most-annotated pages each having between 10 and 25 annotations per page. Even at the level of an edition just beginning to see use, there are already too many annotations per page for most readers; we already need a way to filter out the distraction of the annotations that don’t fit our interests. In particular, the site has been read by both first-time readers of the novel and professors who have taught the text; sorting and filtering helps get the appropriate granularity of annotation to each reader, whether that’s “what does this word mean?” or “how does this dialogue fit into what we know about Joyce’s opinions on Irish politics?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/defense-slides/defense-slides.019.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of presentation slide from the dissertation defense&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Infinite Ulysses and the dissertational project around it modeled small but actionable changes to the fields of the digital humanities and textual scholarship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the area of participatory projects, Infinite Ulysses provided an example of a small but eager audience for a participatory digital humanities project; although the data gathered on site visits is early, there were over 2000 sessions of site use and over 1500 unique site visitors during this first month of open testing. The code and design work that allows textual annotations to be curated and moderated are being tested on at least two other digital editions (the Shelley-Godwin Archive and Romantic Circles); further work toward packaging and documenting the code will allow for digital humanists with less technical expertise to set up similar participatory annotation projects for their own texts, theories, and testing. Early site use data suggests that the site’s design and functionalities do represent a working route, for digital editions to support public participation, through personalization of annotations to reader and researcher needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the area of meaningful crowdsourcing, Infinite Ulysses provided a modest example of public digital edition visitors adding value to a text, through contextualizing and interpretive annotations over a trial month. The project also outlined a number of ways digital humanities researchers may use non-critical participation to advance scholarly knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the area of edition design and data, Infinite Ulysses experimented with digital edition editorial statements by providing a detailed explanation of how scholarly values were manifested through specific instances of project design and code. Preliminary data gathering and analysis provided support and pointed out flaws in my digital edition design, while also providing text-agnostic knowledge about user testing methods for participatory digital editions, that can be used by other textual scholars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the area of textual scholarship field boundaries, I’ve explored scholarly textual artifacts that draw on the values and skills of textual scholarship, without necessarily looking like a scholarly edition. By distilling textual scholarship values from their common embodiments and saving the term “scholarly edition” for a very specific type of edition, we can let the term “edition” invite broader types of textual projects that still hold true to textual scholarship values. Re-examining core assumptions about technologies like the edition can open new possibilities for humanities knowledge, and it can also help edition reviewers provide more constructive critique that better fits individual digital editions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/defense-slides/defense-slides.020.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of presentation slide from the dissertation defense&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New questions, not unexpectedly, arose from my research. I’ll want to explore the possibilities for “non-critical” but meaningful participation I’ve listed in the whitepaper, looking for projects that have tested these possibilities, and creating wireframes and prototypes exploring the untested participation methods among my suggestions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I’ll want to think further about design that specifically scaffolds critical digital edition participation: how can we teach critical ways of reading Ulysses without belaboring existing theories? (Teach methods, not content.) I’ll also continue analysis of site data and user feedback, using these to reassess the edition’s curation and moderation functionalities as more readers and classrooms use the edition.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Finally, I’ll add to the discussion around editorial statements for digital editions by crafting a more detailed methodological statement for Infinite Ulysses, one that focuses on the choices of design and code that perform the edition’s values, and then seeking a platform for peer review of my methodology.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My distillation of textual scholarly values would only benefit from drawing in more diverse examples from the history of the field, as well as circulating my arguments for feedback and refinement. And I think the field would benefit from drawing up suggested guidelines for reviewing editions that aim at participation, something I hope to think through with members of the Shelley-Godwin team.
These steps should both improve Infinite Ulysses as a textual resource, and add to our body of knowledge about designing a more public, participatory digital humanities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/defense-slides/defense-slides.021.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of presentation slide from the dissertation defense&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(End of formal dissertation defense presentation.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;more-about-this-dissertation&quot;&gt;More about this dissertation?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re interested in reading more about &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.infiniteulysses.com&quot;&gt;Infinite Ulysses&lt;/a&gt; or the dissertation around it, the dissertation exists as &lt;a href=&quot;http://dr.AmandaVisconti.com&quot;&gt;dr.AmandaVisconti.com&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;http://dissertation.amandavisconti.com&quot;&gt;dissertation.amandavisconti.com&lt;/a&gt; was the URL I used pre-defense), which functions as an umbrella documenting all the pieces of my dissertational effort: blog posts, code repositories, links, the dissertation’s whitepaper (written just in the final month before the defense, as an analytical debriefing), etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s also &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/tag/dissertation/&quot;&gt;the full set of blog posts written during my dissertation available here&lt;/a&gt;, which talk not only about the focus of my research (digital humanities design, Joyce, textual scholarship, annotation) but about the practical aspects of designing and pursuing a digital dissertation. Also, I’m always happy to answer questions &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.literaturegeek.com&quot;&gt;@Literature_Geek&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bonus-slides&quot;&gt;Bonus slides&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had some extra slides and talking points ready for questions I anticipated, or for things I didn’t have time for in the presentation but wanted to be sure to cover. One of the anticipated questions was “Is Infinite Ulysses an edition?”, so I was very prepared to argue that it isn’t a &lt;em&gt;scholarly digital edition&lt;/em&gt; (which is a term of art meaning certain methods and rigor), but that it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; a digital edition. I blog that argument soon, for anyone who hasn’t heard me present on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If any of these slides intrigue you, feel free to contact me, or check out my dissertation whitepaper at &lt;a href=&quot;http://dr.AmandaVisconti.com&quot;&gt;dr.AmandaVisconti.com&lt;/a&gt; for more info.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/defense-slides/defense-slides.025.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of presentation slide from the dissertation defense&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/defense-slides/defense-slides.026.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of presentation slide from the dissertation defense&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/defense-slides/defense-slides.027.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of presentation slide from the dissertation defense&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/defense-slides/defense-slides.028.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of presentation slide from the dissertation defense&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/defense-slides/defense-slides.030.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of presentation slide from the dissertation defense&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/defense-slides/defense-slides.031.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of presentation slide from the dissertation defense&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/defense-slides/defense-slides.032.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of presentation slide from the dissertation defense&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/defense-slides/defense-slides.033.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of presentation slide from the dissertation defense&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/defense-slides/defense-slides.035.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of presentation slide from the dissertation defense&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/defense-slides/defense-slides.036.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of presentation slide from the dissertation defense&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/defense-slides/defense-slides.038.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of presentation slide from the dissertation defense&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/defense-slides/defense-slides.039.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of presentation slide from the dissertation defense&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/defense-slides/defense-slides.047.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of presentation slide from the dissertation defense&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/defense-slides/defense-slides.050.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of presentation slide from the dissertation defense&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/defense-slides/defense-slides.061.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of presentation slide from the dissertation defense&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/defense-slides/defense-slides.056.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of presentation slide from the dissertation defense&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/defense-slides/defense-slides.057.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of presentation slide from the dissertation defense&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jun 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/2016/06/20/digital-humanities-dissertation-defense-talk</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2016/06/20/digital-humanities-dissertation-defense-talk</guid>
        
        <category>digital-humanities</category>
        
        <category>infinite-ulysses</category>
        
        <category>dissertation</category>
        
        <category>advice</category>
        
        <category>dh-now</category>
        
        <category>best</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Digital Humanities Dissertation Defense Advice</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently realized that although &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/tag/dissertation/&quot;&gt;I thoroughly blogged my dissertation (almost 40 blog posts)&lt;/a&gt; and wrote &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2015/05/09/dissertationdefended&quot;&gt;a post after successfully defending the dissertation in April 2015&lt;/a&gt;, I never blogged my actual defense talk. In keeping with &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2016/02/28/DHjobtalk&quot;&gt;blogging the job talk&lt;/a&gt; that took me into my current job, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/tag/grad-advice/&quot;&gt;other DH/grad student advice&lt;/a&gt;, I am now rectifying this oversight! I’ll make a few comments about the defense process in this blog post, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2016/06/20/digital-humanities-dissertation-defense-talk&quot;&gt;I blogged the actual talk in a separate post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;knowing-what-to-expect&quot;&gt;Knowing what to expect&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I highly recommend attending at least one dissertation defense in your department, preferably early in your degree. (I was lucky to get to attend two excellent literature defenses that incorporated digital humanities: Jason Rhody’s defense of &lt;a href=&quot;http://hdl.handle.net/1903/11161&quot;&gt;Game Fiction&lt;/a&gt;, and Lisa Rhody’s defense of &lt;a href=&quot;http://hdl.handle.net/1903/13969&quot;&gt;Ekphrastic Revisions: Verbal-Visual Networks in 20th Century Poetry by Women&lt;/a&gt;.) It was extremely useful for me to learn early on that defenses aren’t necessarily the scary things they’re made out to be in popular culture. If things go right, you should only be defending because your advisor thinks you’re ready—at that point, you have the expertise, and the defense is your opportunity to showcase the experience you’ve built up over the years of dissertational work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The defense experience can be pretty similar to the orals/comps (&lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2012/11/27/info-dump-humanities-doctoral-candidacy-exams-advice/&quot;&gt;advice on those here&lt;/a&gt;), both in terms of practical preparation you can do beforehand (anticipate questions you’ll be asked, know what the room will look like where you’ll present) and in the experience (have your first five minutes just about memorized, and after that hope to relax and enjoy the chance to discuss your work—and nothing but!—with smart people for an hour.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have a chance to present a version of your talk to another grad student or family—or even better, at a conference or other public venue—I’d recommend using that time to get comfortable with your talk, so that your focus just before the defense can be on the Q&amp;amp;A rather than the presentation. &lt;strong&gt;Fun fact:&lt;/strong&gt; I was going to give a Digital Dialogue at MITH the week before my defense, but the electricity across campus went out while I was on my first slide and stayed out the rest of the day, so we had to reschedule for the week &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; my defense. Didn’t get to practice the talk publicly, but I did end up feeling like nothing worse could happen during the actual defense, so it worked out all right!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prepare-but-dont-worry&quot;&gt;Prepare, but don’t worry&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m lucky and privileged to have had &lt;a href=&quot;http://dr.amandavisconti.com/#preservation&quot;&gt;an amazing committee&lt;/a&gt;, an audience with some friendly faces (thanks, Porter, Kyle, and Jordan!), and a really positive experience—but I recognize that you should also be prepared for less ideal outcomes. We’ve all heard about questioners showing up without reading the full dissertation, and questions framed as interrogation rather than an invitation for you to share your unique expertise. At the same time, I really want to emphasize that &lt;strong&gt;the defense isn’t something to overly worry about&lt;/strong&gt;: compared to all the work you’ve done to get to this point, the defense is a time-limited situation, specific to what you’ve been thinking and working on for years, and at this moment &lt;strong&gt;you&lt;/strong&gt; are better prepared for it than anyone else in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some things you can do, if you are in a situation where it’s not clear the room will be entirely friendly: Practice phrases for steering confusing questions and defining the discussion in your own terms. In particular, I’d practice “double evasion” of off-topic questions, since I’ve seen this fluster conference speakers: if an audience member asks you about something that you’re not claiming expertise in via your dissertation, you can start by noting this difference but speculating briefly on possibilities, then have a statement ready if they press you again to talk about some topic outside your focus (e.g. “As I said, x and not y was the focus of my research, and you might be interested to know that [thing about x tangentially related to y and segue back into your area of research]”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My awesome advisor (Matt Kirschenbaum) also talked me through all the possible outcomes of the defense (I think these were: accepted without revisions, accepted pending revisions, or requiring a second defense? The norm tended toward being accepted with or without revisions, and if I needed revisions I shouldn’t feel bad about it). It was good to know what the best through worst possible outcomes could be (and that none were too terrible). Also, this let me emotionally prepare myself for being okay with a request for revisions (against a perfectionist streak I’m sure I share with a majority of people doing graduate studies). (I did end up passing without needing revisions, yay!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also talked about an unlikely but possible scenario for any grad student doing DH work: that someone with an ax to grind about digital scholarship shows up to the public part of the defense and makes trouble. This felt unlikely enough that I was able to not worry about it, but at the same time I had prepared for public challenges to the scholarly nature of my work. A weekly email to my advisor as a record of what I’d been doing wasn’t just motivation for me, it also kept a log we could produce if what I had been doing was questioned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sure I’m leaving things out, so feel free to email (aviscont@purdue.edu) or tweet (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.twitter.com/Literature_Geek&quot;&gt;@Literature_Geek&lt;/a&gt;) me with any questions about the defense process (note that particulars will vary by university and department, of course). I’ll share my actual defense talk in the next post early next week when I’m back from the Joyce conference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;more-about-this-dissertation&quot;&gt;More about this dissertation?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re interested in reading more about &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.infiniteulysses.com&quot;&gt;Infinite Ulysses&lt;/a&gt; or the dissertation around it, the dissertation exists as &lt;a href=&quot;http://dr.AmandaVisconti.com&quot;&gt;dr.AmandaVisconti.com&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;http://dissertation.amandavisconti.com&quot;&gt;dissertation.amandavisconti.com&lt;/a&gt; was the URL I used pre-defense), which functions as an umbrella documenting all the pieces of my dissertational effort: blog posts, code repositories, links, the dissertation’s whitepaper (written just in the final month before the defense, as an analytical debriefing), etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2016/06/20/digital-humanities-dissertation-defense-talk&quot;&gt;text and slides from my thesis defense are in this post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s also &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/tag/dissertation/&quot;&gt;the full set of blog posts written during my dissertation available here&lt;/a&gt;, which talk not only about the focus of my research (digital humanities design, Joyce, textual scholarship, annotation) but about the practical aspects of designing and pursuing a digital dissertation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jun 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/2016/06/14/digital-humanities-dissertation-defense-advice</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2016/06/14/digital-humanities-dissertation-defense-advice</guid>
        
        <category>digital-humanities</category>
        
        <category>infinite-ulysses</category>
        
        <category>dissertation</category>
        
        <category>advice-tutorial</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Infinite Ulysses beta closes for 1.0 work</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Infinite Ulysses’s open beta (March 2015-May 2016) has ended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-this-means-for-currentprospective-users&quot;&gt;What this means for current/prospective users&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(If you’re just interested in future plans for the site and an overview of how the beta period went, skip to the next section.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s time for my &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.InfiniteUlysses.com&quot;&gt;InfiniteUlysses.com&lt;/a&gt; participatory edition to get some serious post-beta improvements, and I’ve decided the best way to do this is taking some time off from moderating the site while I focus on its web development needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The site will remain up and readable (except for short hours-long downtimes when pushing major improvements), but on July 15th I’ll be closing signups for new users as well as blocking logging in/annotating by existing users for a while. Please contact &lt;a href=&quot;&amp;#109;&amp;#097;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;:&amp;#105;&amp;#110;&amp;#102;&amp;#105;&amp;#110;&amp;#105;&amp;#116;&amp;#101;&amp;#117;&amp;#108;&amp;#121;&amp;#115;&amp;#115;&amp;#101;&amp;#115;&amp;#064;&amp;#103;&amp;#109;&amp;#097;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#046;&amp;#099;&amp;#111;&amp;#109;&quot;&gt;&amp;#105;&amp;#110;&amp;#102;&amp;#105;&amp;#110;&amp;#105;&amp;#116;&amp;#101;&amp;#117;&amp;#108;&amp;#121;&amp;#115;&amp;#115;&amp;#101;&amp;#115;&amp;#064;&amp;#103;&amp;#109;&amp;#097;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#046;&amp;#099;&amp;#111;&amp;#109;&lt;/a&gt; with any questions this choice raises (e.g. I can try to accommodate needs such as plans to use the site in a summer or fall course or reading group, or to demo the site on a given day.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.infiniteulysses.com/content/terms-use&quot;&gt;the site’s public data policy&lt;/a&gt;, I’ll be emailing site users this week with an invitation to export their annotations during the next six weeks (before July 15th, 2016). After that date, &lt;strong&gt;site users will not be able to log in until after the post-beta overhaul is complete&lt;/strong&gt; (currently no set date). Before July 15, logged-in users can use new links on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.infiniteulysses.com/user&quot;&gt;your user profile page&lt;/a&gt; to export DOC, XML, and CSV versions of your annotations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note there’s no necessity to export your annotations&lt;/strong&gt;—they’ll still be there on the 1.0 site. Since from July 15, 2016 onward until the 1.0 release is ready there will be no new site signups and no logging in or annotating for existing users, I wanted to give you access to your annotations. If you don’t export your annotations during that time, you won’t lose them—an export of all user annotations will be available &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/amandavisconti/infinite-ulysses-public/tree/master/Annotations&quot;&gt;in the GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt; (and I see no reason for it to not stay there as long as GitHub is around, so no rush). Please contact &lt;a href=&quot;&amp;#109;&amp;#097;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;:&amp;#105;&amp;#110;&amp;#102;&amp;#105;&amp;#110;&amp;#105;&amp;#116;&amp;#101;&amp;#117;&amp;#108;&amp;#121;&amp;#115;&amp;#115;&amp;#101;&amp;#115;&amp;#064;&amp;#103;&amp;#109;&amp;#097;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#046;&amp;#099;&amp;#111;&amp;#109;&quot;&gt;&amp;#105;&amp;#110;&amp;#102;&amp;#105;&amp;#110;&amp;#105;&amp;#116;&amp;#101;&amp;#117;&amp;#108;&amp;#121;&amp;#115;&amp;#115;&amp;#101;&amp;#115;&amp;#064;&amp;#103;&amp;#109;&amp;#097;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#046;&amp;#099;&amp;#111;&amp;#109;&lt;/a&gt; with any questions or special needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-a-hiatus&quot;&gt;Why a hiatus?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was hoping to have enough stuff ready to do a 1.0 release in time for this year’s Bloomsday and my speaking at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://anniversaryjoyce.com/provisional-programme/day-5-friday-17-june/&quot;&gt;XXV International James Joyce Symposium that week&lt;/a&gt; (we’re doing a full day of digital+genetic editing panels all day on Friday, including Hans Gabler and Michael Groden—pretty exciting!). Alas, I won’t have time to finish my improvements by that deadline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m looking forward to continuing work on the site, and I do think now that I’ve settled into my new job and have some support to expand the site into a team project from a solo dissertational one, I’ll be able to release something pretty cool. But I’m not yet at a place where I can commit to a release date, and instead of continually pushing that time off, I need to make a change to reduce the moderation and community design effort the site involves, and focus on the site’s web development without feeling constantly behind where I want the site to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The community deserves care.&lt;/strong&gt; Running a digital community is so rewarding, but I need to acknowledge that I don’t have the time to currently do everything the site requires—especially the constant vigilance against abuse and spam that the community absolutely deserves. I didn’t have time to focus on accessibility testing as much as I should have; the reading interface only works for limited window sizes and breaks after a certain level of magnification, which is a poor reward for anyone answering my invitation to a public &lt;em&gt;Ulysses&lt;/em&gt; conversation. And I dislike continually pushing the date for the 1.0 changes back—it’s better for everyone if I wait to make a clear promise on when and what I can do with the site (more on what’s holding back changes farther below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My research trajectory.&lt;/strong&gt; I also need to acknowledge how my research interests are developing—I’ve always been primarily interested in participatory interface design for knowledge-building, and I think of myself as more of a research programmer and textual scholar, than as a Joycean or community manager. I’m also interested in putting my research efforts more squarely toward improving student and publics access, participation, and inclusion in the humanities, and in making the humanities (researchers, topics, and audiences) more diverse. (&lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2014/05/27/inclusivityeditioncanon&quot;&gt;I’ve written about this a bit in a post on why I chose Ulysses for my edition, despite this supporting the problematic canon of white male authors writing in English&lt;/a&gt;. I don’t mean to say others shouldn’t be working in Joyce studies—this is a personal decision about where I want to put my time and effort going forward). I’m interested in inviting more people into the conversations around challenging literature, and less interested in spending my future specifically wed to Joyce’s texts (although I suspect I’ll continue to do silly &lt;em&gt;Ulysses&lt;/em&gt; things like &lt;a href=&quot;http://digitalliterature.net/usurper/&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2012/02/20/anachronistic-linati-schema&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://digitalliterature.net/fun/marionette.html&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;…).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;testing-the-edition&quot;&gt;Testing the edition&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A variety of user testing and feedback helped shape the current site, and will be the foundation for the 1.0 version:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Informal (hallway testing, tweeted questions)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Talk-aloud observation (single and paired)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Participatory design (sketching ideal layouts)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Site contact form feedback &amp;amp; emailed feedback&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;GitHub issue queue&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Open beta soft launch survey with non-academic testers (March 5th, 2015)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Open beta survey responses (March 9-30, 2015)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Google Analytics (going forward, I want to have a clear statement to users on what kind of information I can see)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Aggregated mapping (heatmaps, scrollmaps, clickmaps)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Drupal statistics on frequency and authorship of annotations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;howd-the-beta-go&quot;&gt;How’d the beta go?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The open beta was a fantastic experience for me. We had some decent exposure via social media, helped in no small part by making the Hacker News Top 20 the day after my dissertation defense. As of June 2, 2016, the site had:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;22,251 unique visitors&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;776 members&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;1,167 annotations&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;283 unique annotation tags&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A huge thanks to all the site’s beta testers&lt;/strong&gt;, who generously gave me feedback on the site’s design and how it fit their individual reader and research needs. (And another shout-out to all the people whose code and support made the site possible, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.infiniteulysses.com/credits&quot;&gt;listed here&lt;/a&gt;—especially &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/mwidner&quot;&gt;Michael Widner&lt;/a&gt;, whose development of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lacunastories.com/&quot;&gt;Lacuna annotation platform&lt;/a&gt; you should definitely check out!.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though there wasn’t a race for quantity over quality, special thanks are due to the site’s power annotators for their generosity to our reader community, and for helping me design the next iteration of the site to better support heavy annotation: user &lt;strong&gt;tim finnegan&lt;/strong&gt; outpacing us all with 546 excellent annotations, followed by &lt;strong&gt;bbogle&lt;/strong&gt; (159) and by three users with 20-30 annotations each—&lt;strong&gt;pbohan&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;serinamarie89&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;wvarga7a1&lt;/strong&gt;. I also authored 248 annotations myself, although many of these were drawn from my earlier &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.UlyssesUlysses.com&quot;&gt;UlyssesUlysses.com&lt;/a&gt; annotations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(Hey, existing site users: I have stickers created as rewards for my alpha and beta testers now—if you used the site between now and back when it went live, send me an email with your mailing address by the end of June 2016 and I’ll ship you one! Subject to not running out of them, of course…)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/IUSticker.png&quot; alt=&quot;Infinite Ulysses publicity sticker&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(The nose fell out of the logo… still looks like a face to me…)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-numbers-are-nice-but&quot;&gt;The numbers are nice, but…&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s been amazing to have so many strangers interact with something I built—and the number of people who visited the site (22k+) is probably a bit unusual for a literature dissertation? But the reality of those numbers suggests that while there’s interest in the idea of the project, most of those visitors didn’t stick around long to read and didn’t come back any or many times. Check out this spike of interest right after my defense, and the relative flatline after—over half (about 14,000) of the 22,251 visitors came within the first month of the open beta, with the remaining 8,000 trickling in over the following year:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/statriseandfall.png&quot; alt=&quot;Line chart of site visitors since the site when live, with spike in April 2015&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interest in the digital humanities and in designing for a more participatory literature conversation is great, but that’s really just a tiny step—the real assessment is whether I can build something that goes beyond initial curiosity, and supports people reading selections or the whole book over weeks and months. Site account creation (required to annotate and use some other features) was low compared to the total number of visits, returning visits were low, and reading without annotating was largely the norm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure, reading &lt;em&gt;Ulysses&lt;/em&gt; is a significant investment of time…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/AlisonBechdelUlysses.png&quot; alt=&quot;Panel from Alison Bechdel&#39;s graphic novel Fun Home, showing the protagonist reading Ulysses and swearing&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(&lt;em&gt;Panel from Alison Bechdel’s highly recommended graphic novel&lt;/em&gt; Fun Home)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…But as much as I like to see these stats as heartening, I know I have a lot of work to do in making the look and feel of the site a delightful experience, and in making major changes to the site’s functionality supporting how people are most comfortable reading (a frequent request, touch annotation to allow comfy armchair reading, is held back by there not currently being a fully functioning plugin for this).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the concerns above about keeping the annotations a safe, welcoming space for including diverse voices in the &lt;em&gt;Ulysses&lt;/em&gt; conversation, I need to think through supporting a community with unusual ebbs and flows of activity. Once hooked, print readers do frequently come back to &lt;em&gt;Ulysses&lt;/em&gt; for many rereads. Even with rereaders, though, most users will come to the print book or website for stretches of weeks or months, then disappear for a while. Keeping the site feeling alive meanwhile—for example, making sure readers’ new questions get answered—takes regular effort that I don’t have enough time to support myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Annotators, assemble!&lt;/strong&gt; I do have some ideas for addressing this ebb and flow of the reading community, and for getting the site back into a schedule of regular improvements. I’ll be thinking about how to turn the site into a community-led project: I have funding for a graduate research assistant, some offers to push improved code to the site once I’ve got the repo ready, and the hope that the project can be a space for students and staff to train in various areas of DH interest (coding, scholarly digital editing, social media work…). I’m also working on a project that will make sharing new functionalities between digital editions easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A reading-sprint model.&lt;/strong&gt; Once the 1.0 site is ready, I’m interested in trying out a reading-sprint model, where I’d advertise an approaching sprint several months in advance (optimistically, enough that any teacher could then plan to include in their course the following term), then open the site for a set period of reading by individuals, book clubs, and classes—knowing that I had team in place to support the community (curation, moderation, guidance) through that period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Removing the account requirement.&lt;/strong&gt; I also want to recognize that even with a delightful look and intuitive functionality, not all readers will want to annotate or sign up for the site. I need to build things so that all features except annotation and comments are open without a user account (early on, I focused over much on sign-ups as a way of tracking a threshold of site engagement—but ease of use is more important than nice stats!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Splitting the text.&lt;/strong&gt; I also plan to divide the site into two interlinked texts: one text with a curated set of annotations, aimed at the bulk of people arriving at the site who just want some help reading &lt;em&gt;Ulysses&lt;/em&gt;. The second text will be the place for experimenting with new features and with diverse kinds of annotation (Team Mulligan? reader injokes? annotating as the book’s characters? check, check, and check!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This split into two texts should take some of the burden off human moderators—the curated text can have annotations pulled in from the experimental text as time allows, while the experimental text can be a little more open to various kinds and granularities of annotation (though I’ll still have mechanics in place to report abuse, ask for moderation, and to require a few good-faith annotations before your annotations are visible to anyone else).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;best-laid-plans-vs-real-life&quot;&gt;Best-laid plans vs. real life&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s why I keep pushing the 1.0 version off. I had a handful of site improvements I’d meant to release last Bloomsday (a couple weeks after my graduation), and lots of additional local work since then (e.g. moving annotations into a collapsible side drawer to aid tablet reading, and changing the theme to support smaller screens and greater screen magnification were big ones).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dissertation scope repercussions.&lt;/strong&gt; I was lucky in having a lovely dissertation experience. But because the final beta version of the site was built largely during the final year of my dissertation (after a lot of research and trying out other tech platforms and code libraries), I didn’t have time to put in place everything I’d normally do for a professional job. Sometimes visual design suffered for the sake of functionalities I needed to move user testing forward; scope tightened and pieces dropped out (e.g. comment threading display was buggy, so I ended up just removing commenting on annotations for the beta).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Incremental improvements are currently hard to push.&lt;/strong&gt; It was difficult to push incremental changes to the site; for example, simply removing the up/down voting button (an early decision) couldn’t happen until I had time to modify the site’s theme to accommodate how the annotation structure would shift into the resulting gap, or the whole display would be out of whack. The text I chose ended up having needing manual addition of Joyce’s typographic choices, and having many more OCR errors than I expected—and as with other site changes, making it possible for site users to correct errors themselves wasn’t an easy thing to add, although users were generous with locating errors. There were a lot of small things like that, and the solution really needs to be a general overhaul rather than a collage of bandaids.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Work is getting done, albeit not pushed to the live site.&lt;/strong&gt; Since defending the dissertation, I’ve been working locally on a bunch of other improvements, starting with a complete from-scratch rebuilding of the site’s database and theme. I’ve been able to share my code for testing on development versions of several other digital editions (Romantic Circles, the Shelley-Godwin Archive, and the Victorian COVE site I’m co-PI’ing with Dino Felluga), and I made some headway toward packaging my code for easier reuse by others at the CODEX hackathon in January.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But with starting a new job, settling into post-student life, and moving to a new place, I haven’t been able to make the concentrated clumps of time I need to finish things up—just hours here and there, with days in between. Despite journaling constantly alongside my webdev work, it’s hard to pick work back up swiftly after putting it down for weeks at a time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also recognize that in trying to connect and grow the digital humanities community at Purdue, I might not have time to set this all up in the near future. The hope is to get the site to a place where others can participate in improving the site if they’re interested in doing so, but I recognize that I’ve been pushing “improvements soon!” off for a while now, and that isn’t the best situation for either me or the site’s readers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a fun project, and I’ve been honored by the generosity of others in helping me build something better. So: I’m going to stop saying the new site will be ready soon, and wait until I can make and keep a promise about the site’s next version. I hope that this is a reasonable way to do that (any suggestions or requests to improve how I’m implementing this decision are welcomed).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;read-more-stuff-related-to-infinite-ulysses&quot;&gt;Read more stuff related to Infinite Ulysses?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Infinite Ulysses site will remain available for looking at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.InfiniteUlysses.com&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; until it’s ready for further interactive use. If you’re interested in reading more about the work behind Infinite Ulysses, you might fancy the dissertation around the edition at &lt;a href=&quot;http://dr.AmandaVisconti.com&quot;&gt;dr.AmandaVisconti.com&lt;/a&gt;, including a whitepaper discussing stuff like designing interfaces for a public humanities, how public humanities participation can be meaningful without necessarily using full “critical” academic rhetoric, an analysis of past annotation and digital &lt;em&gt;Ulysses&lt;/em&gt; projects as well as my Infinite Ulysses user testing, and some thoughts on whether Infinite Ulysses is an edition (for my textual scholarship peeps.) There’s also &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/tag/dissertation/&quot;&gt;the full set of blog posts written during my dissertation available here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jun 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/2016/06/02/infinite-ulysses-beta-closes</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2016/06/02/infinite-ulysses-beta-closes</guid>
        
        <category>digital-humanities</category>
        
        <category>infinite-ulysses</category>
        
        <category>scholarly-web-design-and-coding</category>
        
        <category>best</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Lunar dust &amp; tapioca pudding (touring Purdue Archives&#39; aerospace collections)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lib.purdue.edu/spcol&quot;&gt;Purdue University Archives &amp;amp; Special Collections&lt;/a&gt; (ASC) have an amazing aerospace history collection due to Purdue’s many students and faculty who were pilots (Amelia Earhart was faculty), went on to be astronauts, or worked in the aerospace industry. I’m working with the ASC towards digital humanities projects that increase public and student access to our collections; in particular, we’re planning to use 3D scanning and printing to make some of the more interesting, fragile, or rare artifacts more accessible to visitors and student researchers. Today, Flight Archivist Tracy Grimm kindly gave me a tour of some of the objects we’re thinking about using in our DH work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve shared some of the more interesting things below (sorry for shaky photo quality on a couple of these!). These photos were okayed for educational sharing on social media (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lib.purdue.edu/spcol/digital-reproduction-requests&quot;&gt;copyright info here&lt;/a&gt; if you’re interested in using these somehow).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/AerospaceTour/IMG_1087.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Amelia Earhart’s goggles&lt;/strong&gt;. These are too fragile for regular handling; we want to explore using various types of 3D printing filament (pliable, glass-like) to replicate these as wearable facsimiles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/AerospaceTour/IMG_1088.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;An ice pick Amelia Earhart used&lt;/strong&gt; to puncture open cans of tomato juice. She used these as a compact way of getting calories while flying. (I think Tracy said this was a specific brand—Beecham’s?—and that Earhart was used in their advertisements.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/AerospaceTour/IMG_1128.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/AerospaceTour/IMG_1129.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Checking out the safe inside the archives vault where artifacts are kept extra-secure, including Amelia Earhart’s scrapbooks and helmet, the smelling salts she used to keep awake during her flights, and flight suits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/AerospaceTour/IMG_1090.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;strong&gt;glove&lt;/strong&gt; astronaut Eugene Cernan wore on the moon. Sealed in a bag so as not to lose any of the &lt;strong&gt;lunar dust&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/AerospaceTour/IMG_1091.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/AerospaceTour/IMG_1127.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A “frangible nut” from a space shuttle flown on by astronaut Janice Voss&lt;/strong&gt;. The nut was packed with explosive charges and separated from a rocket on takeoff (presented on a commemorative plaque). It’s quite heavy, and the edges are sharp where explosives sheared off the metal. The nuts were originally around 50 lbs, so this fragment is about 25 lbs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/AerospaceTour/IMG_1103.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/AerospaceTour/IMG_1104.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/AerospaceTour/IMG_1105.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/AerospaceTour/IMG_1108.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/AerospaceTour/IMG_1109.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/AerospaceTour/IMG_1110.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Astronaut food&lt;/strong&gt; from the Mark N. Brown Papers collection, assumedly used during training on Earth. Each contains info on how to prepare the food. Potatoes au gratin, noodles and chicken, tapioca pudding, butter cookies! Each unit includes a small velcro dot (to anchor the food to something when there’s no gravity).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/AerospaceTour/IMG_1112.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Possibly the coolest business card title: “&lt;strong&gt;Astronaut&lt;/strong&gt;”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/AerospaceTour/IMG_1115.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/AerospaceTour/IMG_1118.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/AerospaceTour/IMG_1122.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/AerospaceTour/IMG_1124.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Apollo XVII LRV Map Book&lt;/strong&gt;, a commemorative binding of maps actually used on the moon by astronaut Eugene Cernan while traveling on the lunar rover. A broken fender on the lunar rover had to be repaired (while on the moon!) with 4 of the map pages (the Smithsonian has the repaired fender in its collection). The individual pages aren’t too interesting to look at, but we’re thinking about creating a digital quilt of the images and then augmenting this with historical and topographical information.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 09 May 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/2016/05/09/aerospace-history-dh-projects-purdue-archives</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2016/05/09/aerospace-history-dh-projects-purdue-archives</guid>
        
        <category>digital-humanities</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
