<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Literature Geek</title>
    <description>smarter online communities via digital humanities</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sat, 06 Apr 2019 17:45:46 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 06 Apr 2019 17:45:46 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.4.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Notes: Workflows to consider before opening a DH lab (Purdue version)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part of &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/tag/meta-dh/&quot;&gt;my meta-DH series&lt;/a&gt; documenting DH/DS infrastructure: the hows &amp;amp; whys of treating a project team, lab, department, or campus as itself a DH project.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Caveat&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;This post consists of notes taken during my former &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/tag/purdue-dh/&quot;&gt;DH Librarian role at Purdue&lt;/a&gt; (2015-2017), rather than my latest thinking at Scholars’ Lab. I’ll be sharing that updated thinking here soon!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What workflows should I think through before the Purdue Libraries DH Lab can open its doors?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;IP policy: okay to post work to GitHub? using what license?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Project management: Basecamp? Asana? Trello? something that can connect to GitHub, IFTTT or Zapier, or the Archives &amp;amp; Special Collections unit’s Drupal workflow if it’s created there&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Code of conduct for events, interactions, collaborations, social media (including commitment to equitable representation via speakers and event participants)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How do new or learning coders participate in technical work?: Development/experimentation server, checklists for coders and whoever is approving moves to the production site&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;General server workflow: production, test, staff development, learner experimentation servers/VMs and flow among servers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Policy on what projects we host ourselves&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Policy on best practices: usability, accessibility, public participation, outreach, research publication, technical stack (e.g. when possible build a static site)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Workflow for preserving projects: Webrecorder, BagIt, video of narrated exploration; LOCKSS; Purdue repo’s and Archives &amp;amp; Special Collections unit; workflow for collapsing dynamic sites into static ones&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sample contract for working with DH Lab staff: mutual agreements&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sample contract with Libraries IT concerning technical coverage and ASC on web archiving (if interested)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Web design and development checklist&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Usability and accessibility checklist (web, events, publications)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Best practices doc for digital editions: who locates, transcribes/digitizes/proofs, uploads (as individual pages) text?; signed documentation of IP right for use of text?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Workflow for working with Archives &amp;amp; Special Collections artifacts: security, moving objects between offices/buildings&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Workflow for staff adding resources, people, etc. to “DH at Purdue” site&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Social media policy: tone, etiquette, access, schedule for Twitter, blog, Facebook&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;IT workflow (negotiating how we work alongside the Libraries’ existing IT team): meet early in project/grant design, accessibility/video captioning, service contract, data plan w/security, accessibility compliance, longterm hosting plans&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 25 Nov 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/11/25/workflows-before-opening-DH/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/11/25/workflows-before-opening-DH/</guid>
        
        <category>digital-humanities</category>
        
        <category>meta-dh</category>
        
        <category>notes</category>
        
        <category>purdue-dh</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Notes: Wise resource investments for a DH initiative (Purdue version)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part of &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/tag/meta-dh/&quot;&gt;my meta-DH series&lt;/a&gt; documenting DH/DS infrastructure: the hows &amp;amp; whys of treating a project team, lab, department, or campus as itself a DH project.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Caveat&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;This post consists of notes taken during my former &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/tag/purdue-dh/&quot;&gt;DH Librarian role at Purdue&lt;/a&gt; (2015-2017), rather than my latest thinking at Scholars’ Lab. I’ll be sharing that updated thinking here soon!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ideas about making wise resource investments:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ask “Should we even build a center?” and explore other metaphors/options&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Convene a Libraries DH initiative advisory committee: not oversight/supervision, but resource and advocates for my DH in the department (e.g. on the hiring committee)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Require potential faculty fellows/project members to attend one term of “introduction to DH” workshops first before committing to collaboration, using MITH’s DH Incubator model (lessons in finding, creating, cleaning, sharing, documenting data; collaboration best practices, why and how to credit everyone involved in your work: how to use GoogleDocs, Trello, Doodle polls; common mistakes using new methodologies; joining the DH online community via blogging and Twitter)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sign mutual contract with collaborators indicating expected deliverables and deadlines, checkpoints and what will happen if work not done, and expectations for crediting and citing all team members in publications and presentations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Send Purdue DHers at all levels out to train (HILT in Indianapolis, RBS), then bring back to campus to give a presentation on what they learned&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Invest in collaborators, not projects&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Train the trainers (peer review, personal research &amp;amp; professionalism time for all)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Publications (questions by Geoffrey Pullum, “To co-author, or not to co-author?” with slight alterations to fit our needs): What names will appear on title page? What order? Who/what has IP rights? Can any team members recycle paper’s content for conference presentation or for inclusion/adaptation in other work including journal articles and books? What happens if the project is dropped or one member fails to uphold their contract? Would other team members be allowed to wrap up the project or publications about the project as desired (and publish under what names)? For continuing projects, how long should all team members names stay on the front page? (All names should always stay on a history or about page).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;See also students’ (UCLA) and collaborators’ (MITH) bills of rights. Include info on assuring student mentorship for all assistance, internships, jobs, teaching, and mentoring—not e.g. data entry.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;All panels, sets of conference keynotes, and hiring should look for unconscious bias and be structured to support inclusion.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CRM for consultation/campus DH tracking?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Consultation appointment set up includes consent to code of conduct, optional inclusion in campus DH directory&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Public workflows a la Guelph (what we do/don’t do, what effort involved…)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 25 Nov 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/11/25/wise-resource-investments-digital-humanities-initiative/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/11/25/wise-resource-investments-digital-humanities-initiative/</guid>
        
        <category>digital-humanities</category>
        
        <category>meta-dh</category>
        
        <category>notes</category>
        
        <category>purdue-dh</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Notes: Planning a DH lab's physical location (Purdue version)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part of &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/tag/meta-dh/&quot;&gt;my meta-DH series&lt;/a&gt; documenting DH/DS infrastructure: the hows &amp;amp; whys of treating a project team, lab, department, or campus as itself a DH project.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Caveat&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;This post consists of notes taken during my former &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/tag/purdue-dh/&quot;&gt;DH Librarian role at Purdue&lt;/a&gt; (2015-2017), rather than my latest thinking at Scholars’ Lab. I’ll be sharing that updated thinking here soon!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dh-lab-physical-space&quot;&gt;DH Lab physical space&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have strong need for a space for project work (e.g. 3D scanning and printing), team meetings, class demonstrations, events, and the ability to livestream and record (e.g. for later DH website hosting, classroom watching, sharing with Archives &amp;amp; Special Collections [ASC] donors) project work, demos, and presentations. I propose we initially identify an interim location that could be used over the next 1-3 years while we pilot the projects outlined above and seek major external funding—preferably somewhere we could begin occupying with a minimum of renovation, cost, and time (the newly arrived 3D setup cannot be unpacked until we have a dedicated space). I’m calling this initial, low-cost space a “DH Lab” as we’ll be focused on research and development there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;DH Center (3-6 years in)&lt;/em&gt;. We’ll also apply for external funding for a formal “DH Center”, which could increase the types of DH we nurture from Libraries-focused R&amp;amp;D to broader campus work such as classroom tours and one-off class visits to the center.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In the long run&lt;/em&gt;, there’s strong mutual interest from the ASC and DH in locating a more formal DH Center side-by-side with the ASC, turning the HSSE 4th floor non-ASC space into the DH Center. This would both ease our daily collaborations, and visually demonstrate to the campus the flow of possible scholarship from acquisition, processing, teaching, and research in the ASC through research, teaching, and diverse publication in the DH Center. Much of our initial DH work will develop from the expertise and collaboration of the ASC, and we should improve the DH conversation (where archival expertise and labor are sometimes left out of the conversation) by visibly showcasing the ASC’s critical partnership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;DH position in the org chart&lt;/em&gt;. I’m not advocating the DH Center being positioned within the ASC, to allow for autonomy and partnerships with other campus units. However, we discussed (in the DSC) exploring changes to the current department organization structure that make collaborations and reporting better represent our developing cohesion as partnered curation and digital creation spaces. In particular, I’d like to think about where we’d be placed as a potential research center with its own staff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-a-dedicated-dh-space-provides&quot;&gt;What a dedicated DH space provides&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s important to have a space where work can be left as-is without needing to be secured or tidied away; to visibly associate a set location with our DH initiative, rather than using random campus spaces for different events; and where we can customize the space to specific DH needs (including video capture and live-streaming of project work and presentations).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A dedicated physical DH space would&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;provide a visible, fixed physical location for DH presentations, workshops, and teaching from which the audience would always leave aware of our Libraries DH initiative, and knowing where to return (or point colleagues) with any future DH needs of their own&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;include space tailored to digital project research and discussion, 3D equipment use, and both livestreaming and video-recording of project work and presentations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;showcase our own Libraries DH (and related) research as both model projects and opportunities for collaborating with us, and model best practices for collaboration&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;develop space where interdisciplinary projects can grow and people across Purdue are incentivized to cross paths and locate shared interests&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;allow informal overlap among Libraries staff working or interested in DH, growing DH expertise in-department via drop-in times and informal reading groups and coffee sessions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;provide the equipment necessary to DH presentation and iterative publishing needs (good projection monitors, demo’ing live websites and tools, supporting audience members downloading and tweeting, capturing a live video feed and better audio/video for later hosting on the DH website)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A dedicated/non-reservable space&lt;/em&gt;. If we convert the CSC to a DH lab, I would like to model the room on Swaim and make the space non-reservable. This allows us to leave leave our expensive 3D equipment out when in the middle of use (because of how hot the printer gets and potential for liquid filament to stain other areas), use the space for informal ASC+Press+DH work (in addition to formal meetings) without needing to schedule these impromptu sessions, and keep areas where we’ll be working with ASC collections and 3D prints free from food and drink.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A social and experimental space&lt;/em&gt;. Longtime DHer Stephen Ramsay has said, “I cannot think of a successful digital humanities center — anywhere in the world — that did not begin with a bunch of people who had found each other through various means and who were committed to the bold and revolutionary project of talking to one another about their common interests.” DH labs thrive on supporting collaboration, not service. To accomplish this, we need to leave unscheduled, unplanned space for unexpected opportunities to arise, designing a space where you can come to chat about DH, find partners and mentors, and get help jumpstarting your research. I’ll work with Libraries strategic communication, outreach, and marketing experts to publicize our work and these opportunities once we’re ready.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;floorplan-and-major-purchases&quot;&gt;Floorplan and major purchases&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following approval, I would continue working with Candy on a proposed room layout, identifying furnishings we already have in the attic, and budgeting for any additional items needed from preferred vendors. I would also work with RaeLynn and Sarah to change the room’s scheduling status.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a more specific list of furnishings and proposed layout, but below is a summary of the work spaces I’m anticipating:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Individual work desks (4, pending additional DH staff and 2 post-docs, and can also be used by project collaborators)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A conference table and seating that can be re-arranged for large group meetings, demos, and presentations (and, if we have the furniture in the attic already, a separate informal area with armchairs)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Station for 3D imaging and printing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Station for livestreaming, video-recording work and presentations, and video editing; including a computer and monitor that can be swiveled for use at the 3D scanning and printing station, and two dedicated external hard drives for 3D and video file backup&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And the major purchases anticipated:&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Webcam for livestreaming&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Video camera (and accessories speakers, microphone, tripods, disks, 2 HDs to store videos and 3D scans, video editing software; both cameras could be checked out by Libraries staff for non-DH events)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Computer stations: at least one dedicated computer for 3D imaging and video editing (plus accessories: keyboard, mouse, monitor, dock)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A presentation-size wall-mounted digital monitor (as an alternative to the projector screens that allow higher definition and better color fidelity)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Optional: 1-2 computer monitors facing through the glass walls into the library, for display of Purdue Libraries DH projects and other interesting DH projects and visualizations to passerby&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dh-lab-users&quot;&gt;DH Lab users&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I envision our DH Lab as an R&amp;amp;D space for DH prototyping projects, teaching, and events, not as an open service space that can be booked by others. Its earliest users would be project work including experimentation with the 3D setup and formal meetings and demos (which can be livestreamed and.or video-recorded for teaching and publicity uses), a drop-in space for collaborators working on this year’s major grant proposals toward a DH Center and ASC+DH+Press/SPS co-evolution, and room for group DH consultations. If we begin to add DH graduate research assistants, staff, and/or post-docs, this will be space to work together (although retaining private offices for each staffer would allow for sometimes necessary focus or conference calls). In the near future, the space could support invited DH speakers and workshop leaders,a s well as Libraries-led intensive summer workshops for faculty and graduate students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Future uses could include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;As a drop-in space, possibly jumpstarted by partnerships with student groups such as the English Department’s Graduate Technology Working Group, or by creating a new digital dissertations in Africana Studies cohort with Ron Stephens (AASRC director and professor)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Scheduled class visits for lessons and project demos&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hosting an experimental, Libraries-taught DH and ASC and/or Press class and associated drop-in space for students working on their class project&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We need to exist in the Libraries to increase access and cross-disciplinary collaboration in ways individual departments cannot. An actual physical space associated with regular DH speakers and training opportunities fosters a community that’s both interdisciplinary and can reduce barriers among different university roles (student, staff, faculty, librarian).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;initial-basic-physical-space-setup&quot;&gt;Initial, basic physical space setup&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Space rental cost?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Basic renovations &amp;amp; space cleanup&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If possible, small rooms or cubicles (one director’s office, one huddle room for sharing by other staff; both with desks, desk chairs, computers, monitors, peripherals)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Large conference table and chairs (collapsible/rolling tables to allow for different room setups)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lockable area for artifacts, 3D equipment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Basic furniture (chairs, tables)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Signage outside&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Projector, screen, large monitors, livestreaming camera, conference phone setup, presentation podium with speakers, microphone&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cheap coffee maker (invite people to hang out and chat, rather than leave the space for coffee or chat in non-DH spaces like Starbucks)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clarity on who can access the space, whether the space can be booked by others or used for after-hours events by others; generally no other use should be made of the DH space, with requests for use needing to come through the DH Specialist and uses that are actually particularly in need of what the DH space uniquely offers supported if/when they don’t interrupt normal work (e.g. class visits, speakers and livestreaming talks)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ideal-room-setup-furniture&quot;&gt;Ideal room setup, furniture&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(&lt;em&gt;After large external grant for renovation/model DH center.&lt;/em&gt;)
We would need keys or key cards and a list of everyone with access to these spaces; ideally, we’d use IDs as key cards that could let people into the class/meeting space but not into offices or areas with equipment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Twitter scroller/blink(1) setup for server/project use status, social media oversight&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;DH books and shelving&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Waiting space armchairs and coffee table&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Shelves/display for old books, old computing stuff&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Etsy neon signs with DH terms&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Window blinds&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Framed posters of cool and/or Purdue DH projects&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Door and over-door signs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In/out/ring bell signs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Security/rekeying of main doors&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Locked space for 3d equipment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“This is an office; here’s how to sign up for a consultation” sign. If space is highly visible, this will deflect random walk-ins from interrupting work and inform those actually interested in DH to get in touch without interrupting work; we’ll probably have a mix of days with no sign/doors open (Mondays and Tuesdays, when consultations are scheduled or on days with visiting speakers), and days with doors closed so project team members can concentrate on their work. Will need further thinking to balance desire for a space that increases visibility and draws in passersby, with need for researchers to have interrupted focus.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Large digital screen (like at Brown) instead of projector+screen, for presentations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Podium, speakers, microphone, pointer, dongles&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Conference table and chairs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Video camera + webcam&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Demo computer and monitor and peripherals&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Special ASC transport cart/checklist&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dry-erase boards and markers and erasers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Water, garbage, recycling, fridge, microwave, coffee maker&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Branded stickers, bookmarks, mugs/shirts for presenters only&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Office with door for director&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Analyst office?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cave/commons desk and 3rd huddle room with telephone and internet&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Monitors for outside walls&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Inside monitors (Big DIVA, IU, DH projects, Twitter)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Folding chairs/tables for events&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Monitors and desk space for personal laptop hookups&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Water/fridge/microwave and coffee maker, informal area for watercooler-style chats, snacks, eating lunch together&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 25 Nov 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/11/25/planning-dh-lab-physical-location/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/11/25/planning-dh-lab-physical-location/</guid>
        
        <category>digital-humanities</category>
        
        <category>meta-dh</category>
        
        <category>purdue-dh</category>
        
        <category>notes</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Notes: A mission statement for digital humanities (Purdue version)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part of &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/tag/meta-dh/&quot;&gt;my meta-DH series&lt;/a&gt; documenting DH/DS infrastructure: the hows &amp;amp; whys of treating a project team, lab, department, or campus as itself a DH project.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Caveat&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;This post consists of notes taken during my former &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/tag/purdue-dh/&quot;&gt;DH Librarian role at Purdue&lt;/a&gt; (2015-2017), rather than my latest thinking at Scholars’ Lab. I’ll be sharing that updated thinking here soon!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post (everything below) is from a post I was drafting back when I was designing Purdue Libraries’ DH initiative; some parts weren’t completely fleshed out, and the “values” list doesn’t reflect my current thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stuff below—identifying what our values are, and stating that we mean to prioritize them—doesn’t mean that prioritizing or “doing the work” of those values will happen. This isn’t the work. The work is doing stuff that performs, amplifies, shares, teaches, argues for these values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with a code of conduct, it’s more dangerous to say you’re going to do (or are doing) something and then not stand by that promise, than to not make the promise at all. Lots of institutions say they value diversity, but either they don’t follow up on that claim at all (or enough), or they define the term so broadly as to neutralize any benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s easy to say you’re going to do a thing, and harder to imbue your work with the values you think you care about. I’m sharing this publicly now for a couple reasons: I want to be held publicly accountable to show I value these things. As we get deeper into specific projects, I hope to post what each project aims for, and to follow up with periodic analysis of whether we’ve held to those goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My dissertational &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.infinteulysses.com&quot;&gt;Infinite Ulysses&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; work, for example, has failed at doing its best to support all the values I list below—but &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2013/12/02/valuespost&quot;&gt;stating my values at the beginning of that project&lt;/a&gt; was essential to helping me realize the project’s shortcomings later on, and to build my knowledge so my future work can do better. (You can read about the most obvious problem from &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2014/05/27/inclusivityeditioncanon&quot;&gt;a mid-dissertation post here&lt;/a&gt;, the conclusion of which I no longer agree with.) I also want to encourage others to document and self-reflect on their work, by contributing to the existing pool of statements and charters holding scholars to their values—just as I’ve been encouraged by work like Scott Weingart’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://scottbot.net/pledges/&quot;&gt;Pledges&lt;/a&gt; page and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/about/charter&quot;&gt;Scholars’ Lab charter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;identifying-values&quot;&gt;Identifying values&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I built on past mission statements and charters I’ve encountered (DH or otherwise). On my dry-erase board, I made a list of things I think I care about and/or I think our DH initiative should value, given our experts, resources, and department and campus mission and strategic statements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a more public and participatory humanities through DH, with engagement with non-academics recognized as scholarship&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;topic, practitioner, and audience diversity and inclusion, pervasively rather than as an add-on&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;move beyond the idea that libraries can be neutral: choose work that is actively good, not just not-bad (e.g. explicit anti-racist approaches)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;accessibility and universal design from the beginning of projects&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;participatory design with a project’s intended audience from the beginning of projects, not just user testing at the end&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;listening and amplification, e.g. through&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;full credit and IP retention for all involved in making a project regardless of professional role, affiliation, or type of work performed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;fully citing &amp;amp; crediting the resources we build on (with especial care for under-cited digital resources and alt-ac scholars)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;care to not accidentally nor intentionally overstate, when stating our involvement in collaborative projects or in other scholars’ projects (and knowledge that the larger our initiative grows, the more potential there is for people to incorrectly assume any DHer or DH project on campus involves us or is ours)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;recognition of multiple publics, and funding and designing with under-supported publics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;recording today’s campus through the eyes of our community (e.g. the students who use our Archive to study past students), but only when we can do so in a rewarding, respectful, safe way&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;open access, reuse, remix, and user-friendly documentation allowing these&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;share about our project work during and after the work to help others understand the choices and effort that goes into various kinds of DH&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;making project IP, privacy, data management clear to users (including any tracking such as Google Analytics) and a public plan for how data and site users will be impacted if funding or maintenance of the site are cut off&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;projects that are sustainable &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; explicitly ephemeral and well documented; create space for experimentation and failure&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;clear ways to accept, credit, and incorporate user feedback&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;only involve or build communities if you can commit to tending them well and enforcing a code of conduct that protects community members&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;student mentorship, and funding and professional development support for non-tenure-track-faculty such as adjuncts, continuing lecturers, and students&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;evaluable mission statements for projects&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;time for reflection on past work and realigning new strategy to fix previous failures&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;prioritize work that supports collaboration and offers potential for a branching impact (invest in training the trainers)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;participate in and support broader DH initiatives beyond our campus&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;if-we-think-these-are-what-we-value-how-are-we-acting-on-these-values&quot;&gt;If we think these are what we value, how are we acting on these values?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ID specific actions and/or policies supporting these&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I’ll keep track of any DH visitors/speakers and ensure we’re using our funds and time to support a diverse representation of DH; projects must explicitly advance one of our stated core values (access, diversity, inclusion), with a preference for projects that include mentorship for students and credit for all team members&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What do we study? We’ll likely want to work with our many Objects That Have Been in Space and other neat aerospace history stuff—how do we keep that from pulling us toward work by and for white dudes?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Initial philosophy-heavy proposal focused on foundational policies: what would we do, and what wouldn’t we do? how would we interact with campus IT? what funding needs will we have?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Next step is report/request/objectives &amp;amp; goals doc that outlines how we’ll do the work over the next two years&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-dh-mission-statement&quot;&gt;A DH mission statement&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This was originally the abstract for my first proposal to the Purdue Libraries on where our DH initiative should go. I’m thinking it will evolve into charters for major projects here (like a possible DH space, and a DH team-taught course), so I’m capturing each version in a GitHub repo so we can track changes over time.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I propose we initially focus our digital humanities initiative on a collaboration among DH, the ASC (&lt;em&gt;note: Purdue Archives &amp;amp; Special Collections, a Libraries unit&lt;/em&gt;), and the University Press &amp;amp; Scholarly Publishing Services (&lt;em&gt;also located in the Libraries!&lt;/em&gt;), with a focus on &lt;strong&gt;co-evolving these units while developing infrastructure toward a more open (diverse, inclusive, accessible, participatory, real-time, relevant) humanities.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I envision a DH Center for the Open Humanities in the Purdue Libraries, serving as the hub of the campus DH community. We will build a culture of digital scholarship, assisting through incubation rather than service: connecting potential collaborators, recording DH work for institutional memory, modeling best practices and inspiring other DH work with our own experiments, showcasing the Libraries’ strengths, and raising visibility for Purdue’s digital humanities successes through diverse publication forms and audiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I take the Libraries’ valuing of diversity, inclusion, and access as core motivating ideals, and plan strong demonstrations in all three areas of the latest (2016-2019) strategic plan (particularly 1:3, 2, and 3:2-4). We should proactively develop what we want the digital humanities to be, by pursuing and publicizing projects that advance all our strategic values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In practical terms, our activities will include modeling DH research and publication best practices through collaborative internal projects, cross-campus collaboration and outreach, consultations and mentorship, and hosting events including a DH visiting speaker series, a day of talks by DHers from all over campus (co-hosted with the CLA), and intensive methodological training workshops. We will additionally maintain an information-rich “DH @ Purdue” website (including a campus DH directory), and design and co-teach pilot DH+ASC+Press courses giving students theoretical, technical, and alternative academic experience in building a DH project as a collaborator. Our work will emphasize collaboration and mentorship, value a more public and inclusive humanities, and lead by modeling effective DH research and teaching for other departments. Because we currently have limited staff time and resources, we’ll focus on building a sustainable funding model, doing a few specific pilot projects extremely well, and DH networking on campus through events and consultations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I propose a two-phase approach:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[3 sentences on specific plans for fund allocation in the next two years]&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[3 sentences on specific plans for fund allocation years 3-5]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During Phase 1, [paragraph on specific major grant project idea].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of this document offers details on specific activities we could pursue, longterm goals for the initiative, reasoning for requested funding and hiring, and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;next-steps&quot;&gt;Next steps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rewrite this philosophy-heavy proposal into an objectives and goals report with specific requests, actions, and timeline.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 25 Nov 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/11/25/mission-statement-digital-humanities-purdue/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/11/25/mission-statement-digital-humanities-purdue/</guid>
        
        <category>digital-humanities</category>
        
        <category>meta-dh</category>
        
        <category>purdue-dh</category>
        
        <category>notes</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Notes: DH initiative scope &amp; practice (Purdue version)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part of &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/tag/meta-dh/&quot;&gt;my meta-DH series&lt;/a&gt; documenting DH/DS infrastructure: the hows &amp;amp; whys of treating a project team, lab, department, or campus as itself a DH project.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Caveat&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;This post consists of notes taken during my former &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/tag/purdue-dh/&quot;&gt;DH Librarian role at Purdue&lt;/a&gt; (2015-2017), rather than my latest thinking at Scholars’ Lab. I’ll be sharing that updated thinking here soon!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a followup on my philosophy-focused &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2018/11/25/mission-statement-digital-humanities-purdue&quot;&gt;mission statement post&lt;/a&gt;, this post lays out the scope of what DH we would do (and &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; do), and what long-term success might look like for the Purdue Libraries DH initiative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mission-and-plan&quot;&gt;Mission and plan&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What is DH?&lt;/em&gt; The digital humanities is a “big tent” of a field combining humanities research (cultural heritage, literature, history, the arts, ethics…) with the design, building, use, teaching, and theorizing of digital methods (e.g. text analysis) and forms (e.g. blog posts). My DH is also defined as a community sharing interests in methods and tools that cross disciplinary boundaries. This community values open access, diversity and inclusion both in researchers and in their areas of study, a more public humanities reaching diverse audiences, and research that is real-time, collaborative, iterative, and generative of further work beyond the initial researchers. DH’s emphasis on interdisciplinary collaboration, methodologies over content, and recognition that all academic fields deal with history of the field, ethics, subjective interpretation, design, and texts will help us further connect Purdue’s CLA and Libraries departments to the university pillar of STEM excellence as well as other campus communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What subset of DH should we support?&lt;/em&gt; I’d welcome suggestions for projects, goals, or values you think we should include in the DH initiative. Our ability to support specific ideas will depend on funding and hiring (both how many staff we can fund, and the expertise and interests of who we hire). I’ve prioritized projects we can achieve in 1-3 years, while also recording ideas we’d love to support in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scoping our DH.&lt;/em&gt; Even if we achieve strong funding, we’ll want to specialize and focus so that we can develop specific expertise, rather than offering shallow engagement across the broad board of DH. We’ll partner with other campus units to help them develop their own initiatives for DH support (e.g. departments must hire DH faculty if they are sincere about desiring DH scholarship and teaching). We’ll also work to connect anyone interested in an area we don’t support to resources and potential collaborators (e.g. by developing our directory of campus DHers and DH @ Purdue resource website).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our DH Center would not be a service shop; our closest activities to service would be offering consultations at the beginning of projects, and pursuing DH research that also results in better support for further campus DH (e.g. improving collection metadata for use with specific DH tools). We will frame any DH Center roles as experts rather than staff, and enter into any collaborations with a clear sense of the discoveries and publications we intend to build on the experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will try to do a few specific DH things very well, rather than be everything everyone desires of DH. We will publicly articulate this limited scope, while encouraging and advising others on campus in imagining and addressing areas outside our scope. We will also publicize and support other DH initiatives on campus, designing our DH Center as a hub rather than hoarder of campus DH.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our initial main partners will be the ASC and Press/SPS, as these collaborations show the most immediate potential: experts ready to partner, past teaching experience and contacts, and realizable specific projects. Eventually, we hope to foster connections throughout the Libraries, and pursue diverse projects not bound to any one area of campus (e.g. working beyond the Libraries and CLA with departments such as CS and the Polytechnic Institute).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Strategic overlaps.&lt;/em&gt; I’ll define specific connections to the Libraries strategic plan and University mission after the next round of feedback on this proposal. As a preview, we take the Libraries’ valuing of diversity, inclusion, and access as core motivating ideals, and plan strong demonstrations in all three areas of the latest (2016-2019) strategic plan (particularly 1:3, 2, and 3:2-4). Several of the projects proposed below are currently up for discussion by the DSC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mission-refined-proposed-dh-activity&quot;&gt;Mission, refined: proposed DH activity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We should shape what we want Purdue’s DH to be, with an emphasis on access, diversity, inclusion, public and student engagement, and making the humanities open through innovative modes of publication. We should prioritize work that mentors, trains, and supports under-supported campus constituents and/or public audiences; encourage and reward collaboration over solo and silo’ed scholarship; recognize all kinds of scholars as knowledge seekers worthy of support (including undergraduate and graduate students, adjuncts and continuing lecturers, staff); and acknowledge many kinds of knowledge-seeking and -sharing as research (including teaching, coding, infrastructure design, and metadata improvement).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Enhancing collections metadata towards use with DH methods&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Identifying workflows both theoretical (what’s the ideal flow of an acquisition, from donation through to DH research and publication?) and practical (how can we augment existing processing tools to better answer questions related to research and teaching needs?)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Creating model DH projects showcasing resources and opportunities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Piloting DH+ASC+Press teaching are priorities for our DH efforts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of this work doesn’t have immediate payoffs. To quote a colleague, “metadata isn’t sexy”—most people don’t get excited about plans to create and improve metadata, think through workflows for making ASC collections ready for DH methodologies, or making and testing small changes to our publication repositories. But strong metadata and infrastructure are critical to strong DH projects: the things we can make and teach with clean, thorough, accurate metadata and content and well-designed hosting and publication platforms will have broad and immediate appeal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-we-could-do&quot;&gt;What we could do&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Build a culture of digital scholarship: connect new and experienced DHers, create institutional memory, model best practices in DH, experiment, showcase DH on campus, raise public and campus visibility of DH work&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work that engages audiences beyond other faculty, including students and underserved publics, and that translates and motivates the humanities for these audiences. Work that welcomes and incorporates these audiences’ participation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work that makes the shiny, engaging stuff go. We value and support as scholarly work often-hidden innovations increasing capacity, care, and ethical design, including metadata improvement, documentation, and other infrastructure improvement.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work that is generative and transformative: we invest in making things better for more people.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work that includes explicit mentorship or learning opportunities for others, especially in the often-hidden variety of intellectually fulfilling career paths available to students.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work that values diversity, inclusion, and open access. We’re particularly dedicated to supporting under-supported Purdue researchers, including undergraduate and graduate students, all levels of staff, and adjuncts and continuing lecturers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-we-wouldnt-do&quot;&gt;What we wouldn’t do&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our DH Center would always interested in learning about digital humanities activity or curiosity on campus. To guard our time and focus, here are some things we wouldn’t tend to do:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Redundant tool or website building. We prioritize work that is reusable or extendable to support alternative uses in other fields and/or for other audiences, or otherwise innovates in line with our values.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hosting DH projects long-term (or otherwise beyond the length formally contracted in the mutual contract we sign with any faculty or other collaborators), unless the project has been appraised and selected for inclusion in the archives (subject to ASC interest, time, funding, and appraisal).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Replacing the need for humanities departments to increase hiring of faculty and staff with DH expertise. We might position ourselves as an incubator (a place to connect with others, polish ideas, hear about tools and methods, and otherwise jumpstart your DH involvement). I concur with Carly’s suggestion we focus on teaching transferable skills and values rather over specific tools (e.g. making learning BitCurator about learning archival values and digital materiality, making learning Omeka about learning the interpretive nature of archives and the scholarship that goes into building humanities tools).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Non-research service shop work (e.g. we won’t build your idea for you or set up your class blog). We can help you understand the scholarship and critical effort underlying digital work that you don’t yourself do, and we can assist you in identifying funding and experts to collaborate with on projects needing additional scholarly expertise.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We currently do not guarantee free ongoing consultations beyond the initial consultation. If you’d be interested in a more in-depth collaboration with us, we recommend inviting us to be credited project collaborators.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We currently consider but do not guarantee class visits, one-shot instructional sessions, or course design help. If you’d be interested in a more in-depth collaboration with us, we recommend inviting us to be listed co-teachers for the course. In all cases, we require at least one academic term of notice before any requested classroom involvement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;long-term-goals&quot;&gt;Long-term goals&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some examples of what success might look like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Large external grant support for a DH Center in addition to individual, interdisciplinary project grants&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A good workflow for projects connecting ASC -&amp;gt; DH -&amp;gt; Press (e.g. everyone involved learns and enjoys the collaboration, and we can accurately estimate time and money needs)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A workflow to easily support common training requests (e.g. using an ASC master timeline, Neatline exhibit spin-ups)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A change in university structure allowing for-credit listing of undergraduate and/or graduate courses taught by DH Center staff and other Libraries experts.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Experimentation with faculty and dissertation fellowships, seed funding, or other models to jumpstart promising DH collaborations, making sure that we pay special attention to those doing maintenance and scale work, teaching and service, and filling in humanities silences. Emulating MITH’s DH Incubator series, we could require applicant attendance at a previous “Intro to Collaborative DH” intensive workshop (preparing collaborators and letting them demonstrate longterm interest in DH engagement). This series would provide introductory training in basic skills such as using GoogleDocs to write collaborative grant proposals, creating a data plan, and proposing a project.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A sustainable model for teaching student cohorts on DH project-based courses/fellowships/internships, including co-teaching with the ASC and Press.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gathering DH and related courses (possibly with a theme such as DH, curation, alternative academic careers, and/or information studies) into a certificate, minor, major, or dual DH+ graduate degree.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A visible DH community (connected via a physical space with events, listserv, directory) energized through frequent events aimed at inspiring (e.g. speakers) and teaching (workshops, classes, seed funding).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increased access to and involvement with Libraries and campus resources for students and alumni through interactive digital projects.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A reputation for ethical, useful DH work, shared widely with the public and making an impact within DH and Libraries communities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 25 Nov 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/11/25/digital-humanities-initiative-scope-practice/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/11/25/digital-humanities-initiative-scope-practice/</guid>
        
        <category>digital-humanities</category>
        
        <category>meta-dh</category>
        
        <category>purdue-dh</category>
        
        <category>notes</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Notes: DH initiative working with existing IT expertise (Purdue version)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part of &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/tag/meta-dh/&quot;&gt;my meta-DH series&lt;/a&gt; documenting DH/DS infrastructure: the hows &amp;amp; whys of treating a project team, lab, department, or campus as itself a DH project.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Caveat&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;This post consists of notes taken during my former &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/tag/purdue-dh/&quot;&gt;DH Librarian role at Purdue&lt;/a&gt; (2015-2017), rather than my latest thinking at Scholars’ Lab. I’ll be sharing that updated thinking here soon!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post thinks through the DH initiative’s relation to the existing Libraries IT team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;libraries-it-partnership&quot;&gt;Libraries IT partnership&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We want to recognize and support the Libraries IT team’s expertise, while also recognizing that digital humanists are peculiarly, intimately involved with technical decisions at all levels of a digital project, from hardware building and calibration through long-term digital maintenance and preservation. Autonomy in technical decisions, implementation, publicity, and maintenance is an important piece of digital scholarship’s success, and we should design workflows that allow the DH Center to lead decisions about its own technical setup within the campus and departments frameworks IT oversees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of designing the DH Center, we would explore with IT service-level contracts, routine consultations and notice to IT early in new technical projects, regular invitations to IT for involvement, and support for Libraries IT’s experts (including GAs) to attend DH events and cross-training workshops in DH tools. At each digital project’s outset, we will decide who is responsible for creation, hosting, preservation, and maintenance among the DH Center, ASC, Libraries IT, Press and Purdue repositories, another campus unit (e.g. CLA IT), or the personal hosting of a project team member.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dh-center-virtual-space-dh--purdue-resource-website&quot;&gt;DH Center virtual space (DH @ Purdue resource website)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve created an initial Digital Humanities @ Purdue resource website at dh.lib.purdue.edu (not yet finished with design, so hasn’t gone through final marketing and admin oversight or publication yet, although I’ve done an initial site feedback round with Paul, Libraries IT, and marketing).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The site’s initial goal was to provide an umbrella resource for anyone searching for DH activity at Purdue, and to show the Libraries is pursuing a DH initiative. The current basic site includes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A nascent directory of campus DHers (not yet widely advertised to other departments, but containing faculty and staff from the Libraries as well as several other departments)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ways to get involved with DH at Purdue (joining the DH directory or a campus DH listserv, consulting with the DH Specialist, reading about DH events on Twitter using the #PurdueDH hashtag)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;During Fall 2016, I will convert the site to Drupal and match the look of the Libraries website. I will add the following resources:&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An automated way for DH staff to add new resources (links to DH projects, tools, and writing) from their smartphones&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A section curating the resources shared at DH consultations on popular topics (e.g. designing a DH dissertation, using Omeka in the classroom, humanities visualization)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Replacing the “DH Directory” and listserv option with a simpler page that will not need regular updating. This page will highlight how various Libraries staff, units, and resources can support DH, and also list people at Purdue working on DH under a few headings (e.g. teaching DH, DH grant proposal experience, DH students; name/role and department/email address).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Information about the Libraries’ DH initiative, plans, and goals&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Calendar for past and future DH campus events, workshops, and opportunities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Slides and video from past DH events (e.g. SHORE Symposium, Rikk Mulligan visit)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Regional opportunities such as the HILT training workshop in Indianapolis and Indiana THATCamp&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Institutional memory for campus DH projects, classes and their syllabi, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Guides to getting started in various DH methodologies (e.g. visualization of humanities data; links, blog posts, example projects, Libraries units and services)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Short video presentations on various DH topics suitable for use during a classroom session&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Blog posts documenting in-progress Libraries DH work (e.g. 3D setup installation)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am hosting this site (and all other websites that the DH Center contracts to host and maintain) on a separate dedicated DH Center server space. Libraries IT set up dh.lib.purdue.edu and dhdev.lib.purdue.edu for public and development sites; the main DH @ Purdue site will live at dh.lib.purdue.edu, while future projects will live at URLs such as dh.lib.purdue.edu/newproject.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 25 Nov 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/11/25/dh-initiative-existing-IT/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/11/25/dh-initiative-existing-IT/</guid>
        
        <category>digital-humanities</category>
        
        <category>meta-dh</category>
        
        <category>purdue-dh</category>
        
        <category>notes</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Notes: DH hiring ads &amp; HR policy (Purdue version)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part of &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/tag/meta-dh/&quot;&gt;my meta-DH series&lt;/a&gt; documenting DH/DS infrastructure: the hows &amp;amp; whys of treating a project team, lab, department, or campus as itself a DH project.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Caveat&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;This post consists of notes taken during my former &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/tag/purdue-dh/&quot;&gt;DH Librarian role at Purdue&lt;/a&gt; (2015-2017), rather than my latest thinking at Scholars’ Lab. I’ll be sharing that updated thinking here soon!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notes from back when I was designing a DH initiative at Purdue Libraries; not my latest thinking, but still worth sharing. See also the Scholars’ Lab &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/announcements/job-opening-curious-about-focusing-on-dh-development/&quot;&gt;DH Developer&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/announcements/job-opening-developer-outreach-testing-coordinator/&quot;&gt;User Advocate&lt;/a&gt; job posts for which I was one of the authors. The Scholars’ Lab job ads were created after the notes in this post, and better represent my current thinking about digital humanities HR and hiring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;job-ad-wording&quot;&gt;Job ad wording&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Job ad wording should allow for latent interests that the candidates’ current positions or formal academic coursework may not have allowed them to demonstrate or explore.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Job ads should make clear that candidates need not have all mentioned attributes to apply, but more importantly not ask for characteristics that are not needed to fulfill the job satisfactorily.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Job ads should highlight benefits of the position, such as personal research time and/or tenure-track role&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;See Angela Pashia’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://angelapashia.com/2017/03/seeking-a-diverse-candidate-pool/&quot;&gt;post analyzing hiring&lt;/a&gt;, e.g. “Being willing to consider experience in other areas for transferrable skills seems like a really important factor in diversifying our field.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;List a likely salary range using numbers (no vague “salary is competitive/will match hiree’s experience” language, no reference to arcance institutional wage structures such as “Pay Grade J”). If there’s a cost of living difference that means a position’s salary may look small but stretch farther, include that info in the ad (and perhaps a link to a calculator letting candidates compare to their current cost of living).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use candidates’ time well. Give as much info up front as possible (see last point: state the salary range!) and don’t ask for special work beyond a cover letter and resume during the initial application. For roles requiring previous experience, asking for e.g. a GitHub repo or link to a past project website may be appropriate (but consider e.g. who may fit your needs but not use GitHub/have an active repo), but save anything requiring new work or significant labor to curate for later stages in the interviewing process (and give candidates adequate time to prepare these when you do).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use references’ time well. Don’t ask for references during the initial application process, if your department allows you to do this; many folks are skittish about search committees contacting references who may not know you’re on the job market, and would appreciate knowing beforehand if you’re at the point where references will decide the hiring (give candidates time to let their bosses know first). Do let candidates know if &lt;em&gt;letters&lt;/em&gt; will be required later in the process, and only require letters rather than a phone call or email if these are judged to somehow be necessary or more fair.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-skills-are-we-seeking&quot;&gt;What skills are we seeking?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More important than specific skills or content expertise are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Interest in learning to publicly speak about the digital humanities to diverse audiences through diverse means such as Twitter, blogging, GitHub, and public speaking both on campus and at external opportunities such as conferences&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Interest in making the humanities more public&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Interest in critical thinking about the digital humanities, including areas like diversity, inclusion, ethics, and mentorship&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Interest in learning new things, and the demonstrated ability of the curiosity and ability to teach oneself new skills&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Interest in mentoring and teaching others what you’ve learned&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Interest in pursuing a personal research agenda in the digital humanities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Interest in balancing the excitement of innovation with work that makes the digital humanities more caring about its community and projects, more productive and generative, better at long-term thinking and planning (link Nowviskie “Capacity and Care” talk)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ability to discuss how your research interests either extend current Purdue DH or Libraries expertise, or add new areas of expertise&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vision for what the digital humanities could ideally be&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Interest in working with diverse colleagues and demonstrated experience contributing to an inclusive environment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;try-to-build-these-into-the-job-description-or-practicespolicy-of-their-organizational-unit&quot;&gt;Try to build these into the job description (or practices/policy of their organizational unit)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Funds for professional development&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mentorship&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Collaborative model that will always publicly credit their contributions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ability to shape DH Center and campus community&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ability to experiment and learn in their chosen areas of research&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Flexible work schedules, commitment to work-life balance, spousal placement help, childcare, and other benefits that increase access to and wellbeing in the job&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What formal (e.g. brownbag talks on what staff have been working on) and informal (water cooler) ways does your department encourage and reward collegiality?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;All staff should be able to PI; if they are not faculty and faculty status is required to PI, we should try to obtain the ability for them to PI across the board rather than per project.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ideally, hires should have a reasonable expectation that they can build a career here if they move here. If the work need is truly short-term (are you sure it is?) or (more likely) you’re only able to secure funding for a contract/short-term/grant-funded position, be extra diligent in including professional development opportunities and mentorship throughout the contract, and schedule work to allow the staffer to be on the job market during the final three months (including interview travel, reference requests, and time to practice job talks).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Each role should have a clear path for promotion, increased autonomy, and other types of development (as preferred by the staffer).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;20% personal research &amp;amp; professionalism time, in-house, on projects chosen in agreement with director/supervisor.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The shape of the DH Lab will be determined by the individual skills, interests, and experience of the staff.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Weekly standup meeting, monthly issues discussion lunch, regular scheduled participation in DH community (to be set with staff, e.g. Wikipedia editing, Programming Historian tutorial creation, Slack/Twitter focused chats and tech support hangouts, DH Q&amp;amp;A answers, work on open-source coding projects including documentation and usertesting)?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Develop a charter (mission, values) that whole team develops and agrees to (e.g. Scholars’ Lab charter).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 25 Nov 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/11/25/dh-hiring-ads-hr-policy/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/11/25/dh-hiring-ads-hr-policy/</guid>
        
        <category>digital-humanities</category>
        
        <category>meta-dh</category>
        
        <category>purdue-dh</category>
        
        <category>notes</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Designing a digital humanities initiative at Purdue: all my notes</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Some time back, I started a &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/tag/meta-dh/&quot;&gt;series of “meta-dh” posts&lt;/a&gt; documenting digital humanities and digital scholarship infrastructure: the hows and whys of making DH go. Treating a project team, lab, department, or campus as itself a DH project, if you will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I kicked the series off with &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2016/09/05/meta-dh&quot;&gt;an introductory post&lt;/a&gt;, and got two posts in before life (including a career change from Purdue to UVA!) intervened:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2016/09/11/designing-digital-humanities-initiative-background-campus-survey&quot;&gt;“Designing a Digital Humanities Initiative: Background &amp;amp; Campus DH Survey”&lt;/a&gt; covers basic questions you might ask when starting a DH or digital scholarship initiative at your school, and an analysis of Purdue’s (circa 2015-2016) campus strengths and needs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2017/01/31/2017-01-31-3D-digitalhumanities-proposal&quot;&gt;“Buying digital humanities hardware (a proposal for an archival DH 3D scanner and 3D printer”)&lt;/a&gt; shares one (successful!) model for asking your unit to fund something expensive. The actual proposal I submitted is attached, and the post covers a short skimmable summary of what I was asking for (and technical terms critical to understanding budget asks, e.g. what filament is), expected audiences for and example projects we could pursue with the equipment, expected IT support and maintenance needs, the budget, and a discussion of why the existing local options didn’t meet my needs (the Engineering Library had a 3D printer already, but we wanted one for dedicated use with the Purdue Archives)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I’m releasing &lt;em&gt;7 new posts&lt;/em&gt;, completing the series on designing DH infrastructure at Purdue Libraries; a table of contents listing all these posts in one place is below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Please note&lt;/em&gt; that these posts consist of notes taken during my former &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/tag/PurdueDH/&quot;&gt;DH Librarian role at Purdue&lt;/a&gt; (2015-2017), rather than my latest thinking at Scholars’ Lab. I’ll be sharing that updated thinking here soon!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;notes-from-my-time-at-purdue-as-their-first-dh-librarian-2015-2017&quot;&gt;Notes from my time at Purdue as their first DH Librarian (2015-2017)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Previously released:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2016/02/28/DHjobtalk&quot;&gt;job talk&lt;/a&gt; for my role at Purdue (DH Librarian, a tenure-track faculty role 2015-2017; see also the &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2017/02/23/scholars-lab-dh-center-managing-director-job-talk&quot;&gt;job talk&lt;/a&gt; for my current role co-directing the UVA Library’s Scholars’ Lab, 2017-current)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2016/09/11/designing-digital-humanities-initiative-background-campus-survey&quot;&gt;What I learned&lt;/a&gt; about DH at Purdue during my first year in this role, doing a campus DH/DS survey&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2017/01/31/2017-01-31-3D-digitalhumanities-proposal&quot;&gt;Proposing a significant expense&lt;/a&gt;: analysis a successful request to fund a DH-specific 3D scanning and printing setup&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;7 new posts!:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2018/11/25/workflows-before-opening-DH&quot;&gt;Workflows to consider before opening a DH lab&lt;/a&gt;: What workflows should I think through before the Libraries DH Lab can open its doors?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2018/11/25/mission-statement-digital-humanities-purdue&quot;&gt;A mission statement for digital humanities at Purdue Libraries&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Following up on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2018/11/25/mission-statement-digital-humanities-purdue&quot;&gt;mission statement post&lt;/a&gt;, a post &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2018/11/25/digital-humanities-initiative-scope-practice&quot;&gt;on what that mission would look like in practice&lt;/a&gt;: defining what would and wouldn’t be in scope for the initative, and what long-term success might look like&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2018/11/25/dh-hiring-ads-hr-policy&quot;&gt;DH lab hiring, writing good job ads, &amp;amp; HR policy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2018/11/25/planning-dh-lab-physical-location&quot;&gt;Planning a DH lab’s physical location&lt;/a&gt;: basic setup needs &amp;amp; rationale, thinking toward an eventual DH Lab physically paired with the Archives &amp;amp; Special Collections space&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thinking through the &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2018/11/25/dh-initiative-existing-IT&quot;&gt;DH initiative’s relation to the existing Libraries IT team&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2018/11/25/wise-resource-investments-digital-humanities-initiative&quot;&gt;Ideas for wise management of DH initiative resources&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s a wrap on my notes from Purdue DH, I think! My future posts in this &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/tag/meta-dh/&quot;&gt;meta-DH series&lt;/a&gt; will be about my current work at the UVA Library’s Scholars’ Lab.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 25 Nov 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/11/25/designing-dh-initiative-purdue-table-of-contents/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/11/25/designing-dh-initiative-purdue-table-of-contents/</guid>
        
        <category>digital-humanities</category>
        
        <category>meta-dh</category>
        
        <category>purdue-dh</category>
        
        <category>notes</category>
        
        <category>best</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>I/O: Reading &amp; writing as a digital humanist</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently collaborated with my awesome colleagues Ammon Shepherd and Brandon Walsh &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/i-o-reading-writing-as-a-digital-humanist/&quot;&gt;to self-interview&lt;/a&gt; about how we read and write as digital humanists, e.g. how our PhD program experiences changed where and how often we read. I’ve included my answers below, but please do check out &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/i-o-reading-writing-as-a-digital-humanist/&quot;&gt;the whole post&lt;/a&gt; to read Brandon and Ammon’s thoughts and see the variety (and some interesting similarities: fewer print books!) among three digital humanists growing in alternative academic careers in libraries after humanities doctoral research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-has-your-reading-style-changed-over-the-years&quot;&gt;How has your reading style changed over the years?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/i-o-reading-writing-as-a-digital-humanist/&quot;&gt;Brandon writes&lt;/a&gt;, reading for literature comps (&lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/assets/ExamsSharingCopy.pdf&quot;&gt;here’s my reading list and rationale!&lt;/a&gt;) changed my relationship to reading, but in an ultimately good way—I pay a lot more attention to whether I’m enjoying and challenged and learning from something I’m reading now, and am better at just stopping reading when those things aren’t happening. There was never enough time to read, during the first three years of my PhD program—I always was racing to get through the pages, and didn’t have enough time to reflect, or to move through readings non-linearly. I worried about being questioned about some random concept on page 180, rather than getting a sense of some of a book’s arguments and what &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; thought about them. And I felt like I needed to Know Things, that I needed to have read X thinkers on Y authors to be a functional scholar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(My mentors in grad school were &lt;em&gt;amazing&lt;/em&gt;, and to their credit none of these pressures came from them. Rather, I was seeing how other students were working and figuring out what being a scholar meant to me. I remember Melanie Kill recommending I use exams prep to figure out how I want to manage the reading part of being a scholar, before starting the first big project of the dissertation. Her advice rewrote my initial floundering with how to usefully ingest a lot of texts into something expected and welcomed.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I basically don’t read any books or print journal articles anymore. I’ve gotten off most (all?) listservs. I’m not any less of a scholar for delimiting my reading to other formats. Folks who do all or some of their reading via these formats are real scholars, too. How, when, and where you read are personal choices. There is a lot of writing and discussing out there, no one can read more of it, and it’s completely fine and intellectually responsible to delimit the formats and topics you’re going to read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scholarship doesn’t come from restricting the ways you take in new ideas; scholarship is challenging yourself to think hard and share that thinking so others can learn from and build on it (a re-articulation of Mark Sample’s great “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.samplereality.com/2013/02/08/when-does-service-become-scholarship/&quot;&gt;When does service become scholarship?&lt;/a&gt;“). And I guess I do extrapolate some best practices from that definition of scholarship, like representative and accurate citation being necessary for scholarship to &lt;em&gt;work&lt;/em&gt; (e.g. see &lt;a href=&quot;http://saranahmed/&quot;&gt;Sara Ahmed&lt;/a&gt;‘s articulation of citation as a black feminist practice). You can’t share your thinking well if you don’t say whose work you’re building on and how, and contribute to the community’s knowledge of other thinkers to learn from in addition to your thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-do-your-reading-inputs-connect-with-writingoutputs&quot;&gt;How do your reading inputs connect with writing/outputs?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My reading nowadays largely consists of: blog posts, tweets and Twitter conversations, attending conference and event talks (or reading transcripts afterward), talking/Slacking/emailing with people. For Slack, we’ve got an active Scholars’ Lab internal Slack for our staff and students, I love the &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/1Wk0JdF2Cty2VHMqpf_QlJXVKQdUtfeeFhaYRben3qaM/viewform&quot;&gt;Documenting the Now Slack&lt;/a&gt; for generous and smart thinking about the ethics of archives (particularly archiving and doing research with social media), and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://tinyurl.com/DHSlack&quot;&gt;DH Slack&lt;/a&gt; (which I’ve been posting to less lately, but still enjoying reading). Sometimes the blog posts or tweet link to digital projects or online journal articles that I read, but the “next” books on my work to-read list have been the same ones for what feels like a year, and I’m not getting to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve moved away from bookmarking stuff that I think I ought to read, and am only bookmarking things I think I’m likely to read soon, and that will impact my work (change or improve how I think or talk or listen). Having a huge backlog of “should reads” can make me feel behind, or like I’m slogging through processing text for reasons other than my own. I’d rather not have too much stuff on the backburner, and take longer thinking about the stuff I do read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes it’s physically small pieces of reading that have a large impact on my writing, like this &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/elikaortega/status/618097310505938944&quot;&gt;tweet&lt;/a&gt; by Élika Ortega, that rewrites the popular focus on “What is DH?” to instead ask “What can DH be?” That tweet—and &lt;a href=&quot;https://elikaortega.net/&quot;&gt;her work&lt;/a&gt; living that shift—plus Stewart Varner’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://stewartvarner.com/2016/01/what-dh-could-be/&quot;&gt;building on&lt;/a&gt; Élika’s thinking, all encouraged me to take more personal agency in my scholarly community. Rather than just imagining what I’d like DH to become as a field, I started looking at how the tiny snowflake of &lt;em&gt;my&lt;/em&gt; scholarly choices contributes to what the field becomes. For example, &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2014/05/27/inclusivityeditioncanon&quot;&gt;I’d thought&lt;/a&gt; I was okay with my dissertation creating yet another edition of a canon white male author, and I don’t think I’d argue the same today. That is not a comment on what anyone else should study—I just found that a shift in my thinking about the field of DH accompanied a shift in scholarly topics and formats. This is all to say that something as un-book-like as a tweet can cause a profound shift in someone’s scholarly career, and influence various kinds of future scholarship (including, in this instance, blogs posts, research projects, and keynotes).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Élika’s tweet (arising from the #WhatIfDH2016 etc. hashtags) made a huge impact, but Twitter’s been significant for my scholarship in subtler ways as well. I’ve learned to be a better scholar and person from Twitter exposing me to new ideas, or ideas I didn’t take seriously enough. It is wrong that I’m able to get so much from a platform that is actively unsafe for many of my peers to use. Some of my more recent scholarship has been a reaction to this: what features and feeling would an ideal academic virtual community have; what good virtual academic communities already exist, and whether there’s even a need for alternative technical platforms to assist with addressing social issues; and how we can better structure the work of community-building and moderation that helps such communities thrive (particular interests: more equitable distribution of the labor and stress of moderation, and recognition and reward for this work as scholarship).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-do-you-wish-you-did-differently-what-do-you-want-to-try&quot;&gt;What do you wish you did differently? What do you want to try?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d like to get back to blogging a couple of times a month. I’ve got a large backlog of drafts, including a series on designing DH infrastructure from my previous role at Purdue—I’d like to post those, and to continue to make infrastructural documents and decisions from my role in the Scholars’ Lab public, like the work of structuring our new job openings equitably and drafting job ads to match (&lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/announcements/job-opening-developer-outreach-testing-coordinator/&quot;&gt;one example&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/announcements/job-opening-curious-about-focusing-on-dh-development/&quot;&gt;another example&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also want to experiment further with my blogging voice. I’m interested in making public the pieces of scholarship that get “published” less often, whether that’s things like hiring that we don’t share to the detriment of the diversity of our community (e.g. folks sharing the text of their successful job talks—&lt;a href=&quot;http://readywriting.org/uncategorized/faculty-development-for-the-21st-century-and-beyond/&quot;&gt;Lee Skallerup Bessette&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://celestesharpe.com/onward/&quot;&gt;Celeste Tuong Vy Sharpe&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://chrisbourg.wordpress.com/2015/07/12/infrastructure-and-culture-a-job-talk/&quot;&gt;Chris Bourg&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/in-out-across-with-collaborative-education-and-digital-humanities-job-talk-for-head-of-graduate-programs/&quot;&gt;Brandon Walsh&lt;/a&gt;, as well as my &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/disrupt-the-humanities-managing-director-job-talk/&quot;&gt;Scholars’ Lab&lt;/a&gt; and previous &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2016/02/28/DHjobtalk&quot;&gt;Purdue job talk&lt;/a&gt;s), or what the daily scholarly practices look like that eventually result in a book or website (e.g. the software they use to make daily progress on &lt;a href=&quot;https://mkirschenbaum.wordpress.com/2012/08/15/on-tradecraft-and-track-changes/&quot;&gt;writing a book&lt;/a&gt;), or some small technical thing I figured out (e.g. automating screenshots of my liked tweets for personal Morale Boosting; post coming… soon?). And I’m proud of my &lt;em&gt;Programming Historian&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://programminghistorian.org/en/lessons/building-static-sites-with-jekyll-github-pages&quot;&gt;lesson&lt;/a&gt;, which I tried to write with kindness and thorough explanation of non-obvious technical stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I also love to read digital writing that is thoughtful in a different way about language and structure. I think I’ve had “write something that makes me feel excited about scholarship the way &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/nowviskie&quot;&gt;Bethany Nowviskie&lt;/a&gt;‘s &lt;a href=&quot;http://nowviskie.org/&quot;&gt;blog posts&lt;/a&gt; make me feel” as a goal for years now. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/walshbr&quot;&gt;Brandon&lt;/a&gt; recently shared &lt;a href=&quot;http://walshbr.com/blog/praxis-and-scale-on-the-virtue-of-small/&quot;&gt;some of his writing&lt;/a&gt; that made me similarly really excited about work, and reminded me that I want to try similarly structuring some of my own thoughts. I think more attention to language and structure could help me here, but I’m also realizing that a difference between many of my blog posts and these digital essays I admire, is that they argue in a generative way much of my writing doesn’t. Some things I’d like to experiment with emulating and building on: Bethany’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://nowviskie.org/2014/anthropocene/&quot;&gt;lyrical force&lt;/a&gt;, Brandon’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://walshbr.com/blog/praxis-and-scale-on-the-virtue-of-small/&quot;&gt;clarity&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/digiwonk&quot;&gt;Aimée Morrison&lt;/a&gt;‘s life-giving affirmation of &lt;a href=&quot;https://hookandeye.ca/2018/02/21/i-did-it-myyyyyyy-waaaaay-and-you-should-too/&quot;&gt;scholars’ brains and bodies&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AprilHathcock&quot;&gt;April Hathcock&lt;/a&gt;‘s &lt;a href=&quot;https://aprilhathcock.wordpress.com/2018/09/18/my-fire-this-time/&quot;&gt;courage and concision&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-technologies-do-you-use-to-facilitate-your-reading-and-writing&quot;&gt;What technologies do you use to facilitate your reading and writing?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I blog in a GoogleDoc (for collaborative stuff like this post), or using a Markdown editor (Typora) or text editor (BBedit, for when I really need to focus and not mess with formatting). I moved my personal blog (&lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/&quot;&gt;LiteratureGeek.com&lt;/a&gt;) from WordPress to a Jekyll-generated static site hosted on GitHub Pages, so sometimes I write directly on the GitHub website. I read and write tweets using Tweetbot (on my iPhone) or Tweetdeck (from my laptop). In the past, I’ve used &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hogbaysoftware.com/products/writeroom&quot;&gt;WriteRoom&lt;/a&gt; (for distraction-free exams presentation writing), and bookmarking tools including &lt;a href=&quot;https://getpocket.com/&quot;&gt;Pocket&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instapaper.com/&quot;&gt;Instapaper&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://pinboard.in/&quot;&gt;Pinboard&lt;/a&gt; to save things to read later. Currently, I save links from Twitter to Chrome bookmarks, and try to open those tabs at work once a week to read or discard them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;where-do-you-read-what-do-you-read-authors-forumsplatforms-formats-topics&quot;&gt;Where do you read? What do you read? (authors, forums/platforms, formats, topics…?)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been meaning to gather a list of frequent authors/places I read online, but have exhausted too much energy on my other answers to do that well right now! ¯_(ツ)_/¯ In addition to more professionally related reading by folks like my colleagues at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/&quot;&gt;Scholars’ Lab&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://nowviskie.org/2014/anthropocene/&quot;&gt;Bethany Nowviskie&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://walshbr.com/blog/praxis-and-scale-on-the-virtue-of-small/&quot;&gt;Brandon Walsh&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://hookandeye.ca/&quot;&gt;Aimée Morrison and the other &lt;em&gt;Hook &amp;amp; Eye&lt;/em&gt; bloggers&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AprilHathcock&quot;&gt;April Hathcock&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://chrisbourg.wordpress.com/&quot;&gt;Chris Bourg&lt;/a&gt;, I follow folks on Twitter who do creative, feminist tech work, many of whom also publish great &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/scholarslab/resources/blob/master/ZineBoard.md&quot;&gt;zines&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/wynkenhimself&quot;&gt;Sarah Werner&lt;/a&gt; does great scholarly blogging and tweeting, and I think I’ve also enjoyed basically every fiction book she’s recommended on Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Our thanks to colleague Ronda Grizzle for helping us frame this piece in a generative way! This is a partial cross-posting from &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/i-o-reading-writing-as-a-digital-humanist/&quot;&gt;a 9/27/2018 group-authored piece&lt;/a&gt; on the Scholars’ Lab blog.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 10 Oct 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/10/10/digital-humanities-reading-writing-habits</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/10/10/digital-humanities-reading-writing-habits</guid>
        
        <category>digital-humanities</category>
        
        <category>meta-dh</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Starter kit for considering a DH dissertation</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cross-posted on the Modern Languages Association (MLA) &lt;a href=&quot;https://infotech.mla.hcommons.org/2018/digital-humanities-dissertation-starter-kit/&quot;&gt;Committee on Info Tech blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Successful non-traditional dissertations include a comic book (&lt;a href=&quot;http://spinweaveandcut.com/unflattening/&quot;&gt;Nick Sousanis&lt;/a&gt;), a hip-hop album (&lt;a href=&quot;http://phd.aydeethegreat.com/&quot;&gt;A.D. Carson&lt;/a&gt;), code and design without written chapters (&lt;a href=&quot;http://dr.amandavisconti.com&quot;&gt;me&lt;/a&gt;), and the use of digital formats and methods such as a Tumblog counter-narrative (&lt;a href=&quot;http://vintageblackbeauty.tumblr.com/&quot;&gt;Jade E. Davis&lt;/a&gt;) or topic modeling (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lisarhody.com/revising-ekphrasis/&quot;&gt;Lisa Rhody&lt;/a&gt;). Are you curious about using digital methods or forms to pursue your dissertation research questions? Or maybe dissertational gate-tenders (advisors, mentors, departments) have you seeking successful examples of DH as part of the dissertation. Wherever you’re coming from, here’s a short selection of readings to get you started exploring digital humanities as doctoral scholarship:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Humanities Commons &lt;a href=&quot;https://hcommons.org/deposits/?facets%5Bgenre_facet%5D%5B%5D=Dissertation&quot;&gt;hosts around 70 dissertations&lt;/a&gt;; you can search for “digital humanities” to whittle these down to around 10 DHy theses such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://hcommons.org/deposits/item/hc:11773/&quot;&gt;Jason Rhody’s &lt;em&gt;Game Fiction&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://hcommons.org/deposits/item/mla:61/&quot;&gt;Alex Gil’s &lt;em&gt;Migrant Textuality&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;DH discussions under the aegis of scholarly organizations like MLA or AHA spend a good portion of time on concerns around evaluation and promotion relevant to the dissertation process. Resources you might check out on Humanities Commons include the &lt;a href=&quot;https://hcommons.org/groups/digital-humanists/&quot;&gt;Digital Humanists Group&lt;/a&gt; and events like &lt;a href=&quot;https://medicalhumanities.mla.hcommons.org/2018/02/07/online-forum-digital-humanities-medicine/&quot;&gt;the Online Forum on DH and Medicine&lt;/a&gt; recently posted on the Medical Humanities site.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://bit.ly/remixthediss-models&quot;&gt;#RemixtheDiss Models&lt;/a&gt; (hosted by the Futures Initiative at the Graduate Center CUNY and HASTAC) A collaboratively built GoogleDoc with information on a variety of dissertations using new formats and methods, including digital humanities approaches. Info includes each dissertation’s university and department, tools and media used, status of the dissertation (possibly outdated), and contact addresses for getting on touch with these dissertators.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org&quot;&gt;The Praxis Program&lt;/a&gt; (hosted by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholarslab.org&quot;&gt;Scholars’ Lab&lt;/a&gt; at the University of Virginia Library) Now in its seventh year, the Praxis Program offers &lt;a href=&quot;http://praxis.scholarslab.org/projects/&quot;&gt;7 examples&lt;/a&gt; of what a small team of (usually pre-ABD) humanities graduate students new to DH can learn, research, and build over the course of two semesters.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zotero.org/amandavisconti/items/collectionKey/V9DA47T7&quot;&gt;DH Guidelines for Dissertations and Tenure Zotero Library&lt;/a&gt; (46 items) Tenure and promotion cases can be models for DH dissertations, with the same issues of evaluation, effort, packaging, and translation at stake.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hastac.org/&quot;&gt;HASTAC&lt;/a&gt; (the Humanities, Arts, Science, and Technology Alliance and Collaboratory) A good community to read what other students in similar fields and stages of the degree to yours are thinking about, and for becoming comfortable with scholarly blogging. See especially those posts tagged as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hastac.org/explore/humanities-arts-media/digital-humanities&quot;&gt;digital humanities&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hastac.org/groups/digital-dissertations&quot;&gt;digital dissertations&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the materials I created before or during my completed DH dissertation might also be relevant:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/assets/ExamsSharingCopy.pdf&quot;&gt;My PhD Exams reading list&lt;/a&gt;, including an introductory argument for the items on the list and two sets of materials: broad digital humanities readings, and textual scholarship with a focus on digital scholarly editing. Among other benefits, making DH a focus of your exams reading can help you understand your exam committee’s (as a potential dissertation committee) attitudes toward DH. A &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zotero.org/amandavisconti/items/collectionKey/MXZR7HFN&quot;&gt;Zotero library of some of the list’s readings is here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My dissertation itself is a website: &lt;a href=&quot;http://Dr.AmandaVisconti.com&quot;&gt;Dr.AmandaVisconti.com&lt;/a&gt;. The focus of the dissertation was the design, building, and analysis of a participatory digital edition, &lt;a href=&quot;http://InfiniteUlysses.com&quot;&gt;InfiniteUlysses.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/tag/dissertation/&quot;&gt;blogged&lt;/a&gt; throughout the dissertation process. I particularly recommend the linked posts on &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2016/06/14/digital-humanities-dissertation-defense-advice&quot;&gt;defense advice&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2016/06/20/digital-humanities-dissertation-defense-talk&quot;&gt;the actual defense talk&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2014/09/30/evaluating-non-traditional-digital-humanities-dissertations&quot;&gt;evaluating a DH dissertation&lt;/a&gt;, thinking through &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2014/05/27/inclusivityeditioncanon&quot;&gt;diversity and inclusion in your dissertation scholarship&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2014/04/28/affinitywallarticle&quot;&gt;planning out the many pieces of a dissertation project&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://literaturegeek.com/2014/04/02/digitaldissformat&quot;&gt;choosing the best format (chapters? something else?) for your scholarship&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 26 Feb 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/02/26/digital-humanities-dissertation-starter-kit</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/02/26/digital-humanities-dissertation-starter-kit</guid>
        
        <category>digital-humanities</category>
        
        <category>advice-tutorial</category>
        
        <category>dissertation</category>
        
        <category>grad-advice</category>
        
        <category>meta-dh</category>
        
        <category>dh-now</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
